<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="freesoftware"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>How does Free Software affect Linux?</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The Linux OS has become increasingly popular mainly due to the
    freedom it allows (and of course also the low or zero-fee price of the
    entire operating system). In this chapter we see how these freedoms come
    to life and how they are protected and sustained.</para>

    <para>We also take a look at the development model used by free software
    projects in general because it is a major result of said freedoms, one
    that makes free software projects often more interesting than
    closed-source commercial software projects. The development model is also
    one of the major strengths of free software.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Free Software</title>

    <para>If we take a step back from all technical aspects, Linux differs
    from the closed-source commercial software in an important aspect:
    licensing. Licensing is what drives free software...</para>

    <section>
      <title>What are Software Licenses?</title>

      <para>Software is someone's intellectual property. Intellectual
      property<indexterm>
          <primary>intellectual property</primary>
        </indexterm> is a heavy word that shouldn't be interpreted to anything
      else than the result of some effort to create something that is not a
      plain copy. If you write some text, the resulting text is your
      intellectual property (unless you've copied it from somewhere).</para>

      <para>Intellectual property is protected by law. Copyright<indexterm>
          <primary>copyright</primary>
        </indexterm> protects your intellectual property by prohibiting others
      to copy, adapt, reproduce and/or redistribute your ``thing'' without
      your consent. Mind you though that not every intellectual property is
      copyright protected and copyright differs from country to country. An
      example of intellectual property that isn't copyright protected is a
      mathematical method: even though the inventor of the method had to
      ponder years and years on it, his method isn't copyright protected (but
      if he wrote a text about this method, the text itself is). Copyright is
      automatically assigned: it doesn't cost you anything and it is broadly
      accepted.</para>

      <para>Another protection is a patent<indexterm>
          <primary>patent</primary>
        </indexterm>. Patents are (or should be) granted to new inventions who
      are not known to the public at the time of the patent request. Patents
      are often used to protect intellectual property that isn't protected by
      the copyright: methods for doing stuff (including medical compositions).
      Sadly, the industry is often abusing patents for much more when they
      have a patent with a broad action field: the patent covers too much,
      allowing the company to force others not to use a method they actually
      do have the right to use. Also, both the request and the patent grant
      are very costly and only larger companies have the abilities to obtain
      (and protect) several patents. Smaller companies or individuals don't
      have the means to obtain a patent, let alone protect themselves in a
      court because they might have used a method that is described in one or
      more patents.</para>

      <para>I use the word <emphasis>abuse</emphasis> because companies often
      get patents for methods that are broadly used or are so silly that you'd
      wonder what patent office (patent requests are - or should be - checked
      for their validity before they are granted) has granted those
      patents.</para>

      <para>I'll abstain from elaborating on this (politically sensitive)
      topic more and move on to <emphasis>software
      licenses</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>software license</primary>
        </indexterm>. A software license is a contract between you, the
      software user, and the software copyright owner. It tells you what you
      can and cannot do with the software. Any software that is not licensed
      is fully copyright protected, meaning you shouldn't even have it, let
      alone run it.</para>

      <para>Most commercial-grade licenses are often called the
      EULAs<indexterm>
          <primary>EULA</primary>
        </indexterm>, or End User License Agreements. They usually say what
      you are allowed to do with the software (often including what you are
      allowed to use the software for). The EULAs more often stress what is
      denied rather than allow anything. One of the many topics is
      redistribution of the software. Most EULAs explicitly disallow
      redistribution.</para>

      <para>Linux (and free software in general) is different. The
      accompanying license grants you the right to copy the software, obtain
      the source code, modify it and redistribute it (with or without
      modifications) and even sell it. Because there are many variations
      possible there are many popular licenses.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>What Licenses Exist?</title>

      <para>I'll list a few of the more popular licenses here, but be advised,
      there are more than 800 licenses around. Many of those licenses are
      quite similar (or are exactly the same) and the free software community
      should start to consolidate all those licenses in a much smaller set.
      Sadly, they haven't done so yet. Luckily, the 90-10 rule here applies:
      90% of all free software uses 10% of the free software (or other)
      licenses. The other licenses are only marginally used, sometimes just
      for a single application.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Public Domain</title>

        <para>When software is placed under the public domain, you're free to
        do whatever you want with it: the author waves any right he can to
        allow for full freedom of his software.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>MIT License and some BSD-like Licenses</title>

        <para>The MIT license and some BSD-like licenses are almost like the
        public domain, but ask you to keep the copyright notice intact. This
        is a very popular license because the author allows you to do whatever
        you want as long as you keep his name on the product copyright notice
        as well.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>GPL</title>

        <para>The GNU Public License<indexterm>
            <primary>GPL</primary>
          </indexterm> is the most widely used free software license, but for
        some people also the most restrictive free software license. The GPL
        tells you that you can do whatever you want with the software, as long
        as you provide the source code of your modifications to whoever you
        distributed the modified version to and as long as this modification
        is under the GPL as well.</para>

        <para>The Linux kernel is GPL licensed.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>OSI Approved Licenses</title>

        <para>An OSI approved license is a license that adheres to the
        <emphasis>Open Source Definition</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>Open Source Definition</primary>
          </indexterm> written down by the <emphasis>Open Source
        Initiative</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>Open Source Initiative</primary>
          </indexterm><indexterm>
            <primary>OSI</primary>
          </indexterm> of which the following points are a free
        interpretation:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>free redistribution</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>source code available</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>modifications are allowed (including redistribution)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>no discrimination (people, fields ...)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>FSF Approved Licenses</title>

        <para>An FSF<indexterm>
            <primary>FSF</primary>
          </indexterm> approved license adheres to the <emphasis>Free Software
        </emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>free software</primary>
          </indexterm>definition written down by the <emphasis>Free Software
        Foundation</emphasis> of which the following points are the core of
        the definition:</para>

        <para>You should be free to ...</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>run the program for any purpose</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>study how the program works and adapt it to your
            needs</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>redistribute copies</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>improve the program and release your changes to the
            public</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Free Software isn't Non-Commercial</title>

      <para>Free software is often perceived to be a pure hobbyist project: it
      would not be commercially viable to bring free software to the
      enterprise world. After all, if software is freely available, what kind
      of profit could a company make from it. Nothing could be further from
      the truth...</para>

      <para>It is true that free software requires a different look on
      software in a commercial environment (including companies). Companies
      who <emphasis>use</emphasis> software want to be assured that they have
      support for the software when things go wrong. They often close (costly)
      support contracts with the software company where service level
      agreements (abbreviated to SLAs) are defined. Based on these contracts,
      the company has the assurance that if certain services become
      unavailable, the supporting company will do whatever it can to bring the
      service back or, in some occasions, compensate the financial damage that
      the downfall has caused.</para>

      <para>Most of the time, these support contracts are closed with the
      software company itself because it has the most knowledge of the
      software (as it is probably the only company with access to the software
      code). Sadly, as good as this reason is, companies don't look at free
      software ``because there is no support''. This isn't true; support for
      free software is still (commercially) available, but most of the time
      not from the creators themselves. And although this scares the
      companies, the reason why this support is still as good as with
      off-the-shelf software remains the same: the supporting company has
      access to the source code of the tool and has professional knowledge
      about the tool. It probably has developers in the software project
      itself.</para>

      <para>Companies that <emphasis>sell</emphasis> software are of course
      often against free software. When these companies major income depends
      on the sales of their software, it would not be viable to make the
      software free. If they would, competing companies would have full access
      to the source code and improve their own product with it.</para>

      <para>I don't think this is a disadvantage though. Software companies
      should use their main strength: knowledge about the tool. As mentioned
      before, other companies often want to close support contracts to ensure
      the service that the software delivers; if the software company creates
      free software, this wouldn't change. For many software companies,
      support contracts are the main source of income.</para>

      <para>It is still possible to sell free software; some pioneering
      companies are payed to made modifications to free software because
      companies don't have the resources to do so themselves. These companies
      can keep the modifications private if the free software license allows
      this) but can also bring these modifications to the public by
      contributing it to the software project itself.</para>

      <para>A major proof of this is the acceptance of free software by major
      software players such as Sun Microsystems and IBM, and the emergence of
      new software players that build their business upon free software, such
      as RedHat or MySQL<indexterm>
          <primary>MySQL</primary>
        </indexterm> (recently acquired by Sun Microsystems). The latter
      company uses a dual-licensed software approach: the MySQL source code is
      available in two licenses, a free software one for the public and a more
      closed one for companies who want support from MySQL itself. Using a
      dual-licensed approach allows the company to support a fixed state of
      their product while keeping the software free. Supporting a fixed state
      of the product is of course much easier than to support the software in
      general.</para>

      <para>However, don't think that every free software project is
      enterprise-ready or that you will be able to find (paid) support for
      every software project. You should carefully check out every software
      title you want to use if you want to use software, free or not. For end
      users, distributions help you to pick software. If a distribution
      packages a certain software title, it feels that the software title is
      stable and well supported.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>So Linux is Free?</title>

      <para>Yes, Linux is free. It is certainly free in the sense of ``free
      speech'' and although most software titles are also free in the sense of
      ``free beer'', you shouldn't be surprised to see distributions you can
      or have to pay for. In that case, you can be paying for the software
      medium (the burned DVD), accompanying printed documentation, 30-day
      installation and usage support or for the resources that the
      distribution has to acquire itself (like infrastructure).</para>

      <para>Most distributions have free downloads with online documentation
      and wonderful community support (active mailing lists or Internet fora),
      which is why Linux is that popular: you can download, install and use
      several distributions to decide which one is best for you. You can try
      the software (without loosing any functionality) and you don't even have
      to pay for it to continue using it (as is the case with
      shareware<indexterm>
          <primary>shareware</primary>
        </indexterm>). Gentoo is one of those distribution projects. Such
      distributions get their financial backing (for infrastructure and
      organisational needs, including juridical support and bureaucratic
      paperwork) from user donations or sales of pressed DVDs. Companies also
      tend to support distributions financially or with hardware / bandwidth
      donations.</para>

      <para>Some distributions are only available when you pay for it. In that
      case you often pay for the support or for additional software in the
      distribution which isn't freely available. A popular distribution is
      RedHat Enterprise Linux, a Linux distribution specifically targeting
      companies who want to set up Linux servers. You don't just pay for the
      support, but also for the resources that RedHat has put in the
      distribution to make it certified for other software (such as Oracle and
      SAP) so that you can run (with support from the software company) this
      software on your RHEL installations.</para>

      <para>It is important however to understand that distribution projects
      only develop a very small part of the software that you install on your
      system. Most software comes from other free software projects and these
      projects often don't get gifts from the distribution projects.
      Nonetheless they do face the same problems as any other (larger) free
      software project: bureaucratic paperwork, juridical support,
      infrastructure needs, ... So it comes to no surprise that these projects
      also have the same income streams as the distribution projects: user
      gifts, commercial sponsorship and software / support sales.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Development Model</title>

    <para>Due to the nature of free software projects, you'll find that it has
    quite some differences with closed-source commercial, off the shelf
    software...</para>

    <section>
      <title>Multi-Project Development</title>

      <para>One distribution provides an aggregation of software. Each of
      those software titles is built by a software project which usually
      differs from the distribution project. Hence, when you install a
      distribution on your system, it contains software from hundreds of
      software projects around the world.</para>

      <para>So to obtain support for a flaw you found, or an issue you come
      across, the first place to seek support would be the distribution, but
      chances are that the distribution will put the support question
      <emphasis>upstream</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>upstream</primary>
        </indexterm>, meaning that it forwards the request to the software
      project that develops the software you have an issue with.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Transparent Development</title>

      <para>Free software is usually developed transparently: if you are
      interested in the development of your favourite software title, you can
      quickly find out how its development works and how to
      participate.</para>

      <para>Usually, software projects use a <emphasis>concurrent versions
      system</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>concurrent versions system</primary>
        </indexterm> such as CVS<indexterm>
          <primary>CVS</primary>
        </indexterm> or SVN<indexterm>
          <primary>SVN</primary>
        </indexterm> to keep the source code in. Such systems allow for dozens
      (or even hundreds) of developers to work on the same source code
      simultaneously and keep track of all changes that have happened (so they
      can easily be reverted). This isn't just for free software projects -
      almost all software projects use such a system. However, free software
      projects usually allow non-developers to see the progress of the
      development by giving them read-only access to the system. This way, you
      can track every change to the software personally.</para>

      <para>To discuss the future of the software, or to take software design
      decisions, most free software projects can't use real-life meetings:
      their developers are scattered around the world. A solution to this
      problem are communication systems such as mailing lists, IRC (chat) or
      forums (Internet or Usenet). Most of these communication systems are
      also open for non-developers to participate in the discussions, meaning
      that end users have direct communication with developers.</para>

      <para>The latter has a major advantage: changes requested by the users
      are directly communicated to the developers so that misinterpretation is
      less frequent, allowing for projects to update their software more
      accurate and frequent.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fast Release Cycles</title>

      <para>Larger free software projects have hundreds of contributors and
      several dozens of developers. Those developers are very motivated to
      work on the software by passion. If they weren't, they wouldn't be
      working on the software as there usually is no other incentive to work
      for (such as a nice pay check) although it must be said that there are
      software projects (and they aren't small in numbers) who have paid
      developers as well. As a result, the software is quickly progressing and
      new features are added quickly (some projects even have new features on
      an almost daily basis).</para>

      <para>To make sure that new features and fixes are tested properly,
      software development snapshots are communicated to a broad community of
      testers and stable snapshots are often released to the general public as
      a new release of the software. Different release types are commonly used
      in free software environments:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>nightly snapshots</emphasis><indexterm>
              <primary>release</primary>

              <secondary>nightly snapshot</secondary>
            </indexterm> are extracts of the source code at a certain period
          in time which are built and put online for everyone to use. These
          releases are automatically generated and are bleeding-edge as they
          represent the state of the software title only a few moments ago.
          They are highly experimental and only meant for developers or
          experienced contributors</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>development releases</emphasis> are intermediate
          releases, similar to nightly snapshots, but somewhat more
          coordinated by the developers. They usually have a
          ChangeLog<indexterm>
              <primary>ChangeLog</primary>
            </indexterm> which lists the changes in it since the previous
          release. Such releases are meant for experienced contributors and
          testers who don't mind the software to be broken from time to
          time.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>beta releases</emphasis><indexterm>
              <primary>release</primary>

              <secondary>beta</secondary>
            </indexterm> contain a preliminary vision of how the final release
          will look like. It might not be fully stable or complete but
          individuals who don't participate in the frequent tests can try and
          see if the new release would still work for them and contain the
          fixes they requested. Beta releases are also important for
          distributions as they can now start developing packages for the
          software so that they are ready when the final release of the
          software is made.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>release candidates</emphasis><indexterm>
              <primary>release</primary>

              <secondary>candidate</secondary>
            </indexterm> are proposals for final releases. They contain the
          software such as the developers would like to release it. They now
          wait for a certain period so that the testers and general public can
          run their tests to ensure no bugs are in it any more. New features
          aren't added to the software now, only bug fixes. When no new (or
          major) bugs are found, the release candidate is converted to a new
          release</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>stable release</emphasis><indexterm>
              <primary>release</primary>

              <secondary>stable</secondary>
            </indexterm> are the final releases of the entire development
          process. These releases are now used by the users and distributions
          and the entire development process can start over.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Stable releases also tend to be released in specific gradations,
      reflected by their version number. A popular numbering scheme is x.y.z
      where:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>x is the major version; this version number is only updated
          when the software has been substantially changed. Often such
          releases also require all packages that depend on it to be updated
          as well because they might use features or libraries that are
          changed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>y is the minor version; this version number is updated every
          time the software has been updated with lots of new features</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>z is the bugfix version; this version number is updated
          whenever mainly bug fixes have been added to the software</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>As an example I'll list the release dates for the KDE 4.9 release.
      Since KDE is a complete graphical environment its release cycle is
      ``slower'' than others. Yet if you compare it with the release cycle of
      for instance Microsoft Windows its still blazingly fast. Of course, that
      would be like comparing apples with glass...</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>2012-05-30: KDE 4.9 beta1 is released</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2012-06-14: KDE 4.9 beta2 is released</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2012-06-27: KDE 4.9 release candidate 1 is released</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2012-07-11: KDE 4.9 release candidate 2 is released</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2012-08-01: KDE 4.9 released</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2012-09-04: KDE 4.9.1 released</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2012-10-02: KDE 4.9.2 released</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2012-11-06: KDE 4.9.3 released</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2012-12-04: KDE 4.9.4 released</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>2013-01-02: KDE 4.9.5 released</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Just for your information, KDE 4.10 beta 1 is released on November
      21st, 2012, merely 6 months after KDE 4.9's beta release, and KDE 4.10
      (now called "KDE Software Compilation" as the applications for KDE
      themselves are following their own release cycle) has been released on
      February 6th, 2013 - 6 months after KDE 4.9.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Large Documentation Base</title>

      <para>Because the project often can't deliver human, paid support for
      the software, its success is largely based on the documentation the
      project delivers. If the accompanying documentation contains all
      information about the software, experienced or independent users can
      find all user related answers in the documentation.</para>

      <para>Free software projects usually have high profile documentation,
      often better than the online available documentation of closed-source
      off the shelf software. Many larger projects even have all this
      documentation available in several languages. And if you don't find your
      answer in the project documentation, chances are that one or more users
      have written independent guides on the software elsewhere.</para>

      <para>There are many sites on the internet that link to the various
      documentation resources and the same problem as with free software
      itself arises: often you have too many resources making it harder to
      find the correct document to guide you through your end user experience
      of the software. However, unlike the plethora on software titles around
      (making it difficult to find the right software for the right job) it is
      easier for a user to know if documentation is good or not so there is no
      need for a ``documentation distribution''.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Software Life Cycle</title>

      <para>If you buy software of an unknown, smaller company, you have the
      chance that after a number of years, the company doesn't exist any more
      or is taken over and doesn't support that software since. Something
      similar is true with free software: if the project decides that there
      aren't enough resources to continue the development of the software
      (usually due to a shortage on developers) it can stop the development of
      the software, usually resulting in a drop of support from users as
      well.</para>

      <para>However, unlike the case of the software company, the free
      software source code remains available to the public. If you desperately
      need the software to work for you, you can just pick the source code and
      continue the development of it yourself (or pay others to do it for
      you). You're also confident that the software will remain free.</para>

      <para>If at any time all the copyright owners of the free software
      decide that the software falls under a different license which you don't
      agree after, you can take the source code of the moment right before the
      copyright holders decided to switch the licenses and continue the
      development under that license (as that software is still under the
      original license and not the new one). This process (where a group of
      developers disagree with the development plans of the software and start
      a new project based on the same source code) is called
      <emphasis>forking</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>fork</primary>
        </indexterm> the project.</para>

      <para>A well known example of such a fork is the creation of the X.org
      project, a fork of the XFree86 project which at a certain point in time
      decided to change their license. The license change wasn't the only
      reason for that fork: some developers were also unhappy with the
      development policy on new features and the development pace. Both
      projects are currently still around although X.org is now the most
      popular one.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Open Standards</title>

    <para>Because so many projects are involved, it is important that each
    project uses standards as much as possible. Only by complying to open
    standards can projects easily and efficiently work together. Next are a
    few important standards or well perceived specifications in the free
    software world.</para>

    <section xml:id="fhs">
      <title xreflabel="File system Hierarchy Standard">File system
      Hierarchy Standard</title>

      <para>The first standard I discuss is the <emphasis>File system
      Hierarchy Standard</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>File system Hierarchy Standard</primary>
        </indexterm>, abbreviated to FHS<indexterm>
          <primary>FHS</primary>
        </indexterm>. This standard is used by almost all distributions and
      discusses the file locations on a Linux file system. One can read the
      FHS online at <link xl:href="http://www.pathname.com/fhs">
          <uri>http://www.pathname.com/fhs/</uri>
        </link> but many other resources describe the FHS layout as
      well.</para>

      <para>The file system layout for Unix/Linux is quite different from the
      file system layout as seen from within Microsoft Windows. Instead of
      marking partitions by a drive letter, Unix/Linux sees a file system as a
      tree-like structure, starting with a root and building up through
      directories and files. You could say that the branches in the structure
      are the directories and the leaves are the files. If you think you have
      not encountered a Unix/Linux file system before, think again: URLs that
      you use on the Internet are based upon this structure. For instance, the
      URL <link
      xl:href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/faq.xml">http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/faq.xml</link>
      denotes the file called <filename>faq.xml</filename> which can be found
      on the server of <link
      xl:href="http://www.gentoo.org">www.gentoo.org</link>, in the directory
      <filename>/doc/en</filename>. So, / is the root, "doc" is a branch of
      this root and "en" is a branch of "doc".</para>

      <para>Distributions that adhere to the FHS allow their Linux users to
      easily switch between distributions: the file system structure remains
      the same so navigation between folders, device files ... doesn't change.
      It also enables independent packagers to create packages for several
      distributions at once (as long as the distributions use the same package
      format). But foremost, it allows Linux users of one distribution to help
      users of other distributions as there isn't actually any difference
      between their file system layouts.</para>

      <para>The current version of this standard is 2.3, released on January
      29th, 2004.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Linux Standard Base</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>Linux Standard Base</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>Linux Standard Base</primary>
        </indexterm>, or LSB<indexterm>
          <primary>LSB</primary>
        </indexterm> sets the layout, binary compatibility, required
      libraries, required commands and more for a Linux operating system. If a
      distribution adheres to the LSB standard it can install, run and
      maintain LSB compliant (software) packages.</para>

      <para>Distributions should adhere to the LSB if they want to ensure that
      they don't deviate from a good Linux standard. As a consequence, the LSB
      is an effort to ensure that distributions stay similar with regards to
      libraries, commands ... or in overall, user experience. It is a good
      effort to ensure that no fragmentation occurs in the Linux world.</para>

      <para>Because the LSB is a broad standard, it comprises of other
      standards, including the aforementioned FHS but also the
      <emphasis>Single Unix Specification</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>Single Unix Specification</primary>
        </indexterm> (SUS<indexterm>
          <primary>SUS</primary>
        </indexterm>) which defines how a Unix system should be. However, one
      cannot say that his Linux operating system is Unix because he would need
      to certify the OS (which requires serious financial support) and this
      certification wouldn't last long because the Linux OS changes
      often.</para>

      <para>One of LSBs' largest advantages is that ISVs (Independent Software
      Vendors) such as Oracle, IBM, Sybase ... can package their software in
      an LSB-compatible software package which can then be installed on any
      LSB-compliant distribution.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Free Desktop Specifications</title>

      <para>On <uri>http://www.freedesktop.org</uri> you'll find a set of
      desktop specifications that are well known in the free software
      community. Although they aren't standards (as freedesktop<indexterm>
          <primary>freedesktop</primary>
        </indexterm> is no standards body and the specifications haven't been
      converted into OASIS or ISO standards) many distributions adhere to
      them.</para>

      <para>These specifications define how menu entries are created and
      maintained, where icons should reside, but also how drag and drop
      between different libraries (most notably Qt<indexterm>
          <primary>Qt</primary>
        </indexterm> and GTK+<indexterm>
          <primary>GTK+</primary>
        </indexterm>, the graphical libraries for KDE and GNOME) should be
      made possible.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Exercises</title>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>What is the difference between GPLv2 and GPLv3?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Part of LSBs standard is the ELF or Executable and Linking
        Format, the binary format for executable, compiled code used by
        various Linux/Unix distributions. Can you find other operating systems
        that support the ELF format beyond Linux/Unix?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Some people see fast releases as a weakness in the free software
        community: users are "forced" to upgrade their software more often and
        even though it is free, it still takes time (and sometimes headaches)
        to upgrade the software this often. Some distributions tend to help
        those users by offering stable (both in stability and in version
        releases) software only. How is this possible?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>How is it possible that many distributions allow you to upgrade
        to the latest version without needing an installation CD or
        re-installation from scratch?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Further Resources</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link
        xl:href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/cathedral-bazaar/">The
        Cathedral and The Bazaar</link>, by Eric Steven Raymond - an essay on
        two different development models used in the Free Software
        community.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link xl:href="http://www.ffii.org">Foundation for a Free
        Information Infrastructure</link>, a NPO dedicated to establishing a
        free market in information technology.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link
        xl:href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/fighting-software-patents.html">Fighting
        Software Patents</link>, by Richard Stallman - GNUs vision on
        software patents.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
