<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Working with Processes</title>

  <section>
    <title>Process Trees</title>

    <section>
      <title>Parent and Child Relationships</title>

      <para>Each Linux (and Unix) process has a parent (except for the top
      process) and can have one or more childs. The relationship is crafted
      when a process is launched: the process that launched the new process
      becomes the parent of that process. As a user, you might not know what
      process you are currently working in. Every program is a process, being
      it the shell you're typing the commands in or the graphical environment
      you're working with.</para>

      <para>For instance, a user who has a terminal open can have the
      following process structure for this terminal:</para>

      <programlisting>init
`- xterm
   `- bash</programlisting>

      <para>You can obtain a tree of running processes using the
      <command>pstree</command> command:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>pstree</command>
init-+-acpid
     |-4*[agetty]
     |-agiletrack---java---19*[{java}]
     |-apache2---8*[apache2]
     |-bonobo-activati---{bonobo-activati}
     |-5*[dbus-daemon]
     |-dhcpcd
     |-gconfd-2
     |-gnome-keyring-d
     |-gnome-power-man
     |-gnome-screensav
     |-gnome-settings----{gnome-settings-}
     |-4*[gnome-vfs-daemo]
     |-gnome-volume-ma
     |-gpg-agent
     |-hald---hald-runner-+-hald-addon-acpi
     |                    |-hald-addon-cpuf
     |                    `-hald-addon-stor
     |-java---15*[{java}]
     |-login---bash---startx---xinit-+-X
     |                               `-gnome-session-+-gnome-panel
     |                                               |-metacity
     |                                               |-nautilus
     |                                               `-{gnome-session}
[...]</programlisting>

      <para>Now, not every process launched immediately becomes a child of the
      process where it was launched from. Some processes might immediately
      become child of the root process, most often called
      <command>init</command><indexterm>
          <primary>init</primary>
        </indexterm>. The root process is the first process launched by the
      kernel when it boots up. It is responsible for running the necessary
      startup services and prepare the system for its duties.</para>

      <para>Processes that become child of the root process usually do this
      because they don't want to be terminated when their parent process exits
      or dies: when this happens, the child processes become orphaned and the
      init process will terminate these processes as well. So, becoming a
      child of the init process will ensure that the process remains
      available. In the above example you'll find a good example: the
      <command>dhcpcd</command> command governs the IP address of the network
      interface through the DHCP protocol. If the process didn't continuously
      run, your IP address would be dismissed after a few minutes (or
      hours).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Process Ownership</title>

      <para>When a process is launched (usually through a command the user
      entered) it, by default, obtains the user id and group id of its parent
      process. When a user logs on to the system, the <command>login</command>
      process launches a shell process with the user id and group id of the
      user that logged on, so every command the user launches takes the user
      id and group id of that user, since the parent process of every launched
      command is either the beforementioned shell process or one of its child
      processes.</para>

      <para>Some processes however explicitly ask the Linux kernel to use a
      different user id and group id. This is accomplished by setting the
      <emphasis>setuid</emphasis> or <emphasis>setgid</emphasis> flags on the
      process file itself. With <emphasis>setuid</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>setuid</primary>
        </indexterm> (set user id) and <emphasis>setgid</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>setgid</primary>
        </indexterm> (set group id) the owner of the process is the owner of
      the file rather than the user that launched the process.</para>

      <para>An example is the <command>passwd</command> command, used to
      change the password of a user:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>ls -l /bin/passwd</command>
-rws--x--x 1 root root  28956 Jul 15  2007 passwd</programlisting>

      <para>As you can see, the command file itself is owned by root. It also
      has the setuid bit set (see the s in <filename>-rws--x--x</filename>).
      If a user runs the <command>passwd</command> command, the command itself
      has root privileges rather than the privileges for the user. For the
      <command>passwd</command> command, this is necessary because it needs to
      update the password files (<filename>/etc/passwd</filename> and
      <filename>/etc/shadow</filename>) which are only writeable by the root
      user (the <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file is not even readable for
      regular users).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Viewing Process Information</title>

      <para>Various tools exist to obtain process information. The next few
      chapters give a nice overview of these tools...</para>

      <section>
        <title>Process Lists</title>

        <para>The main program to create a process list is the
        <command>ps</command> command. If ran inside a shell, it shows the
        processes that are running inside the session (meaning the processes
        launched from the shell, including the shell itself):</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>ps</command>
  PID TTY          TIME CMD
24064 pts/3    00:00:00 bash
24116 pts/3    00:00:00 ps</programlisting>

        <para>The columns shown are:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>PID - process id of the process</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>TTY - controlling terminal (this is Unix inheritage where
            users were logged on through terminals, pts is a
            pseudoterminal)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>TIME - the execution time the process took. In the above
            example, both commands hardly took any CPU time on the system
            (bash is the shell, which is most of the time waiting for input so
            not consuming any CPU time, the other one is ps which gave its
            results in less than a second)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>CMD - the process name itself (the command)</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>Of course, several arguments to ps exist which change its
        behavior. For instance, with <command>ps -e</command> you see the same
        information, but for all processes runnin on the system. With
        <command>ps -f</command> a few more columns are added, including the
        parent process id and the time the process started.</para>

        <para>You can also limit the processes to see based on the user
        (<command>ps -u username</command>), command name (<command>ps -C
        command</command>), really running processes (taking cpu time at the
        moment: <command>ps -r</command>) and more. For more information, see
        the ps manual page.</para>

        <para>Another command that is often used to obtain process list
        information is the <command>top</command> program. The top command is
        an interactive command that shows you a process list, sorted by one or
        more values (default is CPU usage) and refreshes this list every 5
        seconds (this is of course configurable):</para>

        <programlisting>top - 10:19:47 up 6 days,  6:41,  5 users,  load average: 1.00, 1.27, 0.92
Tasks: 120 total,   1 running, 119 sleeping,   0 stopped,   0 zombie
Cpu(s):  3.2%us,  0.7%sy,  0.0%ni, 95.6%id,  0.3%wa,  0.1%hi,  0.0%si,  0.0%st
Mem:   1545408k total,  1490968k used,    54440k free,   177060k buffers
Swap:  2008084k total,      132k used,  2007952k free,   776060k cached

  PID USER      PR  NI  VIRT  RES  SHR S %CPU %MEM    TIME+  COMMAND
 4458 haldaemo  16   0  5488 3772 2388 S  2.0  0.2   4:23.69 hald
27255 swift     15   0  2272 1064  768 R  2.0  0.1   0:00.01 top
    1 root      15   0  1612  544  468 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.48 init
    2 root      12  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.00 kthreadd
    3 root      39  19     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.45 ksoftirqd/0
    4 root      10  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:01.95 events/0
    5 root      10  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.00 khelper
   60 root      10  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.00 kblockd/0
   61 root      11  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:25.77 kacpid
   62 root      11  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:09.60 kacpi_notify
  171 root      10  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.00 ata/0
  172 root      10  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.00 ata_aux
  173 root      10  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.00 ksuspend_usbd
  176 root      10  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.00 khubd
  178 root      10  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.01 kseriod
  196 root      10  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:01.13 kswapd0
  197 root      20  -5     0    0    0 S  0.0  0.0   0:00.00 aio/0</programlisting>

        <para>There is plenty of information in the top screen...</para>

        <programlisting>top - 10:19:47 up 6 days,  6:41,  5 users,  load average: 1.00, 1.27, 0.92</programlisting>

        <para>The first line shows you the uptime of the system (this system
        is running for 6 days, 6 hours and 41 minutes), the number of logged
        on users (beware, this is not the number of different users - if a
        user launches 3 xterms inside a graphical session he will be shown as
        four logged on users) and the load average.</para>

        <para>The load average is something many people misinterprete. The
        load average shows the number of processes that were running or asking
        for CPU time during the given interval. In the above example, this
        means that:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>in the last minute, an average of 1 process was asking for
            or using CPU time</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>in the last 5 minutes, an average of 1.27 processes were
            asking for or using CPU time</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>in the last 15 minutes, an average of 0.92 processes were
            asking for or using CPU time</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>For a single CPU system, you most likely don't want a number
        higher than 1 in the long run (for instance, the 15-minute span). The
        more CPUs, the higher the load average can become.</para>

        <programlisting>Tasks: 120 total,   1 running, 119 sleeping,   0 stopped,   0 zombie</programlisting>

        <para>The number of processes running on this system (120) of which
        119 are sleeping (not performing any duties), 1 running (the top
        command itself), 0 stopped (a process in the stopped state can still
        be revived but is, at this moment, not accepting input or performing
        any tasks) and 0 zombie.</para>

        <para>A zombie process is not really a real process: the process
        itself has already finished, but its parent process doesn't know this
        yet, so the kernel is keeping some process information until the
        parent process asks for the child process state.</para>

        <programlisting>Cpu(s):  3.2%us,  0.7%sy,  0.0%ni, 95.6%id,  0.3%wa,  0.1%hi,  0.0%si,  0.0%st</programlisting>

        <para>CPU state information, showing the CPU usage percentages: user
        processes (us), system/kernel CPU usage (sy), niced processes (ni),
        idle CPU (id), waiting for I/O (wa), hardware interrupts (hi),
        software interrupts (si) and virtual cpu stealing (st).</para>

        <para>Most of the states are self-explanatory. The niced processes is
        for processes the user reniced and is a subset of the user processes
        percentage. The virtual CPU stealing is the percentage of time a
        virtual CPU waits for a real CPU and is not interesting for regular
        Linux/Unix users (as they don't work with virtualization).</para>

        <programlisting>Mem:   1545408k total,  1490968k used,    54440k free,   177060k buffers
Swap:  2008084k total,      132k used,  2007952k free,   776060k cached</programlisting>

        <para>Memory usage: of the 1.5 Gbyte of memory available, 1.45Gbyte is
        in use and 54Mbyte is free. Of the used memory, 177 Mbyte is used by
        the kernel for internal buffers. Also, 776 Mbyte of the used memory
        actually consists out of cached data which can potentially be cleared
        if a process would require more memory than currently
        available.</para>

        <para>The swap space itself is hardly used: of the 2Gbyte of swap
        space defined, only 132 kbyte is in use.</para>

        <programlisting>  PID USER      PR  NI  VIRT  RES  SHR S %CPU %MEM    TIME+  COMMAND
 4458 haldaemo  16   0  5488 3772 2388 S  2.0  0.2   4:23.69 hald
...</programlisting>

        <para>The rest of the screen gives the process listing itself. The
        columns shown are:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Process ID (PID) of the process</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Username (USER) showing the owner of the process</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Priority value (PR) of the process (the higher the value,
            the higher the priority). Priorities are exclusively determined by
            the Linux kernel.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nice value (NI) of the process (is a user sets a nice value,
            or renices a tool, it tells the Linux kernel how "nice" the
            program is - the higher the nice value, the nicer it is so
            (generally) the lower the priority should be).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The virtual memory (VIRT) the process is occupying. This
            includes the memory it is actually using, mapped memory from
            devices, files mapped into memory and shared memory.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The resident (really used) memory (RES) the process is
            using.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The amount of possibly shared memory (SHR). It is "possibly"
            because the memory is shareable, but not automatically used by
            others already.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Process state (S), which can be any of S (sleeping), R
            (running), D (uninterruptible sleep), T (traced or stopped) or Z
            (zombie).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>CPU usage (%CPU)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Memory usage (%MEM - based on RES)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Runtime (TIME+)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Command (COMMAND)</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Process Information</title>

        <para>You can also be interested in more detailed process information
        such as the files (or connections) the process has currently
        open.</para>

        <para>With <command>lsof</command><indexterm>
            <primary>lsof</primary>
          </indexterm> you can view this information. Just give the process id
        with it (lsof -p PID) and you get all this information. However, lsof
        can do much more. For instance, with lsof you can see what process is
        listening on a particular port:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>lsof -i :443</command>
COMMAND   PID   USER   FD   TYPE DEVICE SIZE NODE NAME
apache2  4346   root    3u  IPv4  11484       TCP *:https (LISTEN)</programlisting>

        <para>Another tool that can do the same is
        <command>fuser</command><indexterm>
            <primary>fuser</primary>
          </indexterm>:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>fuser -v 443/tcp</command>
                     USER        PID ACCESS COMMAND
443/tcp:             root       4346 F.... apache2</programlisting>

        <para>The same can be accomplished with files. For instance, to see
        what processes are using a particular file with fuser, just give the
        filename (<command>fuser -v /path/to/file</command>).</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Backgrounding Processes</title>

      <para>Processes can be started in the background, either because the
      process immediately detaches it from the running session (daemons) or
      because the user asks to run it in the background.</para>

      <para>Daemons<indexterm>
          <primary>daemon</primary>
        </indexterm> are processes that do not stay in the running session.
      The moment you launch a daemon process, you immediately get your prompt
      back as if the process has finished. However, this isn't true: the
      process is still running, but it is running in the background. Most
      daemons do not have the possibility to reattach to the session. Wether
      or not a process is a daemon depends on the process itself as this is a
      pure programmatical decision.</para>

      <para>Backgrounded processes however are processes that stay in the
      running session, but do not "lock" the input devices (keyboard). As a
      result, the user gets the prompt back and can continue launching other
      processes or do other tasks. To background a process, a user can add a
      "&amp;" sign at the end of the command line. For instance, to put the
      command "eix-update" in the background:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>eix-update &amp;</command></programlisting>

      <para>You can see what processes are running in your session in the
      background using the <command>jobs</command><indexterm>
          <primary>jobs</primary>
        </indexterm> command:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>jobs</command>
[1]- Running           eix-update &amp;</programlisting>

      <para>You can put a job back into the foreground using the
      <command>fg</command><indexterm>
          <primary>fg</primary>
        </indexterm> command. If you just enter fg, it'll put the last job put
      in the background back. If you want to select a different job, use the
      number that jobs returned. For instance, to return the 3rd job back to
      the foreground:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>fg %3</command></programlisting>

      <para>If you want to put a process that you are running in the
      background, use Ctrl-Z to put the process in the background. Ctrl-Z also
      pauzes the process, so if you want to continue the process in the
      background, enter "<command>bg</command>" afterwards as well:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>eix-update</command>
(...)
(Press <command>Ctrl-Z</command>)
[1]+ Stopped         eix-update
# <command>bg</command>
[1]+ eix-update &amp;</programlisting>

      <para>There are a few things you must keep in mind when using
      jobs:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A (non-daemon) process is attached to a running session. The
          moment you terminate your session, all jobs that were running in
          that session (both foreground and background processes) are
          terminated as well.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Although processes can be ran in the background, their output
          is still forwarded to your terminal. If you do not want this, you
          can redirect the output of a command using the &gt; redirect. For
          instance, to redirect the standard output (default - 1) of
          update-eix to a logfile and do the same for the error output
          (2):</para>

          <programlisting># <command>eix-update &gt; /var/tmp/update-eix.log 2&gt;&amp;1 &amp;</command></programlisting>

          <para>Another popular redirect is to ignore output
          completely:</para>

          <programlisting># <command>eix-update &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1 &amp;</command></programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Process Behavior</title>

    <para>Programs are most often launched when a user selects a tool or
    executes a command. They can also be invoked automatically by a running
    program or by the Linux kernel (although the init tool is probably the
    only one ever invoked by the kernel autonomously).</para>

    <para>The next few sections give pointers on process behavior and how you
    can modify it (if appropriate).</para>

    <section>
      <title>Command Return Codes</title>

      <para>The simplest example of launching a program is a simple command
      you enter in the command line. Once the program has finished, it leaves
      behind its <emphasis>return code</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>return code</primary>
        </indexterm> (or <emphasis>exit code</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>exit code</primary>
        </indexterm>) informing you how well it did its job.</para>

      <para>A returncode is always an integer in the range of 0 to 255. Some
      programs might attempt to return a code larger than 255 (or even
      negative). Although not technically restricted, this is not a good idea
      as some applications only expect a returncode between 0 to 255 and might
      even "wrap" return codes to this range. If a program would ever have a
      return code of 512 for instance, it might be mapped into 0.</para>

      <para>Every program that has succesfully finished its job will (or
      should) return code 0. A non-zero return code means that the application
      has failed to finish its tasks (completely).</para>

      <para>Inside any POSIX-compliant shell (POSIX has a standard for Unix
      environments, including how a shell should function) such as
      <command>ksh</command> or <command>bash</command> you can obtain the
      return code of the last command using <filename>$?</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>ls -l</command>
...
$ <command>echo $?</command>
0
$ <command>ls -z</command>
ls: invalid option -- z
Try `ls --help' for more information
$ <command>echo $?</command>
2</programlisting>

      <para>These return codes are important as they are the means to
      investigate if all commands went succesfully or not, allowing you to
      write quite intelligent shell scripts which trigger several commands and
      include logic to handle command failures.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Priority and Niceness</title>

      <para>On Linux, you can't set the priority of a process yourself: the
      Linux kernel does that for you, based on information about the process
      itself, including but not limited to if the process is I/O-bound (as
      such programs are most of the time user-interactive), its previous CPU
      consumation, possible locks it is holding and more.</para>

      <para>You can, however, inform the kernel on what you think the process'
      priority ought to be. For this, you can set a
      <emphasis>nice</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>nice value</primary>
        </indexterm> value for the application. The value, in the range of -20
      to 10, informs the Linux kernel about how nice the program should be
      towards the rest of the system. Negative numbers (-1 to -20) are not
      that nice; the Linux kernel will thus assign those a larger time slice
      and you'll notice that such programs usually get a higher priority.
      However, only the root user can assign a negative nice number to a
      program. Positive numbers (1 to 19) make a process more nice to the
      system; they will receive a lower time slice and usually a lower
      priority.</para>

      <para>Thanks to this system you can launch long-lasting, non-interactive
      commands in the background without worrying about the inpact to your
      interactive user experience. The <command>nice</command><indexterm>
          <primary>nice</primary>

          <secondary>tool</secondary>
        </indexterm> tool allows you to start up a command with a particular
      nice value.</para>

      <para>For instance, to start a Gentoo system upgrade with the highest
      possible nice value (as this is something you usually want to perform in
      the background):</para>

      <programlisting># <command>nice -n 19 emerge -uDN world</command></programlisting>

      <para>If a process is already running, you can change its nice value
      with the renice tool (for instance, to increase the nice value of the
      process with process id 219 with 5):</para>

      <programlisting># <command>renice +5 219</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sending Signals (and Killing Processes)</title>

      <para>Some processes allow you to send certain signals to them. A signal
      is a simple integer between 0 and 64; each of them is also given a
      particular name. The <command>kill</command><indexterm>
          <primary>kill</primary>
        </indexterm> tool can be used to send signals to processes, but also
      to obtain a list of available signals:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>kill -l</command>
 1) SIGHUP       2) SIGINT        3) SIGQUIT      4) SIGILL
 5) SIGTRAP      6) SIGABRT       7) SIGBUS       8) SIGFPE
 9) SIGKILL     10) SIGUSR1      11) SIGSEGV     12) SIGUSR2
13) SIGPIPE     14) SIGALRM      15) SIGTERM     16) SIGSTKFLT
17) SIGCHLD     18) SIGCONT      19) SIGSTOP     20) SIGTSTP
21) SIGTTIN     22) SIGTTOU      23) SIGURG      24) SIGXCPU
25) SIGXFSZ     26) SIGVTALRM    27) SIGPROF     28) SIGWINCH
29) SIGIO       30) SIGPWR       31) SIGSYS      34) SIGRTMIN
35) SIGRTMIN+1  36) SIGRTMIN+2   37) SIGRTMIN+3  38) SIGRTMIN+4
39) SIGRTMIN+5  40) SIGRTMIN+6   41) SIGRTMIN+7  42) SIGRTMIN+8
43) SIGRTMIN+9  44) SIGRTMIN+10  45) SIGRTMIN+11 46) SIGRTMIN+12
47) SIGRTMIN+13 48) SIGRTMIN+14  49) SIGRTMIN+15 50) SIGRTMAX-14
51) SIGRTMAX-13 52) SIGRTMAX-12  53) SIGRTMAX-11 54) SIGRTMAX-10
55) SIGRTMAX-9  56) SIGRTMAX-8   57) SIGRTMAX-7  58) SIGRTMAX-6
59) SIGRTMAX-5  60) SIGRTMAX-4   61) SIGRTMAX-3  62) SIGRTMAX-2
63) SIGRTMAX-1  64) SIGRTMAX</programlisting>

      <para>Its name might already inform you about its usual task: killing
      processes. By default, if you want to terminate a process but you can't
      commicate with the process directly (like hitting "Quit" or "Exit"), you
      should send a signal 15 (SIGTERM<indexterm>
          <primary>SIGTERM</primary>
        </indexterm>) to the program. This is also what
      <command>kill</command> does by default.</para>

      <para>However, if the process doesn't listen to this signal or has gone
      haywire, you can use the SIGKILL signal. The SIGKILL<indexterm>
          <primary>SIGKILL</primary>
        </indexterm> signal doesn't actually reach the application (ever) but
      immediately terminates the process. Its number is 9:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>kill -9 219</command></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Exercises</title>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>How do you obtain the process ID of a running process?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>How can you run a process in background and still be able to
        terminate the session without terminating the process (without the
        process being a daemon)?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>What is a &lt;defunct&gt; process?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Further Resources</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.gnu.org/software/bash/manual/bashref.html#Redirections">Bash
        redirection</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
