<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Hardware Support</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Some hardware is automatically enabled once you have configured it
    inside the Linux kernel: access to PCI chip sets, graphical card, disks,
    USB storage, etc. Yet, most hardware requires additional work. After all,
    the Linux kernel provides you with a programmatic interface to access
    the devices, but you still need the necessary tooling to get the device to
    function properly. Good examples are network cards and printers, but also
    sound cards.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>ALSA - Advanced Linux Sound Architecture</title>

    <para>ALSA<indexterm>
        <primary>ALSA</primary>
      </indexterm> is an open source project that provides audio functionality
    to the Linux kernel. It supports professional audio hardware (next to the
    consumer audio hardware, including sound cards) and provides a powerful,
    standard interface which allows, for instance, multiple software access to
    a single audio device. For programmers, ALSA's API is well documented and
    you'll quickly find that the ALSA library provides thread-safe access to
    the device(s).</para>

    <para>The project also provides tools to manage the audio devices such as
    a simple mixer program (<command>alsamixer</command>), modular sound
    drivers which allow users to fine-tune the drivers' configuration aspects
    and of course support for the older OSS/Free implementation (Linux'
    previous open sound system).</para>

    <section>
      <title>Installing ALSA</title>

      <para>Installing ALSA consists of two distinct steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Configure the Linux kernel with ALSA support and with support
          for your sound card(s)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Install the ALSA utilities</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>If you configure your kernel, you can either opt to install the
      sound card drivers in your kernel or as a kernel module. ALSA's
      configuration utility (<command>alsaconf</command>) assumes that you use
      kernel modules for your sound cards. However, this is not a requirement
      - you can still configure ALSA sound card drivers if they are built
      inside the kernel. The interface to do so however is a bit more
      complex.</para>

      <para>To install the ALSA utilities, it is sufficient to emerge
      alsa-utils:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>emerge alsa-utils</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Basic ALSA Configuration</title>

      <para>The basic ALSA configuration starts with detecting your sound card
      and enabling the channels on it (sound channels) as ALSA will, by
      default, mute the channels (this is for precautionary reasons - you
      don't want to blow your speakers the first time you launch your computer
      do you?).</para>

      <para>The first part (detecting the sound card) can be done using
      <command>alsaconf</command>. The <command>alsaconf</command><indexterm>
          <primary>alsaconf</primary>
        </indexterm> tool will attempt to detect your sound card(s), load the
      necessary modules and configure those with sane settings. It will save
      whatever it found to a general file which is read by your favourite
      distribution (which is undoubtedly Gentoo ;-) at start up so you don't
      have to rerun <command>alsaconf</command> after every boot.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>alsaconf</command></programlisting>

      <para>With your sound card(s) detected, launch
      <command>alsamixer</command> to view the available channels. The
      <command>alsamixer</command><indexterm>
          <primary>alsamixer</primary>
        </indexterm> tool will show you all channels associated with your
      sound card. You will find that, by default, all channels are muted.
      Unmute them, but bring the volume of the channels to a safe setting.
      Don't worry, you can increase them whenever you want later.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>alsamixer</command></programlisting>

      <para>Inside alsamixer, you can</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>move from one channel to the other with the arrow keys
          (left/right)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>increase/decrease the volume of each channel with the arrow
          keys (up/down)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>mute/unmute the channel using the 'M' key</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>exit the application using the Escape key (or Alt+Q)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If your sound card has particular features you can't seem to find
      inside the mixer application, you will need to turn to the
      <command>alsactl</command> command. The
      <command>alsactl</command><indexterm>
          <primary>alsactl</primary>
        </indexterm> utility supports multiple devices and allows you to tweak
      every supported feature of your sound card. Its interface is quite
      simple: use alsactl to dump the sound card information to a file, then
      edit the file to your likings. Once finished, use alsactl to read the
      (modified) file back.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>alsactl -f /path/to/asound.state store</command>
(Now edit /path/to/asound.state)
# <command>alsactl -f /path/to/asound.state restore</command></programlisting>

      <para>If you have changed the file to such an extend that you can't get
      the sound to work again, you can re-initialize the settings using
      <command>alsactl init</command>.</para>

      <para>Finally, if you have multiple devices, use a sequence number to
      identify them. You can find your list of numbers in
      /proc/asound/cards:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>cat /proc/asound/cards</command>
 0 [ICH6           ]: ICH4 - Intel ICH6
                      Intel ICH6 with Cx20468-31 at irq 17</programlisting>

      <para>The number (I only have one card, so mine is 0) can then be passed
      on to the various alsa utilities, like so:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>alsamixer -c 0</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Keeping your Changes</title>

      <para>When you booted your system, you unmuted the channels and set the
      mixer channels according to your likings. However, if you do nothing
      more now, you'll have to redo all this again after every boot. To solve
      this, you need to store the current settings in a state file (yes, using
      alsactl) and automatically read those in at boot time.</para>

      <para>This is exactly what the alsasound init script does (as provided
      by Gentoo's alsa-utils package). So, add alsasound to your boot
      runlevel, save your current settings and then start the initialization
      script:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>rc-update add alsasound boot</command>
# <command>alsactl -f /var/lib/alsa/asound.state store</command>
# <command>/etc/init.d/alsasound start</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using Sound Servers</title>

      <para>I mentioned before that ALSA supports multiple software access to
      a single device. With the above configuration, you're still not able to
      do so. To provide such multiplexing capabilities, you can create a new
      audio device (some sort of mixer) which aggregates information to/from
      the device and sends/reads it from as many software processes as you
      like.</para>

      <para>This is one of the tasks that sound servers do: these programs
      manage access to the sound card (interfaces) and allow multiple software
      processes to use the sound facilities of your system. Some well known
      sound servers are esd, aRTs (deprecated), JACK and PulseAudio.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>esd<indexterm>
              <primary>esd</primary>
            </indexterm> (Enlightenment Sound Daemon) is GNOME's sound
          management daemon. esd, also known as ESounD, not only supports the
          previously mentioned mixing, but can also manage network-transparent
          audio: audio played on one system can be heard on another. To this
          end, any application supporting esd can stream its audio to any
          system running esd on the network.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>aRTs<indexterm>
              <primary>aRTs</primary>
            </indexterm> (Analog RealTime Synthesizer) is KDE's former sound
          daemon. Although development has been abandoned, you will still find
          references to aRTs here and there on the Internet. Its main power
          was its real-time audio streaming capabilities.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>JACK<indexterm>
              <primary>JACK</primary>
            </indexterm> (JACK Audio Connection Kit) is a real-time sound
          server which supports various operating systems (including GNU/Linux
          and Apple's OS X). It also supports network-transparent audio,
          real-time mixing, etc.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>PulseAudio<indexterm>
              <primary>PulseAudio</primary>
            </indexterm> (PulseAudio) is another sound daemon. It is meant to
          be a replacement for esd but with a wider support field (including
          Microsoft Windows and POSIX-compliant operating systems).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If you'd like to use one of these sound servers (you do need to
      pick one if you don't want to get confused), install one of the
      following packages:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>esd can be installed from
          <package>media-sound/esound</package>, although most people will
          already have it installed if they are running GNOME (it is a
          dependency of the GNOME installation)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>JACK can be installed with
          <package>media-sound/jack</package></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>PulseAudio can be installed from
          <package>media-sound/pulseaudio</package>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Enable the corresponding USE flag (esd, jack or pulseaudio) and
      update your system. Portage will automatically rebuild those packages
      that are influenced by the USE flag change and incorporate support for
      the selected sound daemon in those packages:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>nano -w /etc/make.conf</command>
<emphasis>(Edit USE, add the appropriate USE flag)</emphasis>
# <command>emerge --update --deep --newuse world</command></programlisting>

      <para>You can also ask euse which packages are affected by a USE flag
      change:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>euse -I pulseaudio</command></programlisting>

      <para>If you want to know which packages all use a specific USE flag
      (even uninstalled packages), use <command>euse -i</command>:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>euse -i pulseaudio</command></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>CUPS - former "Common Printing Unix System"</title>

    <para>If you need to connect your Linux system to a printer, using the
    CUPS<indexterm>
        <primary>CUPS</primary>
      </indexterm> tool is advised. With CUPS you can both connect to locally
    attached printers (USB, LPT) as well as remote (through Windows sharing or
    IPP). You can also use CUPS to build a print server yourself, although
    this is definitely outside the scope of this book.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Installing CUPS</title>

      <para>Before you start installing the software, you will first need to
      make sure that your kernel configuration supports the printer:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>for locally attached printers using the (old) LPT interface,
          look for "Parallel port support -&gt; PC-style hardware" and
          "Parallel printer support -&gt; IEEE 1284 transfer modes")</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>for locally attached printers using the USB interface, look
          for "USB Printer support" (as well as all other USB-required
          settings such as one of the xHCI supports)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>for remote printers using the Windows sharing
          (SMB-CIFS<indexterm>
              <primary>SMB-CIFS</primary>
            </indexterm> protocol), look for "Network File Systems -&gt; SMB
          file system support" and "CIFS support")</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>for remote printers using the IPP protocol, you generally do
          not need to enable any additional settings in the kernel</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>If you notice that you have not selected the right configuration
      yet, you'll need to rebuild the kernel and reboot (see our chapter on
      "<link linkend="configuringkernel">Configuring a Linux
      Kernel</link>").</para>

      <para>Next, install the <package>net-print/cups</package> package,
      making sure you select the correct USE flags (this is discussed in a
      different chapter).</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>emerge net-print/cups</command></programlisting>

      <para>Don't worry if you do not have all USE flags correct from the
      first run. As I will mention later, it is always possible to update USE
      flags afterwards and then have Gentoo rebuild those packages affected by
      that change.</para>

      <para>If your printer is locally attached, you need to start the CUPS
      service:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>/etc/init.d/cupsd start</command></programlisting>

      <para>Also, make sure it is started upon every (re)boot:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>rc-update add cupsd default</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring CUPS</title>

      <para>CUPS offers a web interface to configure CUPS (and configure your
      printer). You can reach it through <ulink
      url="http://localhost:631">http://localhost:631</ulink>. In the
      Administration page, enter your root login and password information and
      you can get started with the configuration. <ulink
      url="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/printing-howto.xml">The Gentoo
      Printing HOWTO</ulink> offers a great walk through of the
      configuration.</para>

      <para>You probably hoped for a more elaborate discussion on printer
      configuration. Perhaps in the far future I will discuss printer
      configuration more, but for the time being I'm going to limit this and
      refer to Gentoo's guide and the main <ulink
      url="http://www.cups.org">CUPS</ulink> site.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Managing Device Files</title>

    <para>Almost every device on your system is represented by a device file.
    The <command>udev</command><indexterm>
        <primary>udev</primary>
      </indexterm> device manager discovers attached devices, creates device
    files in <filename>/dev</filename> (yes, you can create them - take a look
    at the <command>mknod</command><indexterm>
        <primary>mknod</primary>
      </indexterm> manpage) and often also creates symbolic links to those
    device files so you can find the correct device file more easily.</para>

    <para>The <command>udev</command> tool receives events from the Linux
    kernel; the moment such an event is received, <command>udev</command>
    matches the device attributes as offered by sysfs (you can browse through
    <filename>/sys</filename> if you want to see what
    <emphasis>sysfs</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>sysfs</primary>
      </indexterm> offers) against a set of rules. These rules you can view at
    <filename>/lib/udev/rules.d</filename> (provided by the udev distribution)
    and <filename>/etc/udev/rules.d</filename> (provided by third-party
    packages and, of course, your own rules if you write them
    yourself).</para>

    <para>Gentoo offers a set of default rules which should be sufficient for
    most users. For instance, they create links to the (removable) disks
    inside <filename>/dev/disk/by-id</filename>, <filename>by-path</filename>
    and <filename>by-uuid</filename>, which should allow you to have a device
    link for fstab which will be the same regardless of when you plug it in
    (in case of a hot pluggable device, of course). This is important, because
    if you have, for instance, two USB storage devices, the order in which
    they are plugged in defines the <filename>/dev/sd*</filename> device
    naming. By using the links at <filename>/dev/disk/by-*</filename> you can
    make sure that the correct device is targeted.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Further Resources</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/alsa-guide.xml">Gentoo
        ALSA Guide</ulink>, an excellent resource on configuring ALSA within
        Gentoo.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.reactivated.net/writing_udev_rules.html">Writing udev
        rules</ulink>, written by Daniel Drake</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/printing-howto.xml">Gentoo Printing
        HOWTO</ulink>, another excellent resource by Gentoo, now on printer
        configuration.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
