<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="softwaremanagement"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Software Management</title>

  <section>
    <title>Gentoo Portage</title>

    <para>In this section, we describe how to install software on Gentoo and
    what Gentoo's Portage and Portage tree are. This chapter is very
    Gentoo-specific - in fact, if you're not using Gentoo or a Gentoo-derived
    Linux distribution, you'll find most of this chapter entertaining yet not
    usable. If you are in this scenario, please do check the documentation of
    your distribution: software management is a part of a distributions'
    responsibilities which isn't standard(ised) in the free software community
    yet (because there are so many different ways, policies, politics and
    functionalities).</para>

    <para>I'm also not saying standardisation here is needed right now - the
    functionalities offered by the various distributions are too different to
    make standardisation possible at this point.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>Gentoo is primarily a source-code based Linux distribution. This
      means that, unlike most operating systems (including other Linux
      distributions), Gentoo does not just place compiled files on your file
      system but actually fetches the source code for the software you need
      from the Internet, configures the compilation environment and builds the
      software before it finally moves the resulting build onto the file
      system.</para>

      <para>Of course, Gentoo does support binary package installations, and
      this on two levels:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Software titles that would take a very long time to build on a
          users' system (such as the popular OpenOffice.org office suite) are
          available as binary packages. In this case, Gentoo downloads the
          binary files and installs those on the file system.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Prebuilt packages are supported as well: software built on a
          different Gentoo system, stored in a binary format file and made
          available to other Gentoo systems <emphasis>with</emphasis> the same
          settings (otherwise the binary packages might not be compatible with
          the system).</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The second level is a more advanced approach as Gentoo doesn't
      provide binary packages itself - you'll need to create and maintain a
      build environment yourself or use a third-party repository. As such, I
      am going to focus on source-code installations and the first binary
      package level (which is automatically supported).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Package Management: Portage</title>

      <para>The software that is responsible for managing installed software
      is called a package manager<indexterm>
          <primary>package manager</primary>
        </indexterm>. It is the interface to the user to install and uninstall
      software, upgrade the system, search through the available software and
      help with the configuration of the various software titles.</para>

      <para>For Gentoo, the default package manager is called
      Portage<indexterm>
          <primary>Portage</primary>
        </indexterm>. I say "default" because there are other package managers
      available for Gentoo as well (like Paludis<indexterm>
          <primary>Paludis</primary>
        </indexterm> and pkgcore<indexterm>
          <primary>pkgcore</primary>
        </indexterm>). These other package managers generally have the same
      features, but behave a bit differently. They are all compatible though,
      thanks to a standard approach to the packaging structure Gentoo
      uses.</para>

      <para>The package manager manages a local package repository called the
      Portage tree<indexterm>
          <primary>Portage tree</primary>
        </indexterm>. This package repository is a set of package metadata (so
      no source code or binary package) about software that can be installed
      on Gentoo.</para>

      <para>You can find the Portage tree at
      <filename>/usr/portage</filename>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Package Structure: Ebuilds</title>

      <para>The package metadata files are called
      <emphasis>ebuilds</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>ebuild</primary>
        </indexterm>. Ebuilds contain information about the package:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the name of the package, the internet site where you can find
          information about the software and the version of the software
          package</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the <emphasis>dependencies</emphasis><indexterm>
              <primary>dependency</primary>
            </indexterm> of the package (what other software is needed in
          order to successfully build or run this software)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the location where the software source code (or binary files
          in case of binary packages - first level) can be downloaded
          from</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the build instructions for the software (remember, Gentoo is
          primarily a source code based distribution)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the license the software uses</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the USE flags the package supports (USE flags are described
          later)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the configuration instructions needed to finalize the
          installation after building and installing the software</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>...</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Because all this information is simple, the ebuild file is a text
      file. This allows users to easily read what an ebuild actually does
      (although this does require knowledge about scripting and the ebuild
      format itself which isn't in the scope of this chapter).</para>

      <para>These packages are the main source for software installation and
      management. In order to keep track of new software releases, you will
      need to update the collection of ebuilds (Portage tree).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>USE Flags</title>

      <para>A USE<indexterm>
          <primary>USE</primary>
        </indexterm> flag is one of Gentoo's main strengths. USE flags are
      simple terms (such as "dvd", "X", "mysql" ...) and are used by ebuilds
      to detect what options you want enabled (or disabled) while building
      software.</para>

      <para>Most applications have optional support for one or more tools and
      libraries. For instance, at the time of writing, the Mozilla Firefox
      application in Gentoo supports the USE flags as shown in <xref
      linkend="use-mozilla"/></para>

      <table xml:id="use-mozilla">
        <title>USE flags in use by Mozilla Firefox version 9.0</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>USE flag</entry>

              <entry>Support description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>also</entry>

              <entry>Enable support for ALSA, the Advanced Linux Sound
              Architecture</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>crashreporter</entry>

              <entry>Enable support for the firefox crash reporting
              plugin</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>custom-cflags</entry>

              <entry>Build with user-specific CFLAGS (this removes any
              filtering the ebuild does). Note that you loose support when you
              enable this for Firefox</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>custom-optimization</entry>

              <entry>Fine-tune custom compiler optimizations (not
              recommended)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>dbus</entry>

              <entry>Enable support for DBUS</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>ipc</entry>

              <entry>Use inter-process communication between tabs and plugins.
              Allows for greater stability in case of plugin crashes</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>libnotify</entry>

              <entry>Enable desktop notification support</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>pgo</entry>

              <entry>Add support for profile-guided optimization using
              gcc-4.5, for faster binaries.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>startup-notification</entry>

              <entry>Enable application startup event feedback
              mechanism</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>system-sqlite</entry>

              <entry>Use the system-wide sqlite installation with
              secure-delete enabled</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>webm</entry>

              <entry>Use system media-libs/libvpx for HTML5 WebM video
              support</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>wifi</entry>

              <entry>Enable wireless network functions</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>gnome</entry>

              <entry>Enables support for the GNOME user interface (within
              Firefox) as well as GNOME file system event support</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>java</entry>

              <entry>Enables support for the java plug-in</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>bindist</entry>

              <entry>Disables the official Mozilla Firefox branding (unless
              USE="iceweasel" is selected) so that you can distribute prebuilt
              versions of the package across your network or even across the
              Internet.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>debug</entry>

              <entry>Enables debugging support (which makes the software
              larger and slower, but allows developers to debug possible bugs
              in the software)</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Other distributions choose what support they want enabled and what
      not when building the software. Because with Gentoo, you build the
      software yourself, you have the opportunity to enable or disable these
      features based on your USE flags.</para>

      <para>You can set your global USE flags inside
      <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename>. To disable a USE flag,
      prepend it with the minus sign.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>nano -w /etc/portage/make.conf</command>
<remark>(...)</remark>
USE="acpi apm pmu sasl howl -cdr -dvdread ..."</programlisting>

      <para>Because of the vast amount of USE flags that Gentoo supports, it
      is not your job to know and understand every single one of them. Gentoo
      is shipped with a sane default for your USE variable. To find out what
      your current USE flags are (based on Gentoo's default USE flags plus the
      USE flags you enabled or disabled in
      <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename>), use <command>emerge
      --info</command><indexterm>
          <primary>emerge</primary>

          <secondary>info</secondary>
        </indexterm>, filtering on the USE term:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>emerge --info | grep USE</command>
<emphasis>USE="X acl acpi alsa apache2 apm arts berkdb bitmap-fonts cairo cdr
cli cracklib crypt cscope css cups dbus dri dvd dvdr dvdread eds
emboss encode esd evo fam firefox fortran gdbm gif gnome gpm
gstreamer gtk hal howl iconv imap innodb ipv6 isdnlog java jpeg kde
kerberos ldap libwww mad maildir midi mikmod mp3 mpeg mudflap mysql
ncurses nls nptl nptlonly nsplugin odbc ogg opengl openmp oss pam
pcre pdf perl pmu png pppd python qt3 qt3support qt4 quicktime readline
reflection sasl sdl session spell spl ssl svg tcpd tetex tiff truetype
truetype-fonts type1-fonts unicode vcd vhosts vorbis win32codecs x86
xml xorg xv zlib"</emphasis> ALSA_CARDS="ali5451 als4000 atiixp atiixp-modem
bt87x ca0106 cmipci emu10k1 emu10k1x ens1370 ens1371 es1938 es1968
fm801 hda-intel intel8x0 intel8x0m maestro3 trident usb-audio via82xx
via82xx-modem ymfpci" ALSA_PCM_PLUGINS="adpcm alaw asym copy dmix
dshare dsnoop empty extplug file hooks iec958 ioplug ladspa lfloat
linear meter mulaw multi null plug rate route share shm softvol" 
APACHE2_MODULES="actions alias auth_basic authn_alias authn_anon 
authn_dbm authn_default authn_file authz_dbm authz_default
authz_groupfile authz_host authz_owner authz_user autoindex
cache dav dav_fs dav_lock deflate dir disk_cache env expires
ext_filter file_cache filter headers include info log_config logio
mem_cache mime mime_magic negotiation rewrite setenvif speling
status unique_id userdir usertrack vhost_alias" ELIBC="glibc" 
INPUT_DEVICES="keyboard mouse" KERNEL="linux" LCD_DEVICES="bayrad
cfontz cfontz633 glk hd44780 lb216 lcdm001 mtxorb ncurses text"
LINGUAS="en nl fr de" USERLAND="GNU" VIDEO_CARDS="i810 i915 vesa"</programlisting>

      <para>To obtain some information on a USE flag, you can use the
      <command>euse</command><indexterm>
          <primary>euse</primary>
        </indexterm> command:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>euse --info mp3</command>
global use flags (searching: mp3)
************************************************************
[+  D ] mp3 - Add support for reading mp3 files

local use flags (searching: mp3)
************************************************************
no matching entries found</programlisting>

      <para>If you want to manage USE flags on a per-package level (say you
      want to include MP3 support in mplayer but not in vlc) you can set
      per-package USE flags in
      <filename>/etc/portage/package.use</filename><indexterm>
          <primary>package.use</primary>
        </indexterm>. This location can either be a simple text file, but you
      can also make it a directory which contains many text files. This latter
      feature is very interesting if you want to manage the USE definitions
      more easily (say by aggregating media-related USE flag settings).
      Gentoo's Portage will read all files inside this directory.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>mkdir /etc/portage/package.use</command>
# <command>nano -w /etc/portage/package.use/media-flags</command>
media-video/vlc +mp3</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Maintaining your Software Stack</title>

    <para>With software stack maintenance, I mean installing and deinstalling
    software, updating your system and keeping track of the security patches
    for your system.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Obtaining the Latest Portage Tree</title>

      <para>As stated before, the Portage tree is the collection of ebuilds
      (which we will call "packages" from now onwards) that you can install on
      your system. Whether you want to update your system, install new
      software or obtain the latest security fixes, you will first need to
      update your Portage tree.</para>

      <para>The command to update the Portage tree is <command>emerge
      --sync</command><indexterm>
          <primary>emerge</primary>

          <secondary>sync</secondary>
        </indexterm>. The sync comes from synchronisation and gives you an
      idea on what <command>emerge</command> (Portage' main tool for software
      management) will do: it will synchronise your local Portage tree with
      the Portage tree available on one of Gentoo's mirrors.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>emerge --sync</command></programlisting>

      <para>You can easily configure what mirror <command>emerge</command>
      should use. For this, open up
      <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename> (Gentoo Portage's main
      configuration file) and locate the SYNC setting:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>nano -w /etc/portage/make.conf</command>
<remark>(...)</remark>
SYNC="rsync://rsync.us.gentoo.org/gentoo-portage"</programlisting>

      <para>The SYNC setting is set to a public Portage mirror. In the
      example, SYNC is set to a round-robin address which covers all mirrors
      in the United States of America. You can substitute the "us" country
      code with your country ("be" for Belgium, for instance) to use the
      round-robin address for the mirrors in your country.</para>

      <para>You notice that the setting references the rsync protocol. Indeed,
      rsync<indexterm>
          <primary>rsync</primary>
        </indexterm> is used to synchronise your local Portage tree. The tool
      (and protocol) has been selected because it only transfers the
      differences between two files rather than downloading the entire new
      tree.</para>

      <para>If you cannot use rsync (for instance because of a firewall
      setting) you can use <command>emerge-webrsync</command><indexterm>
          <primary>emerge-webrsync</primary>
        </indexterm> (without any options). This tool will fetch an archive
      which contains the entire Portage tree using the HTTP or FTP protocol
      and synchronise this archive locally. Of course, this will take more
      network traffic as an entire tree is downloaded.</para>

      <para>Also, Gentoo rsync mirrors update their Portage tree hourly. The
      snapshots retrieved using <command>emerge-webrsync</command> are updated
      daily.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Getting Gentoo News</title>

      <para>With an up to date Portage tree, you will also receive Gentoo's
      latest announcements for its users. Gentoo's news system allows Gentoo
      to inform its users about changes that the end user should read before
      blindly starting with an upgrade. This is also why I mention it before
      we start doing anything with software.</para>

      <para>When a news item is added, you will be notified of this at the end
      of a Portage update session:</para>

      <programlisting>* IMPORTANT: 21news items need reading for repository 'gentoo'.
* Use eselect news to read news items.</programlisting>

      <para>When you find such a notice at the end of your update, you can use
      Gentoo's <command>eselect</command><indexterm>
          <primary>eselect</primary>
        </indexterm> tool to find out more:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>eselect news list</command>
News items:
  [1]      2009-04-18  Generation 1 Java Setup Deprecated
  [2]      2009-07-02  (2009-07-02-kdeprefix+monolithics - removed?)
  [3]      2010-03-25  Python 3.1
  [4]      2010-08-01  (2010-08-01-as-needed-default - removed?)
  [5]      2010-10-22  Perl 5.12 upgrade procedure
  [6]      2011-04-27  Upgrade to GLIB 2.28
  [7]      2011-05-01  Baselayout update
  [8]      2011-05-22  (2011-05-22-kdeprefix - removed?)
  [9]      2011-08-28  Mesa r600 driver now defaults to gallium
  [10]     2011-10-15  Upgrade to libpng15
  [11]     2012-03-16  (2012-03-16-udev-181-unmasking - removed?)
  [12]     2012-04-24  The default JPEG implementation
  [13]     2012-05-21  Portage config-protect-if-modified default
  [14]     2012-09-09  make.conf and make.profile move
  [15]     2012-09-09  Catalyst updates
  [16]     2012-11-06  PYTHON_TARGETS deployment
  [17]     2013-01-23  (2013-01-23-udev-upgrade - removed?)
  [18]  N  2013-03-29  Upgrading udev to version &gt;=200</programlisting>

      <para>You can then read the news items one by one (<command>eselect news
      read &lt;number&gt;</command>) but I prefer to just tell eselect to
      display the content of the unread news items:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>eselect news read new</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Querying for Software</title>

      <para>With tens of thousands of software titles at your fingertips, how
      do you know what software is available (or what software you currently
      have installed)? Or what about querying information about software
      itself (like installed or installable files, dependencies ...), even
      when that software is or is not installed on your system? There are
      quite a few tools that help you with this...</para>

      <section>
        <title>Searching for Software Using emerge</title>

        <para>With emerge, you can query for software using
        <command>--search</command><indexterm>
            <primary>emerge</primary>

            <secondary>search</secondary>
          </indexterm> or <command>--searchdesc</command>.</para>

        <para>With <command>emerge --search</command>, you can look for
        software whose title (or part of) matches the selection you
        passed:</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>emerge --search acroread</command>
Searching...  
[ Results for search key : acroread ]
[ Applications found : 2 ]
 
*  app-text/acroread
      Latest version available: 9.4.2
      Latest version installed: [ Not Installed ]
      Size of files: 121,848 kB
      Homepage:      http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/
      Description:   Adobe's PDF reader
      License:       Adobe

*  media-fonts/acroread-asianfonts
      Latest version available: 9.1
      Latest version installed: [ Not Installed ]
      Size of files: 5,767 kB
      Homepage:      http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/acrrasianfontpack.html
      Description:   Asian font packs for Adobe Acrobat Reader
      License:       Adobe</programlisting>

        <para>In the resulting output, you can find the (in this case two)
        packages that match the given selection, together with</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>the latest, installable version</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the currently installed version (if applicable)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the size of the files that the installation needs to
            download</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the homepage of the application (where you can usually find
            more information about the tool)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the description of the software</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the software license</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If you use <command>--searchdesc</command>, the search also
        tries to match the description fields:</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>emerge --searchdesc acrobat</command>
Searching...  
[ Results for search key : acrobat ]
[ Applications found : 3 ]
 
*  app-admin/watchfolder
      Latest version available: 0.3.3
      Latest version installed: [ Not Installed ]
      Size of files: 93 kB
      Homepage:      http://freshmeat.net/projects/watchd/
      Description:   Watches directories and processes files, similar to the watchfolder option of Acrobat Distiller.
      License:       GPL-2

*  app-text/fdftk
      Latest version available: 6.0-r1
      Latest version installed: [ Not Installed ]
      Size of files: 5,591 kB
      Homepage:      http://www.adobe.com/devnet/acrobat/fdftoolkit.html
      Description:   Acrobat FDF Toolkit
      License:       Adobe</programlisting>

        <para>Running <command>--searchdesc</command> takes quite some time. I
        advise you to use an indexing tool to speed up searches...</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Searching for Software Using eix</title>

        <para>The eix<indexterm>
            <primary>eix</primary>
          </indexterm> tool (not available by default, you will need to
        install it: <command>emerge --ask eix</command>) indexes the
        searchable application information to allow you to quickly search
        through the portage tree.</para>

        <para>Once installed, you will need to run
        <command>update-eix</command><indexterm>
            <primary>update-eix</primary>
          </indexterm> (which will index all the information) after every
        <command>emerge --sync</command> (as this pulls in new packages which
        you want to index). You can also use
        <command>eix-sync</command><indexterm>
            <primary>eix-sync</primary>
          </indexterm> which will synchronise portage first and then update
        its indexing tables immediately afterwards.</para>

        <para>Once the index is built, you can quickly search through the
        Portage tree using eix. I frequently use <command>-HAS</command>
        (<command>--homepage --category-name --description</command>) as this
        also matches the homepage URI next to the application name and
        description:</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>eix -HAS acrobat</command></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Searching Installed Software Based on File(s)</title>

        <para>The <command>qfile</command><indexterm>
            <primary>qfile</primary>
          </indexterm> tool (part of
        <package>app-portage/portage-utils</package>) allows you to find out
        which package has delivered a certain file. That can be interesting if
        someone is asking you which package provided that particular file at
        your system.</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>qfile /usr/bin/qfile</command>
app-portage/portage-utils (/usr/bin/qfile)</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Searching Software (Installed or Not) Based on File(s)</title>

        <para>A Gentoo community project, called <link
        xl:href="http://www.portagefilelist.de">PortageFileList</link>, is
        attempting to store information about files provided by all packages.
        This isn't as simple as it sounds, since the files in a package depend
        heavily on the user his system: USE flags, other installed packages
        etc. The project asks users to run one of their tools to upload the
        local file information (file + package + USE flags) to the server.
        Other users can then use the tool <command>e-file</command><indexterm>
            <primary>e-file</primary>
          </indexterm> (part of <package>app-portage/pfl</package>) to query
        for packages.</para>

        <para>The command supports SQL-like wildcards. For instance,
        <filename>%bin/xdm</filename> matches
        <filename>/usr/sbin/xdm</filename> and
        <filename>/bin/xdm</filename>.</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>e-file '%bin/xdm'</command>
 * x11-apps/xdm
      Available versions: 1.1.8 1.1.9-r0
      Description:        X.Org xdm application
      Matched files:      /usr/bin/xdm;</programlisting>

        <para>Okay, this one was an easy guess as well ;-)</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Listing Installed Files</title>

        <para>To list which files are provided by a package, you can use
        <command>qlist</command><indexterm>
            <primary>qlist</primary>
          </indexterm> (also part of
        <package>app-portage/portage-utils</package>):</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>qlist portage-utils</command>
/usr/bin/q
/usr/bin/qatom
...
/usr/share/doc/portage-utils-0.2.1/qsync</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Enabling Installation Logs</title>

      <para>When a Gentoo developer wants to inform a package user about
      certain changes or things to look out for, he often puts informational
      messages in the package itself which are displayed the moment you've
      finished the installation of the package. However, for lengthy updates
      or installations, you often overlook these messages. For this purpose,
      Gentoo Portage allows you to store these messages in separate log files.
      By default, Portage only sets up a summary log for the installation. You
      can stick with those defaults, or set up a more verbose logging:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>nano /etc/portage/make.conf</command>

PORT_LOGDIR="/var/log/portage"
PORTAGE_ELOG_SYSTEM="save"
PORTAGE_ELOG_CLASSES="info warn error log"</programlisting>

      <para>With this defined, you'll find per-package logs in
      <filename>/var/log/portage/elog</filename>. You can then read those log
      files with your favorite text reader (like <command>less</command> or
      <command>view</command>) or using elog-specific tools like
      <command>elogv</command><indexterm>
          <primary>elogv</primary>
        </indexterm> (console) or <command>elogviewer</command><indexterm>
          <primary>elogviewer</primary>
        </indexterm> (graphical).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing New Software</title>

      <para>You've seen already that emerge is Gentoo's main tool to work with
      Portage and that it can be used to search for software. The same tool is
      used to install or remove software. To help users install software, it
      has a few options that allow you to make better informed decisions on
      which software to install (and what the effects will be). For instance,
      the <command>--pretend</command> option lets emerge show you what it
      would do, without actually modifying anything. You can even add the
      <command>--verbose</command> flag<indexterm>
          <primary>emerge</primary>

          <secondary>verbose</secondary>
        </indexterm> so that emerge tells you what additional settings the
      package supports. It also supports the
      <command>--ask</command><indexterm>
          <primary>emerge</primary>

          <secondary>ask</secondary>
        </indexterm> option which first behaves like
      <command>--pretend</command>, and then asks for confirmation to continue
      or not.</para>

      <para>For instance, to install Adobe's Acrobat Reader on your
      system:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>emerge --ask --verbose acroread</command>
These are the packages that would be merged, in order:

Calculating dependencies   ... done!
[ebuild  N    ] app-text/acroread-8.1.2  USE="cups ldap nsplugin" 
  LINGUAS="de en fr nl -da -es -fi -it -ja -ko -nb -pt -sv -zh_CN -zh_TW" 

Would you like to merge these packages? [Yes/No] </programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>Sometimes it might be necessary to use the category/package-name
        syntax (in this case, <command>emerge --ask --verbose
        app-text/acroread</command>). This could happen when two packages
        share the same name but are part of different categories.</para>
      </note>

      <para>In this example, emerge tells you that it will install Adobe
      Acrobat Reader version 8.1.2 and that it doesn't need any other
      dependencies (otherwise you'll have more lines in the same line as the
      one you see). Emerge also tells you that the acroread package supports
      three USE flags:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>cups (support for the Common Unix Printing System),</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ldap (support for the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol)
          and</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>nsplugin (creating Acrobat Reader plugins for the
          Mozilla-based browsers)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>All three flags are in this case enabled on this system.</para>

      <para>Also, the acroread package supports various languages: de
      (German), en (English), fr (French), nl (Dutch), da (Danish), es
      (Spanish), fi (Finnish), it (Italian), ja (Japanese), ko (Korean), nb
      (Norwegian Bokmal), pt (Portugese), sv (Swedish), zh_CN (Simplified
      Chinese) and zn_TW (Taiwanese Mandarin). Of all these languages, Portage
      will only include support for German, English, French and Dutch (the
      languages I want supported on my system).</para>

      <para>To install the software, accept the merge. This will, for every
      package:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>download the source code from the Internet,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>verify the source code with the checksum stored in the Portage
          tree (to ensure that the downloaded file isn't corrupt),</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>extract the source code to a temporary location on the system
          (<filename>/var/tmp/portage</filename>),</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>patch the source code with Gentoo-specific patches,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>configure the source code based on the USE flags you
          use,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>build the source code into a temporary location,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>register the files it has created in this location, and
          finally</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>move the files to the system (making the application available
          to the end user)</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>This installation process will take some time (compared to
      distributions who use prebuilt packages), mainly because of the build
      step. There are tools that show the user how long the emerge phase of a
      package took in average, but these are only for informational purposes
      and give no guarantee whatsoever about future emerge phase durations (as
      this depends on USE flags, source code size, CPU speed, system resource
      availability ...).</para>

      <para><command>qlop</command><indexterm>
          <primary>qlop</primary>
        </indexterm> (part of the <filename>portage-utils</filename><indexterm>
          <primary>portage-utils</primary>
        </indexterm> package) is such a tool. In the next example, it shows
      the build duration averaged over 27 merges:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>qlop --time --human mozilla-firefox</command>
mozilla-firefox: 1 hour, 15 minutes, 22 seconds for 27 merges</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Updating your System</title>

      <para>When you are booted inside a Gentoo Linux system, many packages
      will already be installed. It is wise to regularly update your system by
      pulling in the latest updates, bugfixes and security fixes.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Updating All Installed Packages</title>

        <para>If you want to update all installed packages to their latest,
        stable version, first update your Portage tree as mentioned before.
        Then, run the following command to see what packages will be updated,
        installed or removed<indexterm>
            <primary>emerge</primary>

            <secondary>world</secondary>
          </indexterm>:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>emerge --update --deep --newuse @world --pretend</command></programlisting>

        <para>The options you pass on to emerge are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><command>--update</command> (or <command>-u</command>),
            asking emerge to update software,</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><command>--deep</command> (or <command>-D</command>), asking
            emerge to select not only the software selected, but also all of
            its dependencies,</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><command>--new</command> (or <command>-N</command>), asking
            emerge to update software when new dynamic switches are used (USE
            flags),</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>@world, asking emerge to select all software that the user
            has installed, and</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><command>--pretend</command> (or <command>-p</command>),
            asking emerge to display what it would install, update or
            remove</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>To really perform the update, use the same command without
        <command>--pretend</command>. The next example does this using the
        single letter arguments:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>emerge -uDN @world</command></programlisting>

        <para>Now, if you're tired of continuously running a command with
        <command>--pretend</command> only to remove the
        <command>--pretend</command> after verifying the output, use
        <command>--ask</command> instead as we discussed before.</para>

        <para>From now onwards, I will be using the <command>--ask</command>
        argument where appropriate.</para>

        <para>You might have noticed that the world argument is prefixed with
        the at sign (@). This is not mandatory - in the past it was without -
        but a while ago, Portage started supporting what we call "sets" of
        packages. The world target is one of such sets, and sets are prefixed
        with an at sign to distinguish them from regular packages.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Updating All User-Installed Packages</title>

        <para>If you don't want to upgrade every single package on your
        system, but only the packages you've selected to install previously,
        don't use the <command>--deep</command> argument. User installed
        packages are the packages you've asked to install excluding the
        dependencies that were pulled in to satisfy the application
        requirements. The end result is that only a small amount of updates is
        installed. However, this doesn't mean that you will quickly have
        outdated dependencies - every time an update is pulled in, this update
        might instruct Portage that it can only work with a higher version of
        a particular dependency, causing Portage to update that dependency as
        well.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>emerge --update --newuse --ask @world</command></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Do not Stop Installing after Build Failures</title>

        <para>By default, Gentoo Portage stops the installation / upgrade
        process when one package fails to build properly. Although this
        definitely needs some attention, you can ask Gentoo Portage to resume
        building the other packages first. At the end of the final build
        process, you will be greeted with a small report informing you which
        packages have failed and why.</para>

        <para>To ask Portage to keep going after failure, use
        <command>--keep-going</command><indexterm>
            <primary>emerge</primary>

            <secondary>keep-going</secondary>
          </indexterm>:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>emerge -uDN --keep-going @world</command></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Pulling Security Fixes</title>

        <para>Gentoo also supports building the software affected by security
        issues<indexterm>
            <primary>security updates</primary>
          </indexterm> alone. In this case, none of your unaffected software
        is upgraded (unless requires as a dependency of a security upgrade).
        Gentoo provides GLSA<indexterm>
            <primary>GLSA</primary>
          </indexterm> (<emphasis>Gentoo Linux Security
        Advisory</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>Gentoo Linux Security Advisory</primary>
          </indexterm>) documents to inform its users about possible security
        issues (except kernel issues). These GLSA documents are parsed by the
        <command>glsa-check</command><indexterm>
            <primary>glsa-check</primary>
          </indexterm> command which can apply the necessary fixes.</para>

        <para>To verify if your system is affected by one or more security
        advisories, first update your Portage tree and then run
        <command>glsa-check --test all</command>:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>glsa-check --test all</command>
This system is affected by the following GLSAs:
200711-10</programlisting>

        <para>In the example, one security advisory matches my system. I can
        obtain more information about the advisory using <command>glsa-check
        --dump 200711-10</command>. To fix the system, I can run glsa-check's
        --fix:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>glsa-check --fix all</command>
<remark>(This will iterate over all GLSAs, including the matching one(s))</remark></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Switching between software versions</title>

        <para>Gentoo supports having multiple versions of the same software on
        the system. Notable examples are gcc, python and java but many more
        exist. Administrators are able to switch between these installed
        versions using <command>eselect</command><indexterm>
            <primary>eselect</primary>
          </indexterm>. We have seen this tool already previously for
        switching between profiles.</para>

        <para>For instance, to display the installed Python versions:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>eselect python list</command>
Available Python interpreters:
  [1] python2.7
  [2] python3.1 *</programlisting>

        <para>In the above example, Python 3.1 is the system default. You can
        switch the system to 2.7 then using <command>eselect python set
        1</command>.</para>

        <para>To get an overview of the supported modules in eselect, run
        <command>eselect help</command>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Uninstalling Software</title>

      <para>Now suppose you've found some software installed on your system
      that you want to remove. With <command>emerge
      --unmerge</command><indexterm>
          <primary>emerge</primary>

          <secondary>unmerge</secondary>
        </indexterm> (<command>-C</command> in short) you can remove installed
      software from your system.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>emerge --unmerge acroread --ask</command></programlisting>

      <para>However, if this software is a dependency of an installed software
      title, your next system update will pull the software back in. Even
      worse, software that depends on it that is still being used / running
      might even stop functioning properly or crash. A safer way of pursuing
      the desinstallation of a package is by asking Portage not to consider
      the package as your "main" requirement using the
      <command>--deselect</command><indexterm>
          <primary>emerge</primary>

          <secondary>deselect</secondary>
        </indexterm> option:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>emerge --deselect acroread</command></programlisting>

      <para>This will not remove the package by itself. To actually remove it,
      run <command>emerge --depclean</command><indexterm>
          <primary>emerge</primary>

          <secondary>depclean</secondary>
        </indexterm>. The <command>depclean</command> instruction asks Portage
      to look for package that are installed but are not required any more. It
      decides this based on the list of packages you have installed explicitly
      and their dependencies. If the package is not in those results, then it
      is most likely not needed anymore.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>emerge --depclean --ask</command></programlisting>

      <para>With this command, Portage will remove packages that are not in
      use. In other words, if no other package depends upon acroread, it will
      remove acroread as you explicitly told Portage that you don't want to
      consider it any more. However, if some package still depends upon
      acroread, Portage will let acroread remain on your system (until the
      package that depends on acroread is removed or deselected as
      well).</para>

      <warning>
        <para>Always first verify depclean's output before resuming. Never run
        depclean if your system isn't fully up to date.</para>
      </warning>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Advanced Software Management</title>

    <para>Of course, Gentoo allows for much more advanced software management
    aspects than described before. If you search the available documentation,
    you'll quickly notice that Gentoo Portage supports the notion of stable
    versus "unstable" packages (the so-called ~arch states), supports
    third-party repositories and more.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Package States</title>

      <para>Gentoo packages, which are called ebuilds, are always in a certain
      state. Although this state is never explicitly defined in the package,
      it is a result of a set of rules set forth by developers to keep track
      of a package's stability, security, license rules, ...</para>

      <para>When you install packages, those rules are checked to make sure
      you are not installing a package that shouldn't be installed on your
      system. These various rules can trigger installation errors, most of the
      time described as being a <emphasis>package mask</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>package mask</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>mask</primary>
        </indexterm>.</para>

      <para>Whenever an installation is triggered, Gentoo Portage tries to
      install the highest version of a package which matches all possible
      validity rules. Only when no such version exists, or when you explicitly
      asked to install a certain version, Gentoo aborts the installation with
      a failure message.</para>

      <para>The following sections describe the various states / rules that
      are checked when an installation is triggered. If you want to work
      around such a rule, see the section on "Unmasking Packages".</para>

      <section>
        <title>Architecture Availability</title>

        <para>Gentoo is a multi-architecture operating system. Packages
        available within Gentoo can be installed on several architectures,
        ranging from the popular x86/amd64 onto sparc, mips, powerpc, ... But
        of course, most packages can't be installed on any platform. Some
        tools are only supported on the Intel-like platforms (x86, amd64) or
        on a specific platform (like the silo boot loader, which is explicitly
        made for the sparc platform).</para>

        <para>Packages are marked as being available for a particular platform
        using their <varname>KEYWORDS</varname><indexterm>
            <primary>KEYWORDS</primary>
          </indexterm> variable. An example, taken from sys-apps/iproute2
        version 2.6.29-r1:</para>

        <programlisting>KEYWORDS="alpha amd64 arm hppa ia64 m68k ~mips ppc ppc64 s390 sh sparc x86"</programlisting>

        <para>When you install a package, its platform keywords are checked
        against the keywords that your system accepts. These keywords are
        defined in the <varname>ACCEPT_KEYWORDS</varname><indexterm>
            <primary>ACCEPT_KEYWORDS</primary>
          </indexterm> variable, which you can query with <command>emerge
        --info</command>:</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>emerge --info | grep ACCEPT_KEYWORDS</command>
ACCEPT_KEYWORDS="amd64"</programlisting>

        <para>Whenever a mismatch occurs (the package doesn't have the keyword
        that you have defined in <varname>ACCEPT_KEYWORDS</varname>) you get
        an error message like so:</para>

        <programlisting>!!! All ebuilds that could satisfy "sys-boot/silo" have been masked.
!!! One of the following masked packages is required to complete your request:
- sys-boot/silo-1.4.14 (masked by: missing keyword)</programlisting>

        <para>Having an error due to an unsupported architecture, it is not
        advisable to try and work around this (forcing the package to be
        installable). It will most likely not work anyhow.</para>

        <para>Other related error messages that you might receive are:</para>

        <programlisting>- lm-sensors/lm-sensors-2.8.7 (masked by: -sparc keyword)
- sys-libs/glibc-2.3.4.20040808 (masked by: -* keyword)</programlisting>

        <para>These error messages are similar to the one above (missing
        keyword). The differences are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>"missing keyword" means that the architecture isn't set in
            the KEYWORDS variable.</para>

            <para>The architecture might be supported by the package, but no
            developer has tried to install it on this platform yet.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>"-sparc keyword" (or other architecture) means that that
            particular architecture is explicitly denied in the KEYWORDS
            variable.</para>

            <para>In this case, the developer has either tried to install it,
            but it destroyed its system, or the package itself is known not to
            work on the mentioned platform.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>"-* keyword" means that all architectures are explicitly
            denied in the KEYWORDS variable except a few.</para>

            <para>This case is mostly used for packages that are meant to be
            available on a single platform only. The developer marks the
            package as unavailable for any other architecture, hence the
            "-*".</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Stabilization of Gentoo Packages</title>

        <para>When a developer creates or edits a Gentoo package, the software
        isn't immediately available for the general public. First, it is put
        through a sort of <emphasis>staging period</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>staging period</primary>
          </indexterm>. During this time, testers try out the package, finding
        possible package definition bugs (like wrong dependencies) and helping
        the further development until the package is deemed stable.</para>

        <para>There is an unwritten rule that says that packages should
        "linger" in the staging period for 30 bug-free days (no additional
        bugs found by the architecture testers) before it is released to the
        general public.</para>

        <para>Within Gentoo, this staging period is described by prepending
        the tilde (~) sign in front of the architecture in the
        <varname>KEYWORDS</varname> variable. In the KEYWORDS example above
        (of the iproute2 package) you notice that this is done for the mips
        architecture. In other words, the package most likely is supported on
        the MIPS architecture, but it is currently under review (in staging
        period). It is well possible that within a month, the package is made
        available for the general MIPS public as well.</para>

        <para>Whenever you try to install a package that is in the staging
        period, you get an error message as follows:</para>

        <programlisting>!!! All ebuilds that could satisfy "&gt;=sys-apps/portage-2.1.8" have been masked.
!!! One of the following masked packages is required to complete your request:
- sys-apps/portage-2.2_rc62 (masked by: ~amd64 keyword)</programlisting>

        <para>If you get such an error message, I recommend to wait until the
        package is generally available (and let the architecture testers bring
        out most of the bugs for you).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Critical Bugs or Security Issues</title>

        <para>Whenever a package has a critical bug (critical = breaks your
        system severely), a security issue (like having an exploitable
        vulnerability that might grant malicious users access to your system)
        or just isn't maintained any more, the Gentoo developer might mask the
        package explicitly.</para>

        <para>Explicit masks do not only disallow the installation of the
        software, they usually also contain a comment as to why the
        installation is prohibited. These explicit masks (and their comments)
        are stored in a file called
        <filename>package.mask</filename><indexterm>
            <primary>package.mask</primary>
          </indexterm>. By default, this file is available in
        <filename>/usr/portage/profiles</filename>.</para>

        <para>An example would be:</para>

        <programlisting>!!! All ebuilds that could satisfy "games-roguelike/slashem" have been masked.
!!! One of the following masked packages is required to complete your request:
- games-roguelike/slashem-0.0.772 (masked by: package.mask)
/usr/portage/profiles/package.mask:
# Tavis Ormandy &lt;taviso@gentoo.org&gt; (21 Mar 2006)
# masked pending unresolved security issues #127167</programlisting>

        <para>In this example, you find out who masked the package, when the
        mask occurs, and why (including a bug number which can be checked at
        <link
        xl:href="https://bugs.gentoo.org">https://bugs.gentoo.org</link>).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>License Approval</title>

        <para>Gentoo packages always keep track of the license under which the
        software is distributed / allowed to be used. Like the architecture
        available cases, this is done through a variable called
        <varname>LICENSE</varname><indexterm>
            <primary>LICENSE</primary>
          </indexterm>. For instance, for the <package>net-im/skype</package>
        package:</para>

        <programlisting>LICENSE="skype-eula"</programlisting>

        <para>And, just like the KEYWORDS case, your system has a variable
        called <varname>ACCEPT_LICENSE</varname><indexterm>
            <primary>ACCEPT_LICENSE</primary>
          </indexterm> in which you set which software licenses you want on
        your system. The default setting on Gentoo systems is quite liberal,
        but you can set it to your liking. For instance, you can accept only
        FSF approved licenses:</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>emerge --info | grep ACCEPT_LICENSE</command>
ACCEPT_LICENSE="-* @FSF-APPROVED"</programlisting>

        <para>The use of the @-sign allows Gentoo to group similar licenses
        together. The list of license groups can be obtained from
        <filename>/usr/portage/profiles/license_groups</filename><indexterm>
            <primary>license_groups</primary>
          </indexterm>.</para>

        <para>If you ever want to install a software which doesn't match the
        license(s) you allow, you will get an error like so:</para>

        <programlisting>!!! All ebuilds that could satisfy "net-im/skype" have been masked.
!!! One of the following masked packages is required to complete your request:
- net-im/skype-2.0.0.72 (masked by: skype-eula license)</programlisting>

        <para>In this example, the package I want to install uses the
        "skype-eula" license which doesn't match the licenses I allow (which
        are only the <varname>FSF-APPROVED</varname> ones).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Profile Supported Software</title>

        <para>Gentoo supports several profiles. A
        <emphasis>profile</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>profile</primary>
          </indexterm> should be seen as a collection of predefined settings
        for your Gentoo Linux environment. These settings include default USE
        flags, default license acceptance, default package choices, etc. Such
        profiles can also have masks against certain packages because they
        don't fit in the spirit of the profile.</para>

        <para>An example is the selinux/v2refpolicy/x86/hardened profile,
        which masks out glibc-2.4 as it doesn't match the security measures
        that the profile wants to enforce.</para>

        <para>Whenever you try to install a package that isn't allowed due to
        your profile, you get a message like so:</para>

        <programlisting>!!! All ebuilds that could satisfy "=sys-libs/glibc-2.4*" have been masked.
!!! One of the following masked packages is required to complete your request:
- sys-libs/glibc-2.4-r2 (masked by: profile)</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Unmasking Packages</title>

      <para>When you get an installation failure because the package you want
      to install is considered masked, you <emphasis>can</emphasis> opt to
      install it anyway. I recommend that you consider this step carefully -
      masking of packages is done with a reason.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If it is because of a critical bug or security issue, I
          seriously discourage you to install it (for obvious reasons).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the package is masked due to the stabilization track, I
          urge you to wait until it is generally available.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the package is masked due to architecture unavailability, I
          suggest that you investigate if the package supports your
          architecture. If it doesn't, there's no point in trying to install
          it anyway. If it does, you might want to ask the architecture
          testing team of Gentoo to investigate the package.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the package is masked due to profile mismatch, you're
          either running the wrong profile or have made a mistake in trying to
          install the package and will now continue with your life as it
          is.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the package is masked due to license mismatch, then your
          license setting is incorrect.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Now, the last reason (license settings) is (in my opinion) the
      only one that warrants a change in the configuration, but the way on
      dealing with these blocks is similar.</para>

      <section>
        <title>System-wide or Package Specific?</title>

        <para>Whenever you want to resolve a masking issue, you need to ask
        yourself if you want to resolve this for this particular package only
        (or a set of packages) or if you want to alter the settings for the
        entire system. In the majority of cases (except for licenses) it is
        for a particular package (or set of packages).</para>

        <para>Portage has a specific configuration directory
        (<filename>/etc/portage</filename>) in which deviation settings can be
        stored. Each type of deviation has its own file or directory:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/etc/portage/package.license</filename><indexterm>
                <primary>package.license</primary>
              </indexterm> allows you to set license-deviations (approve or
            deny a license on a per-package basis)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/etc/portage/package.mask</filename><indexterm>
                <primary>package.mask</primary>
              </indexterm> allows you to mask packages (deny packages on a
            per-package basis)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/etc/portage/package.unmask</filename><indexterm>
                <primary>package.unmask</primary>
              </indexterm> allows you to unmask packages (allow packages that
            are disapproved due to critical bugs, security issues or profile
            mismatches, on a per-package basis)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>/etc/portage/package.accept_keywords</filename><indexterm>
                <primary>package.accept_keywords</primary>
              </indexterm> allows you to set keyword deviations (inform
            Portage that for this package, other keywords are accepted as
            well)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <note>
          <para>Previous versions of Portage use
          <filename>package.keywords</filename><indexterm>
              <primary>package.keywords</primary>
            </indexterm> instead of
          <filename>package.accept_keywords</filename>. Recent Portage
          versions still support this old location, but it is recommended to
          rename them to package.accept_keywords to remain functional in the
          future.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Now, I did say "file or directory" in the previous paragraph.
        That's right: Portage allows you to either put the information in
        files that are called as mentioned above, or in files that reside in a
        directory called as mentioned above.</para>

        <para>The most proper way, in my opinion, is to create directories.
        Within each directory, you can then group deviations based on the
        reason.</para>

        <para>If you want to make a system-wide deviation, you need to edit
        the <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename> file.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Example: Allow the Skype-EULA License for the net-im/skype
        package</title>

        <para>As an example, let's allow the skype EULA license for the skype
        package (and only for the skype package).</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Create a directory called
            <filename>package.license</filename> within
            <filename>/etc/portage</filename>.</para>

            <programlisting># <command>mkdir -p /etc/portage/package.license</command></programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Create a file called "skype" inside this directory, and
            enter "net-im/skype skype-eula".</para>

            <programlisting># <command>nano -w /etc/portage/package.license/skype</command>
net-im/skype skype-eula</programlisting>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>That's it. If you now would launch the installation of the skype
        package, it will not abort saying that the license is masked because
        you explicitly allowed the license on this package. However, if for
        some reason another package uses the same license, it will still fail
        installing because that particular package isn't mentioned as a valid
        deviation.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Example: Allow the Skype-EULA License System-wide</title>

        <para>The other way is to allow the skype EULA system-wide.</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Find out what your current license acceptance rule
            is.</para>

            <programlisting>$ <command>emerge --info | grep ACCEPT_LICENSE</command>
ACCEPT_LICENSE="-* @FSF-APPROVED"</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Open <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename> in your
            favourite text editor:</para>

            <programlisting># <command>nano -w /etc/portage/make.conf</command></programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Navigate to the place where ACCEPT_LICENSE is defined or, if
            it isn't defined, create a new line and make it so that it looks
            like the current setting as obtained from the first step:</para>

            <programlisting>ACCEPT_LICENSE="-* @FSF-APPROVED"</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Now add the skype-eula license:</para>

            <programlisting>ACCEPT_LICENSE="-* @FSF-APPROVED<command> skype-eula</command>"</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Save the file and exit.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>If you now install the skype package, it will not fail due to
        the license, as you now state that you accept this license. If any
        other package also works with the skype EULA license, it will also be
        installable now.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Example: Allow bonnie++ Version 1.96 (Staging State) to be
        Installable</title>

        <para>If you want to install app-benchmarks/bonnie++-1.96 but find out
        that the package is masked (say ~x86 keyword mask), you can inform
        Portage to allow the installation of this particular package
        regardless of it being in the staging state or not:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Create the
            <filename>/etc/portage/package.accept_keywords</filename>
            directory</para>

            <programlisting># <command>mkdir -p /etc/portage/package.accept_keywords</command></programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Create a file (say benchmarks) and add
            "app-benchmarks/bonnie++" to it:</para>

            <programlisting># <command>nano -w /etc/portage/package.accept_keywords/benchmarks</command>
app-benchmarks/bonnie++</programlisting>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>With this setting in place, Portage will allow you to install
        bonnie++ (any version) regardless if it is still in the staging state
        or not.</para>

        <para>If you only want to allow this for the 1.96 version, use the
        following line instead:</para>

        <programlisting>=app-benchmarks/bonnie++-1.96</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Example: Allow All Staging State Packages to be
        Installable</title>

        <warning>
          <para>Setting this is greatly discouraged. You do not get support
          from Gentoo developers if you do this!</para>

          <para>Oh, and if you do it, your next system update will pull in a
          lot of packages, and chances are slim that you can safely downgrade
          (so this step is difficult to undo).</para>
        </warning>

        <para>To allow the staging packages to be installable on your system
        (any package in the staging state), edit
        <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename> accordingly:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Find out your current ACCEPT_KEYWORDS value.</para>

            <programlisting>$ <command>emerge --info | grep ACCEPT_KEYWORDS</command>
ACCEPT_KEYWORDS="x86"</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Open <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename> in your
            favourite editor</para>

            <programlisting># <command>nano -w /etc/portage/make.conf</command></programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Navigate to the ACCEPT_KEYWORDS variable or, if it doesn't
            exist, create it with the value obtained in the first step:</para>

            <programlisting>ACCEPT_KEYWORDS="x86"</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Now add the staging sign to it:</para>

            <programlisting>ACCEPT_KEYWORDS="<command>~x86</command>"</programlisting>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Save the file and exit.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>From this point onwards, Portage will install the highest
        available version of a package regardless of it being in the staging
        state or not.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Other Examples...</title>

        <para>From the previous examples, you should get a grip on how to
        handle masked packages:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>either create a file in a <filename>/etc/portage</filename>
            subdirectory, or</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>edit the make.conf file to make things globally</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>You can find more information on the syntax used within the
        <filename>/etc/portage</filename> subdirectories through the portage
        manpage:</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>man portage</command>
<emphasis>(...)
(Type in "/" followed by the file name you want to know more about)</emphasis>
<command>/package.mask</command>
<emphasis>(Type "n" (next) until you get the section information)</emphasis>

package.mask
  A list of package atoms to mask. Useful if specific ver-
  sions of packages do not work well for you. For example,
  if you swear ...</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Automatically unmasking packages</title>

        <para>More than often, a staging-state masked package has dependencies
        upon other masked packages, who have dependencies upon other masked
        packages, etc. To manually enter these dependencies in
        /<filename>etc/portage/package.accept_keywords</filename> and, more
        importantly, finding out about these packages, you would need to retry
        installing over and over again until you have met and resolved all
        errors.</para>

        <para>A more automated way of dealing with this is to use
        <command>autounmask</command><indexterm>
            <primary>autounmask</primary>
          </indexterm>. <command>autounmask</command> allows you to select the
        main package you want, and it will automatically create a file inside
        <filename>/etc/portage/package.accept_keywords</filename> that unmasks
        all depending packages as well.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>emerge autounmask</command>
# <command>autounmask x11-misc/googleearth</command></programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Switching System Profiles</title>

      <para>Gentoo Linux uses profiles to define defaults for your system
      environment. You should have gotten a first glance at profiles while
      installing Gentoo (if you didn't, that's okay). As a quick recap:
      profiles are a set of predefined default values made by the Gentoo
      project to destinguish between particular uses of the distribution.
      Whereas other distributions ask you to select a particular type of
      deployment (say desktop or server) in the beginning of, or during the
      initial installation, Gentoo allows you to switch profiles whenever you
      like.</para>

      <para>The profile a system uses is defined by the
      <filename>/etc/make.profile</filename><indexterm>
          <primary>make.profile</primary>
        </indexterm> symbolic link:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>ls -l /etc/make.profile</command>
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 57 Dec 2007 make.profile -&gt; 
  /usr/portage/profiles/default-linux/x86/20O7.0/desktop</programlisting>

      <para>A Gentoo profile defines, amongst other things:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>what USE flags are activated by default</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>what applications get installed by default when you select a
          virtual<footnote>
              <para>A virtual is a placeholder for an application. For
              instance, Gentoo offers several Java runtimes; they all
              implement the virtual/jre. A Gentoo profiles marks a specific
              package as default for such virtual.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>what packages are not available for the profile (for instance,
          a uclibc profile doesn't support glibc) or should have a certain
          version (for instance, glibc higher than or equal to 2.4).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Users can easily switch between profiles. A useful tool for this
      is eselect:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>eselect profile list</command>
Available profile symlink targets:
  [1]   default/linux/amd64/13.0 *
  [2]   default/linux/amd64/13.0/selinux
  [3]   default/linux/amd64/13.0/desktop
  [4]   default/linux/amd64/13.0/desktop/gnome
  [5]   default/linux/amd64/13.0/desktop/kde
  [6]   default/linux/amd64/13.0/developer
  [7]   default/linux/amd64/13.0/no-multilib
  [8]   default/linux/amd64/13.0/x32
  [9]   hardened/linux/amd64
  [10]  hardened/linux/amd64/selinux
  [11]  hardened/linux/amd64/no-multilib
  [12]  hardened/linux/amd64/no-multilib/selinux
  [13]  hardened/linux/uclibc/amd64

# <command>eselect profile set 10</command></programlisting>

      <para>As you can see from the profile names, one profile can be a child
      of another; if this is the case (for instance, profile number 4 from the
      above list has profile number 3 as parent), the profile inherits the
      settings from its parent and may extend or override particular settings
      itself.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using Third Party Software Repositories</title>

      <para>Next to Gentoo's main Portage tree, you can also select third
      party software repositories. Those are trees of developers, users and
      organisations that offer ebuilds for you to use which aren't available
      in Gentoo's Portage tree (yet).</para>

      <para>A great tool for managing third party software repositories is
      <command>layman</command><indexterm>
          <primary>layman</primary>
        </indexterm>. Install <command>layman</command> and then see what
      repositories layman supports:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>layman -L</command>
(...)
xen          [Subversion] (source: http://overlays....)</programlisting>

      <para>The output of this layman command shows you what third party
      repositories are configured for use with layman. If you want to select
      one, add it to your system:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>layman -a xen</command></programlisting>

      <para>Likewise, to stop using a repository, remove it with
      <command>layman -d</command>. If you want to see what repositories you
      are currently using, use <command>layman -l</command>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>When Things Go Wrong</title>

    <para>Of course, both Gentoo and the upstream projects that Gentoo relies
    on are still ran and developed by humans, and humans are programmed to
    make occasional mistakes, so things can go wrong. If you have installation
    or build failures, the following sections might help you troubleshoot
    it.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Portage Refuses To Install A Package</title>

      <para>During package installation analysis, a few issues can occur which
      need intervention. Those are:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Blocked packages (a package that needs to be installed is
            blocked by an already installed package or another package on the
            installation list)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Masked packages (a package is not available for your profile
            or environment)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Download failures (one or more files needed to install the
            software aren't available or might be corrupt)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Kernel configuration mismatch (the package requires
            particular kernel configuration directives to be set)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Other issues (catch-all)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <section>
        <title>Blocked Packages</title>

        <para>Sometimes a package offers a functionality that another package
        also offers and where the two packages cannot coexist with each other.
        When this occurs, you get the following two error:</para>

        <programlisting>[blocks B     ] mail-mta/ssmtp (is blocking mail-mta/postfix-2.2.2-r1)</programlisting>

        <para>In this example, the postfix package is on the installation
        list, but cannot coexist with ssmtp (which is already installed). As a
        result, the installation fails.</para>

        <para>To resolve this, the easiest approach is to unmerge (remove) the
        ssmtp package from the system and retry.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Masked Packages</title>

        <para>A package can fail to install if it is masked. A mask on a
        package means that the package is in a state that it shouldn't be
        installed on your system. Package states are described earlier in this
        chapter. Package masks are one of the more common causes of
        installation failures. There can be plenty of reasons why a package
        mask is interfering with an installation cycle:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>the end user was instructed through a document or another
            user to unmask one package, causing a possible failure on the
            dependency integrity</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a developer wrongfully made a package available which has
            dependencies on packages that aren't available in this particular
            state</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the package just doesn't fit the profile that the users
            system requires</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the end user was instructed to install a particular package
            which isn't available for general consumption yet</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If you have a masked package, read "Package States" carefully
        and, if necessary, "Unmasking Packages" earlier in this
        chapter.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Verification of download results in failure</title>

        <para>When Gentoo Portage attempts to install software, it will verify
        the downloaded files with the checksums and file sizes that the Gentoo
        developer has recorded when he added the software package to the
        Portage tree. When the downloaded file and the checksum/file size
        doesn't match, an error is shown:</para>

        <programlisting>('Filesize does not match recorded size', 97003L, 952)
!!! Fetched file: genpatches-2.6.33-1.base.tar.bz2 VERIFY FAILED!
!!! Reason: Filesize does not match recorded size
!!! Got: 97003
!!! Expected: 952
...
&gt;&gt;&gt; Failed to emerge sys-kernel/gentoo-sources-2.6.33, Log file:

&gt;&gt;&gt; '/var/tmp/portage/sys-kernel/gentoo-sources-2.6.33/temp/build.log'</programlisting>

        <para>In the above example, the file size as recorded by the developer
        (952 bytes) is different from the file size of the downloaded file
        (97003 bytes). As a result, Gentoo Portage refuses to install the
        software as it might be corrupted, contain malicious code, etc.</para>

        <para>Most of the time this occurs when the developer has made a
        honest mistake (he uploaded a file, found an issue, resolved it in
        Portage but forgot to upload the modified file). In this case, the
        problem will most likely be reported to <link
        xl:href="https://bugs.gentoo.org">https://bugs.gentoo.org</link> and
        quickly resolved. Try synchronising the Portage tree after a few hours
        and retry.</para>

        <para>If it isn't, check if the problem has been reported or not. You
        can also try synchronising the Portage tree from a different Gentoo
        mirror (change the value of the <parameter>SYNC</parameter> variable
        in <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename>) as it might be
        possible that the rsync server you are synchronising with is
        corrupt.</para>

        <para>Another occurring problem can be that a particular file is
        missing:</para>

        <programlisting>!!! Fetch failed for sys-libs/ncurses-5.4-r5, continuing...
(...)
!!! Some fetch errors were encountered.  Please see above for details.</programlisting>

        <para>If your network connection is up and running, it is possible
        that the mirror where Portage wants to download the source code from
        is temporarily down. You can try again later or search for a different
        mirror (see the Gentoo Handbook for more information). If the file is
        really missing (i.e. other mirrors are also not hosting it), check
        <link xl:href="https://bugs.gentoo.org">https://bugs.gentoo.org</link>
        to see if this is a known issue.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Kernel configuration mismatch</title>

        <para>Some packages require certain kernel configurations. To ensure
        you don't install the packages without running a kernel with the right
        configurations, these packages verify your kernel configuration
        settings. If they find a mismatch, they will report it and abort the
        installation:</para>

        <programlisting>&gt;&gt;&gt; Emerging (1 of 1) net-wireless/broadcom-sta-5.60.48.36
...
 * Determining the location of the kernel source code
 * Found kernel source directory:
 *     /usr/src/linux
 * Found kernel object directory:
 *     /lib/modules/2.6.33-rc8/build
 * Found sources for kernel version:
 *     2.6.33-rc8
 * Checking for suitable kernel configuration options...
 *   CONFIG_WIRELESS_EXT:    is not set when it should be.
 *   CONFIG_WEXT_PRIV:    is not set when it should be.
 * Please check to make sure these options are set correctly.:
 *   Incorrect kernel configuration options</programlisting>

        <para>When such an error occurs, you will need to reconfigure your
        kernel to contain the appropriate configuration parameters (quick
        hint: during the kernel configuration process, search for the settings
        using the / help search system).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Multiple packages within a single package slot</title>

        <para>When software is being installed, Portage verifies if all
        requirements are met. This includes USE requirements that some
        packages have on others. For instance, kdelibs requires dbus, built
        with the USE="X" setting. If for some other reason dbus is being
        pulled in without X (an ebuild requires dbus without X, or you changed
        your USE flags to disallow X in USE), you might get the following
        error message:</para>

        <programlisting>!!! Multiple package instances within a single package slot have been pulled
!!! into the dependency graph, resulting in a slot conflict:

sys-apps/dbus:0

  ('ebuild', '/', 'sys-apps/dbus-1.2.24', 'merge') pulled in by
    &gt;=sys-apps/dbus-1.0.2 required by ('installed', '/', 'x11-libs/qt-dbus-4.6.2', 'nomerge')
    sys-apps/dbus required by ('installed', '/', 'app-misc/strigi-0.7.1', 'nomerge')
    &gt;=sys-apps/dbus-1.1 required by ('installed', '/', 'dev-libs/dbus-glib-0.86', 'nomerge')

  ('installed', '/', 'sys-apps/dbus-1.2.24', 'nomerge') pulled in by
    sys-apps/dbus[X] required by ('installed', '/', 'kde-base/kdelibs-4.4.5', 'nomerge')
    (and 3 more)

  Explanation:

    New USE for 'sys-apps/dbus:0' are incorrectly set. In order to solve
    this, adjust USE to satisfy 'sys-apps/dbus[X]'.</programlisting>

        <para>If this is due to a change in USE flags, undo the change (in the
        above case, setting USE to "-X" generally was a bad idea). If you need
        a particular USE setting, you can use /etc/portage/package.use to
        change the USE settings of one or more packages without affecting the
        entire system.</para>

        <para>If this due to packages with conflicting dependencies, you'll
        either need to drop one of the packages, or file a bug at <link
        xl:href="https://bugs.gentoo.org">https://bugs.gentoo.org</link> and ask
        for a proper solution.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Dependency required with different USE flags</title>

        <para>When a package has a dependency on another package, but requires
        this dependency to be build with some USE flags which you currently
        have not set, Portage will give you an appropriate error:</para>

        <programlisting>emerge: there are no ebuilds built with USE flags to 
satisfy "&gt;=x11-libs/qt-sql-4.5.0:4[mysql]".

!!! One of the following packages is required to complete your request:
- x11-libs/qt-sql-4.5.2 (Change USE: +mysql)

(dependency required by "app-office/akonadi-server-1.2.1" [ebuild])</programlisting>

        <para>In the above case, the package <package>akonadi-server</package>
        requires <package>qt-sql</package> (as a dependency) to be built with
        <parameter>USE="mysql"</parameter>.</para>

        <para>The solution: either add the requested USE flag to your global
        USE flags (in <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename>) or set the
        USE flag specifically for the selected package (in
        <filename>/etc/portage/package.use</filename>).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Other Issues</title>

        <para>A few other issues can come up:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>When a package depends on another package which isn't
            available, you will get a warning "<emphasis>there are no ebuilds
            to satisfy &lt;dependency&gt;</emphasis>". This shouldn't occur as
            this means an ebuild has a missing dependency or dependency which
            isn't available for you. If it does occur, please file a bug at
            <link
            xl:href="https://bugs.gentoo.org">https://bugs.gentoo.org</link>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>When two packages exist with the same name (but different
            category), you will get a warning that the name is ambiguous. In
            this case, Portage will ask you to specify the full name (category
            + packagename) and give you a list of candidates.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Resolving Build Failures</title>

      <para>One of the most troublesome issue is when a package fails to build
      properly. There can be a plethora on issues that is causing this, so
      this section is definitely going to be updated frequently. In any case,
      chances that you're the only one having the issue is very small, so a
      build failure now can be resolved if you sync and retry (say) a day
      later...</para>

      <section>
        <title>Catch-all solution: revdep-rebuild</title>

        <para>Before you start investigating possible build failures, run
        <command>revdep-rebuild</command> first. This tool will check and see
        if all library dependencies are still correct on your system. Really,
        this is a time-saver in case of most build errors. This tool is
        described more in-depth at <link linkend="revdep-rebuild">Dynamic
        Linking Inconsistency</link>.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>revdep-rebuild</command></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Missing .la file</title>

        <para>A .la file is a libtool archive file. Its use is becoming
        obsolete, so this error is most likely going to disappear in the near
        future. However, if you have an error similar to the following:</para>

        <programlisting>/bin/sh ../libtool --tag=CC   --mode=link i686-pc-linux-gnu-gcc  -O2 -march=pentium4 -pipe 
-fomit-frame-pointer -Wall -version-info 2600:1:2600 -export-symbols-regex "^pango_.*"   
-Wl,-O1 -o libpangocairo-1.0.la -rpath /usr/lib libpangocairo_1_0_la-pangocairo-context.lo 
libpangocairo_1_0_la-pangocairo-font.lo libpangocairo_1_0_la-pangocairo-fontmap.lo 
libpangocairo_1_0_la-pangocairo-render.lo  libpangocairo_1_0_la-pangocairo-fcfont.lo 
libpangocairo_1_0_la-pangocairo-fcfontmap.lo  libpango-1.0.la -lgobject-2.0 -lgmodule-2.0 
-lglib-2.0   -lcairo   -lm  libpangoft2-1.0.la -lfreetype   -lfontconfig   

grep: /usr/lib/libGL.la: No such file or directory
/bin/sed: can't read <emphasis>/usr/lib/libGL.la: No such file or directory</emphasis>
libtool: link: `/usr/lib/libGL.la' is not a valid libtool archive
make[4]: *** [libpangocairo-1.0.la] Error 1 </programlisting>

        <para>then running the lafilefixer command might help you out:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>emerge lafilefixer</command>
# <command>lafilefixer --justfixit</command></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Compiler errors</title>

        <para>Compiler errors are almost always due to a bug in the package
        itself, not your system. An example would be:</para>

        <programlisting>/var/tmp/portage/app-misc/lirc-0.8.6-r2/work/lirc-0.8.6/drivers/lirc_i2c/lirc_i2c.c:402:
<emphasis>error: unknown field 'id' specified in initializer</emphasis>
/var/tmp/portage/app-misc/lirc-0.8.6-r2/work/lirc-0.8.6/drivers/lirc_i2c/lirc_i2c.c:402:
warning: initialization makes pointer from integer without a cast
make[5]: ***
[/var/tmp/portage/app-misc/lirc-0.8.6-r2/work/lirc-0.8.6/drivers/lirc_i2c/lirc_i2c.o]
Error 1
make[4]: ***
[_module_/var/tmp/portage/app-misc/lirc-0.8.6-r2/work/lirc-0.8.6/drivers/lirc_i2c]
Error 2</programlisting>

        <para>The important part here is the error statement prefixed by the
        file name (usually ending in .c or .cpp) and a number (which is the
        line number in the file where the compiler found an error). Whenever
        you get such error messages, chances are that the package itself is
        broken. You should check <link xl:href="https://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo's
        Bugzilla</link> to see if it is a known error (usually is) and if a
        fix is already available (or a workaround).</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changing Configuration Files</title>

    <para>When Portage installs or upgrades software which provides
    configuration files, the files themselves aren't automatically updated.
    This is to prevent Portage from overwriting changes you made to the
    configuration files. However, package upgrades might require configuration
    file upgrades as well.</para>

    <note>
      <para>The setting that defines which locations are "protected" from
      automated updates and which aren't is the CONFIG_PROTECT (list of
      directories or files that are not automatically updated) and
      CONFIG_PROTECT_MASK (list of directories or files, inside those defined
      by CONFIG_PROTECT, which are automatically updated).</para>

      <para>Both variables are defined by the profile used by your system and
      expanded by the environment files offered by various applications and,
      optionally, the setting you gave inside
      <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename>.</para>
    </note>

    <para>To be able to identify possible configuration file upgrades, Portage
    warns you when configuration file updates are available. There are a few
    tools available that help you "merge" these updates with your existing
    configuration files. It is important to understand their limitations
    though.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Configuration File Updates</title>

      <para>Whenever a configuration file update is available, the file itself
      is stored on the file system next to the current configuration file.
      These files (whose file name starts with <filename>.cfg_</filename>) can
      then be compared with the current configuration file.</para>

      <para>There are no tools available that do this automatically for you.
      Most functionality that the tools provide is a view on the differences
      and the possibility to merge these changes automatically. In this book I
      describe the <command>dispatch-conf</command> tool. Another tool is
      etc-update.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>dispatch-conf</title>

      <para>The <command>dispatch-conf</command><indexterm>
          <primary>dispatch-conf</primary>
        </indexterm> tool allows you to view the differences between a
      configuration file and its update and merge updates automatically if the
      only differences are comments.</para>

      <para>To view the list of updates, launch
      <command>dispatch-conf</command>. It will first perform the automated
      updates and then show you the differences between the rest of the
      available updates:</para>

      <programlisting>--- /etc/conf.d/bootmisc           2007-12-26 14:41:35.000000000 +0100
+++ /etc/conf.d/._cfg0000_bootmisc 2008-02-29 18:40:02.000000000 +0100
@@ -9,4 +9,4 @@
# Should we completely wipe out /tmp or just selectively remove known
# locks / files / etc... ?
   
-WIPE_TMP="no"
+WIPE_TMP="yes"

&gt;&gt; (1 of 4) -- /etc/conf.d/bootmisc
&gt;&gt; q quit, h help, n next, e edit-new, z zap-new, u use-new
   m merge, t toggle-merge, l look-merge:</programlisting>

      <para>In this example, the <filename>/etc/conf.d/bootmisc</filename>
      file has an update where the <varname>WIPE_TMP</varname> variable is set
      to "yes". If you want to keep the "no" setting, press
      <command>z</command> (zap-new) to keep the current configuration file.
      If you want to use the "yes" value, press "<command>u</command>"
      (use-new) to use the new configuration file.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Modifying Build Decisions</title>

    <para>I have already covered the use of USE flags to help Portage decide
    which features you want (or don't want) in a package. However, there are
    more items that Portage needs to decide upon and you can offer your choice
    inside <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename><indexterm>
        <primary>make.conf</primary>
      </indexterm>, Portage' main configuration file.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Languages</title>

      <para>Some packages support several languages. Portage can help you
      select what languages you want supported on your system through the
      <varname>LINGUAS</varname><indexterm>
          <primary>LINGUAS</primary>
        </indexterm> variable. You set the LINGUAS variable in
      /etc/portage/make.conf with the languages of your choice. In the next
      example, I select the English (en), Dutch (nl), French (fr) and German
      (de) languages.</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>nano -w /etc/portage/make.conf</command>
LINGUAS="en nl fr de"</programlisting>

      <para>For instance, when enabled, OpenOffice.org's ebuild will pull in
      the language packs for those languages.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Video Cards</title>

      <para>Some packages might need video card information. Examples are the
      X11 server but also some games or rendering engines. In these cases, you
      should set the VIDEO_CARDS variable to your video card architecture. You
      might want to include several in case your architecture is quite new
      (you can then select the earlier architectures as well).</para>

      <programlisting>VIDEO_CARDS="i915 i810 intel vesa"</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="compilerdirectives">
      <title>Compiler Directives</title>

      <para>When building packages, Portage offers optimization directives to
      the compiler, telling the compiler for which architecture it should
      build and what optimizations the compiler can try to run. These
      optimization flags are set in the <varname>CFLAGS</varname><indexterm>
          <primary>CFLAGS</primary>
        </indexterm> (C-code) and <varname>CXXFLAGS</varname><indexterm>
          <primary>CXXFLAGS</primary>
        </indexterm> (C++-code) variables, again inside
      <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename>.</para>

      <para>I'll start off with my example CFLAGS (CXXFLAGS is the
      same):</para>

      <programlisting>CFLAGS="-O2 -march=native -pipe"
CXXFLAGS="${CFLAGS}"</programlisting>

      <para>Let's start off with the architecture selection: march. With
      <varname>-march=native</varname>, the compiler is asked to optimize code
      for the architecture of the current system (say a pentium 3
      architecture). Also, because I select <varname>-march=</varname>, it
      will only run on this architecture (or architectures that are backwards
      compatible with mine). If you want to optimize code for a specific
      architecture but want to be able to run the code on any x86
      architecture, use <varname>-mcpu=</varname> instead. You can also select
      a particular architecture, like "core2" or "nocona". A full list of
      supported architectures for the current GCC (make sure you are using the
      current one) is available <link
      xl:href="http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/gcc/i386-and-x86_002d64-Options.html">online</link>.</para>

      <para>With <varname>-O2</varname> (<emphasis>O</emphasis>ptimizations,
      not zero) I ask GCC to use a list of optimization flags (-O2 is
      shorthand for a whole set of optimizations) which are documented in the
      GCC info manual (<command>info gcc</command>, select <emphasis>Invoking
      GCC</emphasis>, <emphasis>Optimize Options</emphasis>).</para>

      <para>I also ask the compiler to pass on information between various
      stages of compilation using pipes (<parameter>-pipe</parameter>) rather
      than temporary files.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Portage Behaviour</title>

      <para>Portage itself also has a lot of features it supports. You can set
      them through the <parameter>FEATURES</parameter> variable.</para>

      <programlisting>FEATURES="sign buildpkg"</programlisting>

      <para>You can find all possible features in the
      <filename>make.conf</filename> manual page (<command>man
      make.conf</command>). A small selection of supported features is given
      next.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>buildpkg</parameter> creates binary packages of
          every succesful build. These binary packages can be reused, even on
          other systems (as long as they have the same build decision
          parameters).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>collision-protect</parameter> ensures that a
          package doesn't overwrite files during its installation that it
          doesn't own. You might want to use
          <parameter>protect-owned</parameter> instead (this is the default)
          as it allows overwriting files if they aren't currently owned by any
          package.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>nodoc</parameter> to tell Portage not to install
          doc files (/usr/share/doc), with <parameter>noinfo</parameter> and
          <parameter>noman</parameter> having similar functions</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>parallel-fetch</parameter> will have Portage
          download files in the background while it is building</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Fixing Postinstall Problems</title>

    <para>Even when software installation has finished successfully, you can
    still get into trouble.</para>

    <section xml:id="revdep-rebuild">
      <title>Dynamic Linking Inconsistency</title>

      <para>When Portage (prior to 2.2) upgrades a library, it removes the old
      shared libraries from the system. As a result, some applications who
      rely on these libraries might fail with a message like the
      following:</para>

      <programlisting>error while loading shared libraries: libcom_err.so.2: cannot
  open object file: no such file or directory</programlisting>

      <para>If this is the case, you will need to run
      <command>revdep-rebuild</command><indexterm>
          <primary>revdep-rebuild</primary>
        </indexterm> to fix this. <command>revdep-rebuild</command> is a tool
      that scans your system for applications that rely on (removed) libraries
      and will rebuild those packages so that they get linked with the new
      libraries.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Exercises</title>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Portage is not the only package manager that works on Gentoo.
        There are at least two others. Look up what these packages are and
        where they differ with Portage.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>USE flags can also be enabled as an environment variable during
        your emerge process itself, like so:</para>

        <programlisting>~# <command>USE="-ssl" emerge irssi</command></programlisting>

        <para>Try to find out where Portage reads all possible USE flags from
        (you know <filename>make.conf</filename> and environment variable now,
        but there are others) and in what order.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Try to find information regarding Gentoo's architecture testing
        program.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
