<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>User Management</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Linux is a multi-user operating system. Even systems that will be
    used by a single user are configured as a multi-user system. This has
    various advantages:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>security-wise, your system is protected from malicious software
        execution as the software is executed as an unprivileged user rather
        than the system administrator</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>if at any time multiple users are going to work on the system,
        you just need to add the user to the system (no need to upgrade to a
        multi-user environment first)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>you can easily back up all files belonging to a particular user
        as all user files are located inside his home directory</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>if you messed up your personal configuration for a particular
        software title, you can just remove the configuration files (or move
        them aside) and start the software title up again to start with a
        clean slate. No configuration changes made by a user are propagated
        system-wide</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>How you deal with this multi-user environment depends on your
    needs...</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Adding or Removing Users</title>

    <para>If your system is used by various users, you will need to add or
    remove their user accounts. Before starting with the command syntax, first
    a few words on how this information is stored on the Linux system.</para>

    <section>
      <title>User Account Information</title>

      <para>A user is identified by his user id, which is an ordinary integer
      number. However, it is much easier to use a user name instead of a
      number. For this purpose, a Unix/Linux system maps a user name to a user
      id. By default, this information is stored within the
      <filename>/etc/passwd</filename><indexterm>
          <primary>passwd</primary>

          <secondary>file</secondary>
        </indexterm> file. However, you can also configure your system to
      obtain this information from a central repository (like an LDAP
      service), similar to how Windows can be configured to connect to an
      Active Directory.</para>

      <section>
        <title id="passwdfile">The passwd file</title>

        <para>The <filename>passwd</filename> file contains a line for every
        user. Each line contains 7 fields, separated by colons:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Username</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Password, or "x" if the password is stored elsewhere</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>User ID</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Primary group ID</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Comment or description</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Home directory</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Default shell</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The <emphasis>password field</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>password</primary>

            <secondary>passwd file</secondary>
          </indexterm> on modern systems contains an "x", telling the system
        that the password is stored inside the
        <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file. Storing the passwords elsewhere
        is needed to improve the security of the system: the
        <filename>passwd</filename> file should be world readable because many
        tools rely on it. Storing the password (even when it is encrypted or
        hashed) in a publicly readable file is asking for troubles - tools
        exist that attempt to crack user account passwords given the encrypted
        / hashed password values.</para>

        <para>For this reason, the hashed password is stored inside the
        <filename>/etc/shadow</filename> file which is only readable by the
        root user (system administrator). The tools that work with passwords
        are small in number and highly audited to decrease the chance that
        they contain any vulnerabilities. More about the shadow file
        later...</para>

        <para>As you will see in the next section, a user can be a member of
        many groups. However, every user has a single, <emphasis>primary
        group</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>primary group</primary>
          </indexterm>: this is the active group at the moment that the user
        is logged on. The active group defines the group ownership of the
        resources the user creates while logged on (remember, resources are
        assigned three ownership groups: user, group and others).</para>

        <para>The users' <emphasis>home directory</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>home directory</primary>
          </indexterm> is usually the directory where the user has full write
        access to (even more, it is most often the <emphasis>only</emphasis>
        directory where the user has write access to). If a user is logged on
        through the command line (not graphically), it is also the directory
        where the user starts to work from.</para>

        <para>Finally, the default <emphasis>shell</emphasis> for this
        particular user is defined. We've talked about what a shell is before.
        Unix/Linux has several shells, each shell provides roughly the same
        functionality, but is manipulated differently. Gentoo Linux by default
        uses the bash<indexterm>
            <primary>bash</primary>
          </indexterm> shell (bourne again shell), a powerfull shell with lots
        of additional functions such as command autocompletion, output
        colouring and more. Smaller shells also exist, such as csh (c shell) or
        ksh (korn shell).</para>

        <para>More information about shells is available online.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The shadow file</title>

        <para>The <filename>shadow</filename> file<indexterm>
            <primary>shadow</primary>

            <secondary>file</secondary>
          </indexterm> contains all information regarding a users' password.
        The most important field for many is the (hashed) password itself, but
        other information is available as well. The shadow file, like the
        passwd file, has a single line for every user; fields are separated by
        colons.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Username</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Hashed password value</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Date of last password change (counted in days since Jan 1,
            1970)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Number of days that need to pass before the password can be
            changed by the user</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Maximum number of days since the password change that the
            password can be used; after this amount of days, the password will
            need to be changed by the user</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Number of days before expiry date (see field 5) that the
            user will be warned about the pending password change
            policy</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the password isn't changed after this many days after the
            forced password change, the account is locked</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Date when the account is (or will be) locked (counted in
            days since Jan 1, 1970)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Reserved field (not used)</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>If the last three fields are left empty (which is the default
        case), their enforcement isn't valid.</para>

        <para>The password value is <emphasis>hashed</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>hash function</primary>
          </indexterm>, meaning that the password itself is not stored on the
        disk (nor in any encrypted form). Instead, a mathematical formula is
        used to create a unique number or string from a password. To verify if
        a password given by a user matches, the given password is passed
        through the same mathematical formula and the resulting number or
        string is matched against the stored string. Such method makes it
        harder for a user to find out the password even if he has access to
        the shadow file because he can't deduce the password from the hash
        value.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Other account storage: nsswitch.conf</title>

        <para>Account information can be stored elsewhere - any repository
        will do, as long as it provides at least the same information as the
        passwd (and shadow) file. This is important because in enterprise
        environments, you rather want to keep track of user accounts in a
        central repository rather than in the files on several hundreds of
        systems.</para>

        <para>The <filename>/etc/nsswitch.conf</filename><indexterm>
            <primary>nsswitch.conf</primary>
          </indexterm> file defines where the system can find this
        information. An excerpt from an nsswitch.conf file is given below. You
        notice that it defines services on every line followed by the
        repository (or repositories) that manages the information.</para>

        <programlisting>passwd: compat
shadow: compat
group: compat
hosts: files dns</programlisting>

        <para>In the example, the passwd, shadow and group services are
        managed by the "compat" implementation. Compat is the default
        implementation provided by glibc (GNU C Library) which offers access
        to the various <filename>/etc/*</filename> files. The hosts service
        (used to resolve host names to IP addresses and vice versa) is managed
        by two implementations:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>"files", which is the implementation that offers access to
            the /etc/hosts file (a table containing IP address and
            host name(s))</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>"dns", which is the implementation that offers queries with
            DNS servers</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Group Information</title>

      <para>Group membership is used to group different users who need access
      to a shared resource: assign the resource to a particular group and add
      the users to this group.</para>

      <section>
        <title>The /etc/group file</title>

        <para>Similar with the /etc/passwd file, group information is stored
        inside the /etc/group. Again, every line in this text file defines a
        group; the fields within a group definition are separated by a
        colon.</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Group name</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Group password, or "x" if the password is stored
            elsewhere</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Group ID</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Group members (who don't have the group as a primary
            group)</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>It might seem strange to have a password on a group. After all,
        a user logs on using his user name. However, there is a sane reason for
        this: you can add users to a different group and password-protect this
        group. If a user is logged on to the system (but doesn't use the
        particular group as primary group) and leaves his terminal, malicious
        users can't change to this particular group without knowing the
        password even if they have access to the users' terminal (and
        therefore logged on session).</para>

        <para>Group passwords aren't used often though. The cases where group
        passwords can be used (privileged groups) are usually implemented
        differently (for instance using privilege escalation tools like
        sudo).</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating or Deleting Users</title>

      <section>
        <title>The useradd command</title>

        <para>If you want to add a user to the system, you can use the
        <command>useradd</command><indexterm>
            <primary>useradd</primary>
          </indexterm> command (you'll need to be root to perform this
        action):</para>

        <programlisting># <command>useradd -D thomas</command></programlisting>

        <para>In the above example, a user account identified by "thomas" is
        created using the system default settings (which, for a Gentoo Linux
        system, means that the default shell is bash, the home directory is
        /home/thomas, etc) after which his password is set.</para>

        <para>You can pass on additional arguments to the useradd command to
        alter the users' attributes (such as the user id, home directory,
        primary group ...). I encourage you to read the useradd manual page
        for more information.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The userdel command</title>

        <para>If a user account needs to be removed from the system, you can
        use the <command>userdel</command><indexterm>
            <primary>userdel</primary>
          </indexterm> command.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>userdel -r thomas</command></programlisting>

        <para>With the <command>-r</command> option,
        <command>userdel</command> not only removes the user account from the
        system but also cleans and removes the users' home directory. If you
        omit this option, the users' home directory remains available on the
        system, allowing you to keep his (private or not) files for future
        use.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The usermod command</title>

        <para>To manipulate an existing account, you can use the
        <command>usermod</command><indexterm>
            <primary>usermod</primary>
          </indexterm> command. For instance, to modify the primary group of
        the thomas account to the "localusers" group:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>usermod -g localusers thomas</command></programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adding or Removing Users to/from Groups</title>

      <para>Once a user account is created, you can't use
      <command>useradd</command> to add the user to one or more groups.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Creating or Deleting Groups</title>

        <para>First of all, if a group doesn't exist yet, you'll need to
        create it: the <command>groupadd</command><indexterm>
            <primary>groupadd</primary>
          </indexterm> command does this for you. Similarly, to remove a group
        from the system, you can use <command>groupdel</command><indexterm>
            <primary>groupdel</primary>
          </indexterm>.</para>

        <warning>
          <para>You will be able to remove groups even though there are still
          users member of this group. The only check that groupdel performs is
          to see if a group is a users' primary group (in which case the
          operation fails).</para>
        </warning>

        <programlisting># <command>groupadd audio</command></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Manipulating Group Membership</title>

        <para>Suppose you want to add or remove a user from a group, you can
        use the <command>usermod</command> tool (as seen before) or the
        <command>gpasswd</command> tool.</para>

        <para>The <command>gpasswd</command><indexterm>
            <primary>gpasswd</primary>
          </indexterm> tool is the main tool used to manipulate the group
        file. For instance, to add a user to a particular group (in the
        example the "audio" group):</para>

        <programlisting># <command>gpasswd -a audio thomas</command></programlisting>

        <para>Most resources on a Unix system are protected by a particular
        group: you need to be a member of a particular group in order to
        access those resources. The following tables gives an overview of
        interesting groups.</para>

        <table>
          <title>Incomplete (!) list of system groups</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center">Group name</entry>

                <entry align="center">Description / resources</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>wheel</entry>

                <entry>Be able to "<command>su -</command>" to switch to the
                root user</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>audio</entry>

                <entry>Be able to use the sound card on the system</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>video</entry>

                <entry>Be able to use the graphical card for hardware
                rendering purposes (not needed for plain 2D
                operations)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>cron</entry>

                <entry>Be able to use the system scheduler (cron)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>cdrom</entry>

                <entry>Be able to mount a CD/DVD</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting and Changing Passwords</title>

      <para>The <command>passwd</command> command allows you to change or set
      an accounts' password.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>passwd thomas</command>
New UNIX password: <emphasis>(enter thomas' password)</emphasis>
Retype new UNIX password: <emphasis>(re-enter thomas' password)</emphasis>
passwd: password updated succesfully</programlisting>

      <para>The root user is always able to alter a users' password. If a user
      wants to change his own password, the passwd command will first ask the
      user to enter his current password (to make sure it is the user and not
      someone who took the users' session in the users' absence) before
      prompting to enter the new password.</para>

      <para>With the tool, you can also immediately expire the users' password
      (<command>-e</command>), lock or unlock the account
      (<command>-l</command> or <command>-u</command>) and more. In effect,
      this tool allows you to manipulate the <filename>/etc/shadow</filename>
      file.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Elevating User Privileges</title>

    <para>On any system, a regular user has little to no rights to perform
    administrative tasks. However, on a home workstation you'd probably want
    to be able to shut down the system. You can log on as the root user on a
    different (virtual) terminal, but you can also elevate your own
    privileges...</para>

    <section>
      <title>Switching User</title>

      <para>With the <command>su</command><indexterm>
          <primary>su</primary>
        </indexterm> command you can switch your user identity in the selected
      session.</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>su -</command>
Password: <emphasis>(Enter the root password)</emphasis>
# </programlisting>

      <para>In the above example, a regular user has switched his session to
      become a root session. The "<command>-</command>" argument informs the
      su command that not only the users' privileges should be switched, but
      also that the root users' environment should be loaded. Without the
      "<command>-</command>" option, the regular users' environment would be
      used.</para>

      <para>This environment defines the shell behaviour; its most important
      setting is the PATH variable which defines where the binaries are
      located for the commands that this user might summon.</para>

      <para>With su, you can also switch to a different user:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>su thomas -</command>
Password: (Enter thomas' password)
$ </programlisting>

      <para>If you just want to execute a single command as a different user,
      you can use the "-c" argument:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>su -c "shutdown -h now"</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Assigning Specific Privileged Commands</title>

      <para>The su-based methods require the user to know the password of the
      other accounts. On many systems, you might not want this. There are two
      ways of dealing with such situations: marking a command so that it
      always runs as a privileged user, or use a tool that elevates privileges
      without requiring the password for the elevated privilege...</para>

      <section>
        <title>Marking Commands for Elevated Execution</title>

        <para>Executable binaries (not shell scripts) can be marked so that
        the Unix/Linux kernel executes that command as a specific user,
        regardless of who started the command. This mark is the
        <emphasis>setuid</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>setuid</primary>
          </indexterm> bit. Once set (using the chmod command), the tool is
        always executed with the rights of the owner and not the rights of the
        executor:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>chmod +s /path/to/command</command></programlisting>

        <warning>
          <para>Using setuid tools is generally considered a security risk. It
          is better to avoid setuid tools when possible and use tools such as
          sudo, as explained later.</para>
        </warning>

        <para>For instance, if the shutdown command is marked setuid, then
        every user is able to run the shutdown command as root (which is the
        commands' owner) and thus be able to shut down or reboot the
        system.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Using sudo</title>

        <para>If you mark an executable using the setuid bit, every user can
        execute the command as the application owner (root). You usually don't
        want to allow this but rather assign the necessary rights on a
        per-user, per-command basis. Enter sudo.</para>

        <para>The <command>sudo</command><indexterm>
            <primary>sudo</primary>
          </indexterm> tool allows the system administrator to grant a set of
        users (individually or through groups) the rights to execute one or
        more commands as a different user (such as root), with or without
        requiring their password (for the same reason as the passwd command
        which asks the users' password before continuing).</para>

        <para>Once available, the system administrator can run the
        <command>visudo</command><indexterm>
            <primary>visudo</primary>
          </indexterm> command to edit the configuration file. In the next
        example, the following definitions are set:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>All users in the wheel group are allowed to execute any
            command as root</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All users in the operator group are allowed to shut down the
            system</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The test user is allowed to run a script called webctl.ksh
            without a password</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All users in the httpd group are allowed to edit the
            /etc/apache2/conf/httpd.conf file through sudoedit</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <programlisting>%wheel    ALL=(ALL) ALL
%operator ALL=/sbin/shutdown
test      ALL=NOPASSWD: /usr/local/bin/webctl.ksh
%httpd    ALL=(ALL) sudoedit /etc/apache2/conf/httpd.conf</programlisting>

        <para>If sudo is set up, users can execute commands by prepending
        <command>sudo</command> to it. If allowed, some users can even obtain
        a root shell through the <command>sudo -i</command> command.</para>

        <programlisting><emphasis>(Execute a single command as root)</emphasis>
$ <command>sudo mount /media/usb</command>
Enter password: <emphasis>(unless configured with NOPASSWD)</emphasis>
<emphasis>(Obtain a root shell)</emphasis>
$ <command>sudo -i</command>
Enter password: <emphasis>(unless configured with NOPASSWD)</emphasis>
# </programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Exercises</title>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>When invoking commands using sudo, sudo logs every attempt
        (including user name, working directory and command itself). Where is
        this log?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
