<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Service Management</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>A <emphasis>service</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>service</primary>
      </indexterm> is a generic term which can be used in many contexts. Here,
    a service is a tool that runs in the background (also known as a
    <emphasis>daemon</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>daemon</primary>
      </indexterm>) which offers a certain functionality to the system or to
    the users. It is also possible that the tool just performs a single set of
    tasks and then quits.</para>

    <para>Examples of services on a Linux system are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the logger service, allowing programs on the system to send
        logging notifications to a global location which is then parsed and
        processed by a logger tool (example: syslog-ng).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the clock service, which sets the necessary environmental
        definitions (like time zone information)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the SSH service, allowing users to log on to your system
        remotely (through the secure shell)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>...</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The scripts that manipulate the services are called <emphasis>init
    scripts</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>init scripts</primary>
      </indexterm> (initialization scripts) and reside inside
    <filename>/etc/init.d</filename>. Although this is quite generic for all
    Linux distributions, Gentoo offers a somewhat different way of working
    with services, so not all activities mentioned in this chapter can be used
    for other distributions.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Services at System Boot / Shutdown</title>

    <para>When your system boots, the Linux kernel starts a process called
    <command>init</command>. This tool executes a set of tasks defined by the
    various init levels on the system. Each init level defines a set of
    services to start (or stop) at this stage.</para>

    <para>Within Gentoo, init levels are mapped onto named runlevels.</para>

    <para>When init is launched, it will first run the sysinit and bootwait
    init levels. On Gentoo, the associated runlevels are also called sysinit
    and boot (sysinit is not configurable). Then, it will start the services
    for the runlevel it is configured to boot into (by default, init level 3).
    This init level at Gentoo is mapped onto the "default" runlevel.</para>

    <para>For instance, the following services are launched when I start my
    laptop (sysinit not shown, but sysinit is always launched).</para>

    <programlisting># <command>rc-status boot</command>
Runlevel: boot
 alsasound        [ started ]
 bootmisc         [ started ]
 checkfs          [ started ]
 checkroot        [ started ]
 clock            [ started ]
 consolefont      [ started ]
 hostname         [ started ]
 keymaps          [ started ]
 localmount       [ started ]
 modules          [ started ]
 net.lo           [ started ]
 rmnologin        [ started ]
 urandom          [ started ]
# <command>rc-status default</command>
Runlevel: default
 hald                 [ started  ]
 local                [ started  ]
 net.eth0             [ started  ]
 net.eth1             [ stopped  ]
 sshd                 [ started  ]
 syslog-ng            [ started  ]
 udev-postmount       [ started  ]
 xdm                  [ started  ]</programlisting>

    <para>As you can see, all configured services for the two runlevels (boot
    and default) are launched but one: net.eth1 isn't started (because it is
    my wireless interface and I'm currently on a cabled network which uses
    net.eth0).</para>

    <para>The init configuration file is called
    <filename>/etc/inittab</filename><indexterm>
        <primary>inittab</primary>
      </indexterm>. The next excerpt is not a full
    <filename>inittab</filename> but explains most important settings:</para>

    <programlisting>id:3:initdefault:            # The default init level is 3
si::sysinit:/sbin/rc sysinit # sysinit       &gt; run the Gentoo "sysinit" runlevel
rc::bootwait:/sbin/rc boot   # bootwait      &gt; run the Gentoo "boot" runlevel
l0:0:wait:/sbin/rc shutdown  # init level 0  &gt; run the Gentoo "shutdown" runlevel
l1:S1:wait:/sbin/rc single   # init level S1 &gt; run the Gentoo "single" runlevel
l3:3:wait:/sbin/rc default   # init level 3  &gt; run the Gentoo "default" runlevel
l6:6:wait:/sbin/rc reboot    # init level 6  &gt; run the Gentoo "reboot" runlevel</programlisting>

    <para>Okay, so in the end, init uses Gentoo's runlevels. How do you
    configure those?</para>

    <section>
      <title>Init Scripts</title>

      <para>An init script is a script that manipulates a particular service.
      It should support the "start" and "stop" arguments as these are used by
      the <command>init</command> tool (actually the
      <command>rc</command><indexterm>
          <primary>rc</primary>
        </indexterm> tool which is called by <command>init</command>). For
      instance:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>/etc/init.d/udhcp start</command>
# <command>/etc/init.d/syslog-ng stop</command></programlisting>

      <para>As you can see, the scripts reside in the
      <filename>/etc/init.d</filename> directory. These scripts are usually
      provided by the tools themselves (udhcp and syslog-ng in our examples)
      but sometimes you might need to write one yourself. Luckily, this is
      less and less the case.</para>

      <para>Next to directly executing the scripts, you can also use the
      <command>rc-service</command><indexterm><primary>rc-service</primary></indexterm>
      tool:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>rc-service syslog-ng start</command></programlisting>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Gentoo Runlevels</title>

      <para>Inside <filename>/etc/runlevels</filename>, Gentoo keeps track of
      the various scripts that need to be started when init starts a specific
      init level (which maps onto a Gentoo runlevel):</para>

      <programlisting># <command>ls /etc/runlevels</command>
boot   default   nonetwork   single</programlisting>

      <para>Inside the directories you get an overview of the services that
      should be started when the runlevel is active. For instance, inside the
      default runlevel one could see:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>ls /etc/runlevels/default</command>
local  net.eth0   net.wlan0   syslog-ng     xdm</programlisting>

      <para>The files found inside these directories are symbolic links,
      pointing to the associated init script found inside /etc/init.d:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>ls -l /etc/runlevels/default/local</command>
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 17 Jul 12   2004 
  /etc/runlevels/default/local -&gt; /etc/init.d/local</programlisting>

      <para>To manipulate the Gentoo runlevels, you can manipulate the
      symbolic links inside these directories directly, but you can also use
      the tools rc-update, rc-config and rc-status.</para>

      <para>With <command>rc-update</command><indexterm>
          <primary>rc-update</primary>
        </indexterm>, you can add or delete links from a particular runlevel.
      For instance, to remove the xdm init script from the default
      runlevel:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>rc-update del xdm default</command></programlisting>

      <para>With <command>rc-status</command><indexterm>
          <primary>rc-status</primary>
        </indexterm>, you can see what scripts should be started in the
      selected runlevel and the current state. The next example shows that the
      net.eth0 runlevel is not started currently even though it is a service
      for the default runlevel (the reason is simple: I deactivated it as I
      don't need the interface currently):</para>

      <programlisting># <command>rc-status default</command>
Runlevel: default
 local                                      [started]
 net.eth0                                   [stopped]
 net.wlan0                                  [started]
 syslog-ng                                  [started]
 xdm                                        [started]</programlisting>

      <para>With <command>rc-config</command><indexterm>
          <primary>rc-config</primary>
        </indexterm>, you can manipulate the runlevels (just like with
      <command>rc-update</command>), show the current status of a particular
      runlevel (just like with <command>rc-status</command>) and view all
      currently available init scripts and the runlevels in which they are
      available (actually, <command>rc-update</command> can also do this using
      <command>rc-update show</command>):</para>

      <programlisting># <command>rc-config list</command>
(...)</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>List of Default Services</title>

      <para>When a pristine Gentoo install has finished, you will already have
      quite a few services available. The following sections give a quick
      overview of those services and what they stand for.</para>

      <section>
        <title>alsasound</title>

        <para>The alsasound<indexterm>
            <primary>alsasound</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for loading the appropriate
        sound kernel modules (if they are known as modules) and
        saving/restoring the sound configuration at boot-up / shut
        down.</para>

        <para>When the service is started, you might see kernel modules being
        loaded in memory. However, no other processes are started as part of
        this service.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>bootmisc</title>

        <para>The bootmisc<indexterm>
            <primary>bootmisc</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for various boot-level
        activities, such as:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>loading the kernel parameters from
            <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename><indexterm>
                <primary>sysctl.conf</primary>
              </indexterm>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>cleaning up directories to ensure they don't contain rogue
            information that might hinder the bootup</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>create, if they don't exist, system files with the correct
            permissions</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>checkfs</title>

        <para>The checkfs<indexterm>
            <primary>checkfs</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for verifying the integrity of
        your systems' file systems. By default, it will verify the integrity
        of the file systems whose last digit in
        <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> isn't zero. You can force a root file
        system check by adding the <parameter>forcefsck</parameter><indexterm>
            <primary>forcefsck</primary>
          </indexterm> boot parameter or force a full file system check for
        all partitions (listed in the fstab file) by creating an empty
        "/forcefsck" file. This file will be automatically removed once the
        check has been finished.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>touch /forcefsck</command></programlisting>

        <para>On the other hand, if you want to ignore the file system checks,
        create the <filename>/fastboot</filename><indexterm>
            <primary>fastboot</primary>
          </indexterm> file. It too will be automatically removed, this time
        when the system has booted.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>checkroot</title>

        <para>The checkroot<indexterm>
            <primary>checkroot</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for checking the consistency of
        the root file system. This service uses the same boot parameters
        (forcefsck or fastboot) as the checkfs service.</para>

        <para>The service is also responsible for remounting the root file
        system read-write (by default it gets mounted read-only by the Linux
        kernel).</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>clock</title>

        <para>The clock<indexterm>
            <primary>clock</primary>

            <secondary>service</secondary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for setting the system time
        based on the BIOS clock and the settings defined in
        <filename>/etc/conf.d/clock</filename>. It will also synchronise the
        system clock with your hardware clock during shut down.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>consolefont</title>

        <para>The consolefont<indexterm>
            <primary>consolefont</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for setting the console
        font.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>hald</title>

        <para>The hald<indexterm>
            <primary>hald</primary>

            <secondary>service</secondary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for starting the hardware
        abstraction layer daemon (see <link linkend="HAL">HAL</link>).</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, you will find the hald
        process running as the haldaemon user.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>host name</title>

        <para>The host name<indexterm>
            <primary>host name</primary>

            <secondary>service</secondary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for setting your systems' host
        name based on the input of
        <filename>/etc/conf.d/hostname</filename>.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>keymaps</title>

        <para>The keymaps<indexterm>
            <primary>keymaps</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for setting your keyboard
        mapping (qwerty, azerty, dvorak, ...) based on the
        <filename>/etc/conf.d/keymaps</filename> file.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>local</title>

        <para>The local<indexterm>
            <primary>local</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for handling the scripts defined 
	  in <filename>/etc/local.d</filename>. The scripts, with suffix
	  <filename>.start</filename> or <filename>.stop</filename>, are executed
	  in lexical order (of course during start or stop of the system, depending
	  on the suffix).
	</para>
	
	<para>The local service is started as the last service before you can log on 
	to your system. It is also the first one to be stopped when the system is 
	shutting down.</para>

        <para>As you completely manage what this service does, I can't tell
        you what will happen when the service has finished starting. By
        default however, it doesn't do anything.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>localmount</title>

        <para>The localmount<indexterm>
            <primary>localmount</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for mounting all local file
        systems (mentioned in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>). It also
        initiates the necessary support for USB file systems, specific binary
        format file systems, security file systems and enabling the swap file
        system.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>modules</title>

        <para>The modules<indexterm>
            <primary>modules</primary>

            <secondary>service</secondary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for automatically loading the
        kernel modules listed in
        <filename>/etc/modules.autoload</filename><indexterm>
            <primary>modules.autoload</primary>
          </indexterm>.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>net.lo (net.*)</title>

        <para>The net.lo<indexterm>
            <primary>net.lo</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for loading networking support
        for a specific interface. Although the name suggests that it only
        supports the lo (loopback) interface, the service actually supports
        any interface. Other interface scripts are just symbolic links to this
        script.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>rmnologin</title>

        <para>The rmnologin<indexterm>
            <primary>rmnologin</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for changing the state of your
        system from a non-logon-capable system (set by the bootmisc service)
        to a logon-capable one. This is needed to ensure no-one can log on to
        your system while important services are being loaded.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>sshd</title>

        <para>The sshd<indexterm>
            <primary>sshd</primary>

            <secondary>service</secondary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for launching the secure shell
        daemon, which allows you to access your system from a remote location
        (as long as the network / firewalls permit it) in a secure
        manner.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, you will find the sshd
        process running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>syslog-ng (or any other system logger service)</title>

        <para>The syslog-ng<indexterm>
            <primary>syslog-ng</primary>

            <secondary>service</secondary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for starting the syslog-ng
        daemon, which is responsible for watching the
        <filename>/dev/log</filename> socket for log events and managing those
        events by dispatching them towards the right log file (or other log
        server).</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, you will find the
        syslog-ng process running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>udev-postmount</title>

        <para>The udev-postmount<indexterm>
            <primary>udev-postmount</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for re-evaluating udev events
        between the moment udev was started and the moment udev-postmount is
        started which might have failed for any reason (for instance because
        not everything was up and running yet).</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>urandom</title>

        <para>The urandom<indexterm>
            <primary>urandom</primary>
          </indexterm> service is responsible for initializing the random
        number generator in a somewhat more secure manner (using a random seed
        obtained during the last shut down of the system). Without this, the
        random number generator would be a bit more predictable.</para>

        <para>Once the service has finished starting, no additional processes
        will be running.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Service Configurations</title>

    <section>
      <title>General Service Configuration</title>

      <para>Gentoo's general configuration file for the start-up service
      behaviour is <filename>/etc/rc.conf</filename>.</para>

      <section>
        <title>/etc/rc.conf</title>

        <para>Inside the <filename>rc.conf</filename> file, generic settings
        which are (or might be) needed by several services can be configured.
        The syntax is, as usual, "key=value". Since openrc (new init system
        for Gentoo), all settings are bundled in this file. Earlier systems
        spread the configuration across <filename>/etc/rc.conf</filename> and
        <filename>/etc/conf.d/rc</filename>. The latter is now
        deprecated.</para>

        <para>The file is pretty well documented.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Specific Service Configuration</title>

      <para>Each system service within Gentoo can be configured using a file
      in <filename>/etc/conf.d</filename> which is named the same as the
      service itself (except in a few specific cases like network
      configurations, which use the <filename>/etc/conf.d/net</filename>
      configuration file). All these files use a key=value syntax for
      configuration purposes.</para>

      <para>For instance, the <command>/etc/init.d/clock</command> init script
      can be configured using the <filename>/etc/conf.d/clock</filename>
      configuration file.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Softlevel States</title>

      <para>Gentoo supports softlevels, which are specific configurations of
      one or more services. The need exists, because you might create
      different runlevels (say "work" and "home" instead of just "default") in
      which services need to be configured differently. As the services would
      only use their general configuration file, this wouldn't work.</para>

      <para>To initiate softlevels, you need to specify
      "softlevel=&lt;yoursoftlevel&gt;" at the kernel option line (for
      instance, in GRUB, this means you add it to grub.conf's kernel line).
      Once set, Gentoo will try to start the softlevel given instead of the
      default runlevel (coincidentally named "default") and first look for
      configurations of this softlevel for each service. If it cannot find
      specific configurations, it will use the default one.</para>

      <para>An example use of softlevels would be to define a softlevel "work"
      and a softlevel "home". Both initiate different settings, such as
      different networking settings, different clock settings, different
      crypto-loop settings, etc. This could result in the following two GRUB
      configuration entries:</para>

      <programlisting>title=Gentoo Linux @Home
kernel /kernel-2.6.31 root=/dev/sda2 softlevel=home

title=Gentoo Linux @Work
kernel /kernel-2.6.31 root=/dev/sda2 softlevel=work</programlisting>

      <para>Whenever a service is started (or stopped), it will look for its
      configuration file called
      <filename>/etc/conf.d/&lt;servicename&gt;.&lt;softlevel&gt;</filename>
      (for instance, <filename>/etc/conf.d/clock.work</filename>) and if that
      doesn't exist, use the default one (for instance,
      <filename>/etc/conf.d/clock</filename>).</para>

      <para>To finish the softlevel, create a new runlevel with the
      softlevels' name:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>mkdir /etc/runlevels/work</command></programlisting>

      <para>Finish up by adding the services you need to this runlevel.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bootlevel States</title>

      <para>The idea behind bootlevel is the same as softlevel, but instead of
      changing the default runlevel "default", you change the default boot
      runlevel "boot".</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
