<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Storage Management</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Within Linux, the file system the user sees acts regardless of the
    underlying storage used (hard disk partitions, CD/DVD, removable USB disk,
    remote file systems). You assign a location of the file system to the
    storage medium and you're up and running.</para>

    <para>I've already covered the <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> file, where
    you can map these locations and media. In this chapter, I'll cover the
    various media, how you can create and manage them as well as assign them
    in the <filename>fstab</filename> file.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title id="hdpartitions">Hard Disk Partitions</title>

    <para>The most common storage is a hard disk partition. I'll only cover
    the x86 partitions as those are most used at this moment.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Partition Layout</title>

      <para>The x86 partition layout only allows for at most 4 partitions
      called <emphasis>primary partitions</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>partition</primary>

          <secondary>primary</secondary>
        </indexterm>. At the time the x86 partition layout was designed, this
      was thought to be sufficient. However, time has proven the assumption
      wrong. Luckily, the x86 partition layout has a way of working around
      this restriction: you can designate one partition as a "container"
      partition which holds other partitions. This container partition is
      called the <emphasis>extended partition</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>partition</primary>

          <secondary>extended</secondary>
        </indexterm>. The partitions inside this extended partition are called
      <emphasis>logical partitions</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>partition</primary>

          <secondary>logical</secondary>
        </indexterm>.</para>

      <para>Linux gives a number to a partition based on their type: primary
      partitions (including the extended partition) are numbered 1 to 4;
      logical partitions start at 5 and can, theoretically, sum up to infinity
      (if you have an infinite amount of disk space, that is). On Linux, you
      can create up to 63 partitions per disk.</para>

      <para>If you do not need more than 4 partitions, you can stick with the
      primary partitions. However, if you need more than 4 partitions, make
      sure you create one extended partition (which holds all disk space) and
      then create additional logical partitions inside this extended
      partition.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Partitioning a Disk</title>

      <para>To partition a disk, you can use tools such as
      <command>fdisk</command>, <command>cfdisk</command>,
      <command>sfdisk</command>, <command>parted</command>, ... Of course,
      there are graphical tools as well (such as <command>qtparted</command>).
      In this section, I'll cover the use of
      <command>fdisk</command><indexterm>
          <primary>fdisk</primary>
        </indexterm> as it is a simple command-line tool (making it easy to
      add the input/output in this book) which is well supported and fully
      featured.</para>

      <para>In the next paragraphs, I'm going to partition the
      <filename>/dev/sda</filename> disk (<filename>/dev/sda</filename> is
      Linux' representation of the first (<filename>a</filename>) SCSI/SATA
      (<filename>sd</filename>) disk). The second SCSI/SATA disk would be
      called <filename>/dev/sdb</filename>, third
      <filename>/dev/sdc</filename>, ...</para>

      <para>IDE disks are called <filename>/dev/hda</filename> (b, c, d, ...).
      Unlike SCSI/SATA disks, IDE disks are labelled based upon their position
      in the computer. Every IDE controller (which is where the disks are
      attached to) has a certain position in the computer. The first
      controller manages the disks a, b, c and d; the second controller
      manages the disks e, f, g and h, etc. Every controller can manage four
      disks: the first two are called the primary disks, the last two are
      called the secundary disks. Every pair of disks has a master (first
      disk) and slave (second disk). So, the primary master disk of the first
      IDE controller is <filename>/dev/hda</filename>, the secundary slave
      disk of the second IDE controller would be
      <filename>/dev/hdh</filename>.</para>

      <para>To find out which disk devices are detected on your system, you
      can list the contents of <filename>/dev/disk/by-path</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>ls -l /dev/disk/by-path</command>
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root  9 2009-12-05 23:35 pci-0000:00:1f.1 -&gt; ../../hda
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root  9 2009-12-05 23:35 pci-0000:00:1f.2-scsi-0:0:0:0 -&gt; ../../sda
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 10 2009-12-05 23:35 pci-0000:00:1f.2-scsi-0:0:0:0-part1 -&gt; ../../sda1
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 10 2009-12-05 23:35 pci-0000:00:1f.2-scsi-0:0:0:0-part2 -&gt; ../../sda2
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 10 2009-12-05 23:35 pci-0000:00:1f.2-scsi-0:0:0:0-part5 -&gt; ../../sda5
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 10 2009-12-05 23:35 pci-0000:00:1f.2-scsi-0:0:0:0-part6 -&gt; ../../sda6
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 10 2009-12-05 23:35 pci-0000:00:1f.2-scsi-0:0:0:0-part7 -&gt; ../../sda7
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 10 2009-12-05 23:35 pci-0000:00:1f.2-scsi-0:0:0:0-part8 -&gt; ../../sda8</programlisting>

      <para>Or, if this location doesn't exist (it is created by Gentoo's udev
      rules, but that doesn't necessarily mean it is available on other
      distributions), you can check the content of
      <filename>/sys/block</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>ls /sys/block</command>
hda  loop0   loop1   loop2   loop3    sda</programlisting>

      <para>Now, fire up fdisk to edit the partitions on /dev/sda:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>fdisk /dev/sda</command>
Command (m for help): </programlisting>

      <para>To view the current partition layout, enter p:</para>

      <programlisting>Command (m for help): <command>p</command>

Disk /dev/sda: 240 heads, 63 sectors, 2184 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 15120 * 512 bytes

Device Boot    Start       End    Blocks   Id  System
/dev/sda1             1        14    105808+  83  Linux
/dev/sda2            15        49    264600   82  Linux swap
/dev/sda3            50        70    158760   83  Linux
/dev/sda4            71      2184  15981840    5  Extended
/dev/sda5            71       209   1050808+  83  Linux
/dev/sda6           210       348   1050808+  83  Linux
/dev/sda7           349       626   2101648+  83  Linux
/dev/sda8           627       904   2101648+  83  Linux
/dev/sda9           905      2184   9676768+  83  Linux

Command (m for help): </programlisting>

      <para>Now, before continuing, let's first think about what partition
      layout you need...</para>

      <section>
        <title>Partition Layout Scheme</title>

        <para>On Linux, as I've told before, the file system can be contained
        inside one partition, but it can also be made up of several
        partitions. The reason to use a single partition or multiple
        partitions depends a bit on how flexible you want to assign your
        available disk space and what other requirements you have for your
        file systems.</para>

        <para>For instance, if you do not want your users to be able to fill
        up your root partition you might want to put their home directories on
        a different partition. In this case, if they end up filling their home
        directory, only the partition used for the home directories is filled
        up and the other partitions remain untouched.</para>

        <note>
          <para>This is not the only possible way of limiting users' disk
          space usage. You can also implement quotas so that users are only
          allowed to use a particular amount of disk space.</para>
        </note>

        <para>You might want to store certain data on a partition which
        shouldn't be always visible. In this case, you can opt not to mount
        the partition automatically.</para>

        <para>One final note is that, if your system is not blessed with a
        huge amount of memory, you need to set up some swap space. Although
        you can use a swap file for this, most distributions (still) prefer
        that you use a swap partition. This is a (relatively) small partition
        which will be used by the Linux kernel to store memory pages when
        physical memory is full.</para>

        <para>An example partitioning scheme is given in <xref
        linkend="partschemetable" />.</para>

        <table id="partschemetable">
          <title>Example partitioning scheme for a Linux desktop</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Partition</entry>

                <entry>Size</entry>

                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>/dev/sda1</entry>

                <entry>100Mbyte</entry>

                <entry>Will be used to house the /boot partition in which the
                bootloader configuration and kernel images are stored.
                Separate partition as none of the files on this partition are
                needed during regular operations (thus partition is not
                automatically mounted)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>/dev/sda2</entry>

                <entry>12Gbyte</entry>

                <entry>Main (root) partition which will host the Linux
                operating system</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>/dev/sda3</entry>

                <entry>27Gbyte</entry>

                <entry>Partition which will hold the /home files (files and
                folders of the users of the system).</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>/dev/sda4</entry>

                <entry>900Mbyte</entry>

                <entry>swap partition. The desktop system will have enough
                physical memory and the system will not use software suspend
                (write memory content to disk and hibernate the system) so the
                swap does not need to be as large as the physical
                memory.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Cleaning Existing Partitions</title>

        <para>Once inside fdisk, you can view the current partitions using the
        <command>p</command> command. You can then remove the partitions you
        do not want anymore with the d command, followed by the partition
        identifier. For instance, suppose you want to remove the third
        partition (/dev/sda3):</para>

        <programlisting>Command (m for help): <command>p</command>
Disk /dev/sda: 240 heads, 63 sectors, 2184 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 15120 * 512 bytes

Device Boot    Start       End    Blocks   Id  System
/dev/sda1             1        14    105808+  83  Linux
/dev/sda2            15        49    264600   82  Linux swap
/dev/sda3            50        70    158760   83  Linux
/dev/sda4            71      2184  15981840    5  Extended
/dev/sda5            71       209   1050808+  83  Linux
/dev/sda6           210       348   1050808+  83  Linux
/dev/sda7           349       626   2101648+  83  Linux
/dev/sda8           627       904   2101648+  83  Linux
/dev/sda9           905      2184   9676768+  83  Linux

Command (m for help): <command>d</command>
Partition number (1-9): <command>3</command></programlisting>

        <para>Repeat this step for every partition you want to delete. When
        you're finished, type the w command to write the changes to disk and
        exit fdisk (of course, you probably want to wait until you've created
        the new partitions as well).</para>

        <programlisting>Command (m for help): <command>w</command></programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Adding Partitions</title>

        <para>Now to add new partitions, I will work from the given partition
        layout example given previously. Also, I assume that the disk has no
        partitions. So first, let's create /dev/sda1:</para>

        <programlisting>Command (m for help): <command>n</command>
Command action
   e   extended
   p   primary partition (1-4)
<command>p</command>
Partition number (1-4): <command>1</command>
First cylinder (1-12621, default 1): <emphasis>(Press return to use the default "1")</emphasis>
Using default value 1
Last cylinder or +size or +sizeM or +sizeK (1-621, default 621):
<command>+100M</command></programlisting>

        <para>In the above command sequence, I asked <command>fdisk</command>
        to create a new partition which will be a primary one (remember, if I
        would select extended then I would be creating a container partition
        which can then host logical partitions). <command>fdisk</command> then
        asks for the first cylinder and proposes as default the first cylinder
        (which means as much as "start at the beginning of the disk"). Then
        <command>fdisk</command> asks where the partition should end. As I'm
        not going to calculate which cylinder is around the 100Mbyte limit, I
        just tell fdisk to create a partition of 100Mbyte size.</para>

        <para>Next, I create /dev/sda2, 3 and 4 in one go:</para>

        <programlisting>Command (m for help): <command>n</command>
Command action
   e   extended
   p   primary partition (1-4)
<command>p</command>
Partition number (1-4): <command>2</command>
First cylinder (97-12621, default 97): <emphasis>(Return again)</emphasis>
Using default value 97
Last cylinder or +size or +sizeM or +sizeK (97-12621, default 12621):
<command>+12288M</command>

Command (m for help): <command>n</command>
Command action
   e   extended
   p   primary partition (1-4)
<command>p</command>
Partition number (1-4): <command>3</command>
First cylinder (4041-12621, default 4041): <emphasis>(Return again)</emphasis>
Using default value 4041
Last cylinder or +size or +sizeM or +sizeK (4041-12621, default
12621): <command>+27648M</command>

Command (m for help): <command>n</command>
Command action
   e   extended
   p   primary partition (1-4)
<command>p</command>
Partition number (1-4): <command>4</command>
First cylinder (12021-12621, default 12021): <emphasis>(Return again)</emphasis>
Using default value 12021
Last cylinder or +size or +sizeM or +sizeK (12021-12621, default
12621): <emphasis>(Return)</emphasis></programlisting>

        <para>In the last sequence we let the final partition be as large as
        the remaining amount of disk space left, so we accept the default last
        cylinder proposal.</para>

        <para>Right now, the partition scheme is set, but the partitions
        aren't ready yet. I now need to mark each partition with a particular
        partition type. A <emphasis>partition type</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>partition</primary>

            <secondary>type</secondary>
          </indexterm> is a small label assigned to a partition that allows an
        operating system to know if it can read the partition (i.e. understand
        its content) or not.</para>

        <para>For instance, the partition type "Linux" (label 83) allows Linux
        operating systems to identify the partition as a partition it
        understands. Windows on the other hand will not show this partition as
        it does not support Linux partitions. Likewise, a FAT32 Windows
        partition has label 0B (labels are hexadecimal).</para>

        <para>In our example, we need to use two partition types: one to
        identify a Linux partition (83) and one to identify the Linux swap
        partition (82). To mark partitions as such, use fdisk's
        <command>t</command> command:</para>

        <programlisting>Command (m for help): <command>t</command>
Partition number (1-4): <command>1</command>
Hex code (type L to list codes): <command>83</command>
Changed system type of partition 1 to 83 (Linux)

Command (m for help): <command>t</command>
Partition number (1-4): <command>2</command>
Hex code (type L to list codes): <command>83</command>
Changed system type of partition 2 to 83 (Linux)

Command (m for help): <command>t</command>
Partition number (1-4): <command>3</command>
Hex code (type L to list codes): <command>83</command>
Changed system type of partition 3 to 83 (Linux)

Command (m for help): <command>t</command>
Partition number (1-4): <command>4</command>
Hex code (type L to list codes): <command>82</command>
Changed system type of partition 4 to 82 (Linux swap)</programlisting>

        <para>Now that our partitions are created and marked, write the
        changes to disk and exit fdisk with the <command>w</command>
        command.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Placing a File System on a Partition</title>

      <para>With a partition alone you cannot do much: the partition is
      available as an empty space, but has no file system on it. File systems
      are mandatory to use as they structure the partition and allow the
      operating system to manage files, directories and more on the partition.
      We covered this already in <xref linkend="filesystems" />.</para>

      <para>To place a file system on a partition you need to use the
      <command>mkfs.&lt;type&gt;</command><indexterm>
          <primary>mkfs</primary>
        </indexterm> command. For instance, to create an ext2 or ext3
      partition, use <command>mkfs.ext2</command><indexterm>
          <primary>mkfs.ext2</primary>
        </indexterm> or <command>mkfs.ext3</command><indexterm>
          <primary>mkfs.ext3</primary>
        </indexterm>. With the example partition scheme I would use ext2 for
      the /boot partition (<filename>/dev/sda1</filename>), and ext3 for the
      two other Linux partitions:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>mkfs.ext2 /dev/sda1</command>
# <command>mkfs.ext3 /dev/sda2</command>
# <command>mkfs.ext3 /dev/sda3</command></programlisting>

      <para>A good idea is to label each partition. A <emphasis>volume
      label</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>volume label</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>label</primary>
        </indexterm> is a simple string of limited length (16 bytes, so 16
      characters as I don't suspect unicode is supported here) which can allow
      you to find the partition more easily. Say that you label your
      partitions based on their use:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>mkfs.ext2 -L boot /dev/sda1</command>
# <command>mkfs.ext3 -L root /dev/sda2</command>
# <command>mkfs.ext3 -L home /home/sda3</command></programlisting>

      <para>With labels set, you can use label-based device file names instead
      of the (sometimes difficult to remember) standard ones:
      <filename>/dev/disk/by-label/root</filename> instead of
      <filename>/dev/sda2</filename>.</para>

      <para>Finally, I need to mark the swap partition as a swap partition
      using the <command>mkswap</command><indexterm>
          <primary>mkswap</primary>
        </indexterm> command. This command also supports the <command>-L
      &lt;label&gt;</command> option if you want to use it.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>mkswap /dev/sda4</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using the Partitions</title>

      <para>With the selected partitions created, you can now start using
      them.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Enabling a Swap Partition</title>

        <para>To enable a swap partition, use the swapon command. This will
        inform the Linux kernel that the selected partition can be used as a
        swap partition:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>swapon /dev/sda4</command></programlisting>

        <para>Because you do not want to enter this command every time you
        boot your system, add the following line to /etc/fstab. This will
        automatically enable the selected partition as a swap
        partition:</para>

        <programlisting>/dev/sda4  none   swap   sw   0 0</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Enabling a File System</title>

        <para>To enable a file system on a partition, you need to mount it on
        your file system. This has already been covered in <xref
        linkend="mountsection" />.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Removable Media</title>

    <para>Removable media differs from partitions in the fact that they are...
    removable. Some removable media cannot be written to, others can. If you
    can write to it, you most likely can partition (and put a file system on
    it) just as if it was a hard disk.</para>

    <para>The most important difference is that they are not always available
    for the system: you can plug (put) them in or pull them out, so you should
    mount and unmount the file system. Luckily, there are tools that
    automatically mount / umount such devices.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Mounting Removable Media</title>

      <para>As seen before, media mountpoints can be defined in
      <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> to ease the mount process. Two examples
      (one for a CD-ROM device and one for a USB storage device) could
      be:</para>

      <programlisting>/dev/cdrom    /media/cdrom    auto   defaults,user,noauto   0 0
/dev/sdb1     /media/usb      auto   defaults,user,noauto   0 0</programlisting>

      <para>As you can see, the mounts are defined with auto as file system
      type (meaning that the mount process attempts to automatically find the
      file system to use) and has user (users have the ability to mount this
      location) and noauto (do not attempt to mount this when the system
      boots) as options.</para>

      <para>But in order to succesfully edit the fstab file, you need to know
      what device will be used and you also need to make sure that the
      destination directories exist.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Device Files and udev</title>

        <para>The <command>udev</command> device manager creates device files
        for your partitions, including removable media when it is attached to
        the system. One of the advantages of using udev is that it also
        creates various symlinks that identify the same device. For instance,
        a plugged in USB stick can get the following device files
        created:</para>

        <programlisting>/dev/sdb1</programlisting>

        <para>The following links can then be created to this device
        file:</para>

        <programlisting>/dev/block/8:17
/dev/disk/by-id/usb-_USB_DISK_2.0_0789E600025-0:0-part1
/dev/disk/by-path/pci-0000:00:1d.7-usb-0:1:1.0-scsi-0:0:0:0-part1
/dev/disk/by-uuid/3466-4C39
/dev/disk/by-label/UDISK-2.0</programlisting>

        <para>The advantage of having these links is that, when you plug
        another USB stick first and then this one, it's device file might be
        different (say <filename>/dev/sdc1</filename>) but the by-id, by-uuid
        and by-label links will remain the same.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Obtaining the device file</title>

        <para>When you plug in a removable media (like a USB stick), the
        kernel will log that it has detected the hardware. One way to find out
        which device file is used is to filter the <command>dmesg</command>
        output for text such as "removable media":</para>

        <programlisting>~# <command>dmesg | grep 'removable media'</command>
sd 4:0:0:0: [sdb] Attached SCSI removable disk</programlisting>

        <para>In this example, the hardware device file is for /dev/sdb. The
        partitions can then be obtained by listing all files in /dev starting
        with sdb:</para>

        <programlisting>~# <command>ls /dev/sdb*</command>
/dev/sdb    /dev/sdb1</programlisting>

        <para>Now, if you want to find out which files point to (or are
        hardlinks to) a particular device file (say /dev/sdb1), you can use
        the following <command>find</command> construct:</para>

        <programlisting>~# <command>find -L /dev -samefile /dev/sdb1</command>
/dev/sdb1
/dev/disk/by-label/UDISK-2.0
/dev/disk/by-uuid/3466-4C39
/dev/disk/by-id/usb-_USB_DISK_2.0_07891E600025-0:0-part1
/dev/disk/by-path/pci-0000:00:1d.7-usb-0:1:1.0-scsi-0:0:0:0-part1
/dev/block/8:17</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Automounting Devices</title>

      <para>You can also have Linux configured so that removable media is
      automatically mounted. In almost all cases, this is done through a
      deamon process provided by the desktop environment. It starts with
      hal...</para>

      <section>
        <title id="HAL">Using HAL</title>

        <para>The <command>hal</command><indexterm>
            <primary>hal</primary>
          </indexterm> (Hardware Abstraction Layer) software daemon provides
        an interface to other programs about plugged in hardware. It attempts
        to provide an abstraction layer on top of the device: is the device an
        USB stick or a digital camera plugged in through USB? The idea is that
        a multitude of hardware devices should be seen as the same kind of
        hardware devices (so the same actions need to be taken when the device
        is plugged in), regardless of brand and type.</para>

        <para>In effect, <command>hal</command> itself isn't sufficient to
        automatically mount a device, but it is part of a more global
        architecture. For instance, with GNOME, you need
        <command>hal</command>, <command>dbus</command> and
        <command>gnome-volume-manager</command>. The tool that actually does
        the auto-mounting is <command>gnome-volume-manager</command>. It
        listens for hal events through <command>dbus</command><indexterm>
            <primary>dbus</primary>
          </indexterm> (which is a service that allows processes to
        communicate with each other through a unified specification). The hal
        software gets an event from udev (which we've seen before), identifies
        the hardware and submits an event to dbus.</para>

        <para>If you have GNOME installed, these tools are probably already
        set up. You can configure the <command>hal</command> device manager
        through the GNOME menu (Desktop &gt; Administration &gt; Device
        Manager) as you can for the GNOME volume manager (Desktop &gt;
        Preferences &gt; Removable Drives and Media).</para>

        <para>If you use KDE, the necessary tools are probably installed as
        well (only the volume manager isn't called gnome-volume-manager
        ;-).</para>

        <para>In both cases I say "probably", because many packages rely on
        USE flags to decide if a certain functionality needs to be enabled
        (check the hal USE flag).</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>emerge -pv kdebase</command>
[ebuild   R   ] kde-base/kdebase-3.5.9-r3  USE="branding cups hal
java ldap opengl pam -arts -debug -ieee1394 -joystick 
-kdeenablefinal -kdehiddenvisibility -lm_sensors -logitech-mouse
-openexr -samba -xcomposite -xinerama -xscreensaver"  0 kB</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Network File Systems</title>

    <para>Although Unix has grown with NFS as the primary network file system,
    others are available which offer different features you might
    require...</para>

    <section>
      <title>NFS</title>

      <para>NFS, or <emphasis>Network File Server</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>NFS</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>Network File Server</primary>
        </indexterm>, is one of the most popular network file systems used in
      the Linux/Unix world. With NFS, you can export files and directories to
      other systems on the network while still using the Unix way of assigning
      permissions and ownership to files.</para>

      <section>
        <title>NFS Server</title>

        <para>If you want to export files to your network yourself, you need
        to install the necessary NFS server tools which is included in the
        nfs-utils<indexterm>
            <primary>nfs-utils</primary>
          </indexterm> package:</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>emerge nfs-utils</command></programlisting>

        <para>Once installed, you need to select what directories you want to
        export through the <filename>/etc/exports</filename><indexterm>
            <primary>exports</primary>
          </indexterm> file. The syntax for the exports file is similar to the
        SunOS exports file<footnote>
            <para>Some Unix flavors have different syntax rules for the
            exports file. If you are not running Gentoo Linux or have
            installed a different NFS server package, check the exports man
            page through <command>man exports</command>.</para>
          </footnote> and allows you to select a particular directory as an
        exportable resource together with specific mount options for the
        clients. I will give a multi-line example that will get you
        going:</para>

        <programlisting>/usr/portage  192.168.1.0/24(ro)
/home 192.168.1.0/24(rw,no_subtree_check)
/media/usb rw,no_root_squash mediacenter ws5 ws6 ws7(root_squash)</programlisting>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The first line gives read-only access to /usr/portage to all
            systems in the 192.168.1.0/24 network.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The second line gives read-write access to /home to all
            systems in the same network. I also added the no_subtree_check
            (see the exports man page for more information) as it improves
            reliability for file systems where file changes occur frequently
            (such as home directories).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The third line gives read-write access to the /media/usb
            location to the hosts with hostname mediacenter, ws5, ws6 and ws7.
            Also, all these hosts except for ws7 have root access to the files
            as well (as a security measure, by default the root user of the
            remote clients do not have root access to the file systems
            exported by NFS).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>As you can see from the syntax, you can either give options
        specific for a host (between brackets) or give general options to all
        hosts for the selected directory.</para>

        <para>To start the NFS service, you only need to start the nfs
        runlevel:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>/etc/init.d/nfs start</command></programlisting>

        <para>All other required services, such as rpc.statd and portmap, are
        automatically started by the initialisation script.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>NFS Client</title>

        <para>At the client side, you add in one or more lines in the
        <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> file to mount a remote NFS file
        system. Suppose that the NFS server is at 192.168.1.100, you can use
        the following lines in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> to mount the
        file systems defined in the previous section:</para>

        <programlisting>192.168.1.100:/usr/portage  /usr/portage       nfs  ro,proto=tcp  0 0
192.168.1.100:/home         /home/remoteusers  nfs  rw,proto=tcp  0 0
192.168.1.100:/media/usb    /media/usb         nfs  ro,proto=tcp  0 0</programlisting>

        <para>You can of course also run an NFS mount without
        <filename>fstab</filename>. For more information about the NFS mount
        options, please read the nfs manual page.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Samba</title>

      <para>Samba, offered by the net-fs/samba<indexterm>
          <primary>samba</primary>
        </indexterm> package, is a toolset that offers interoperability with
      Microsoft Windows networks. Not only can you access files shared on a
      Microsoft Windows network or share files yourself on such a network, you
      can also use or manage printers that are exported to the Microsoft
      Windows network.</para>

      <para>In the majority of cases, if you need to do something with a
      Microsoft Windows network, you'll need to configure Samba on your
      system. Although the configuration options for Samba can be
      overwhelming, there is an integrated web administration tool for Samba
      called SWAT which is included when you install the net-fs/samba package
      with the swat USE flag (which is enabled by default).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Managing Diskspace</title>

    <para>To identify the current file system usage, you can use the
    <command>df</command><indexterm>
        <primary>df</primary>
      </indexterm> tool, which stands for "disk free". I recommend using the
    -h and -T options to show disk usage in a human readable format (using the
    M and G notations for megabytes and gigabytes) and display the file system
    types (ext2, ext3, xfs, ...):</para>

    <programlisting>$ <command>df -hT</command>
Filesystem    Type    Size  Used Avail Use% Mounted on
/dev/sda8     ext3     35G   22G   11G  68% /
udev         tmpfs     10M   88K   10M   1% /dev
/dev/sda7     ext3    9.4G  7.6G  1.5G  85% /home
none         tmpfs    754M     0  754M   0% /dev/shm
/dev/sda1     ext3    9.7G  421M  8.8G   5% /mnt/data</programlisting>

    <para>In the above example you can see the available disk space on all
    mounted file systems.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Finding Top Diskspace Consumers</title>

      <para>To find out how much disk space a file (or, more interestingly, a
      directory with all files and subdirectories) you can use the
      <command>du</command><indexterm>
          <primary>du</primary>
        </indexterm> command (disk usage). By default, <command>du</command>
      shows the disk usage in kilobytes for every file passed on to it. You
      can have <command>du</command> show the total using the -s option
      (summarize) and even have du show it in a more human-readable manner (so
      12.6G instead of 13269313 - kilobytes).</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>du -hs /home/raghat</command>
12.6G     /home/raghat</programlisting>

      <para>If you want to view the largest users (subdirectories or files
      inside the directory) you can do a summary listing of everything beneath
      it and sort the resulting output by number. To make it a bit manageable,
      the next example then only shows the last 5 lines (the largest 5
      consumers).</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>du -ks /home/raghat/* | sort -n | tail -5</command>
7660    folder.pdf
7672    linux_sea.pdf
8532    docs/
3666665 hmd/</programlisting>

      <para>However, you'll quickly find that this process is tedious (you'll
      have to repeat it for every subdirectory if you don't plan on wiping out
      the entire directory) when you need to free some space. One of the
      solutions is to find large files, for instance through the find
      command.</para>

      <para>The next example finds all files of at least 50mbyte in size from
      the current location:</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>find . -type f -size +50M</command>
./tmp/download/testvid001.avi
./tmp/download/testvid002.avi
./iso/SysRescCD.iso</programlisting>

      <para>Another frequently used method for cleaning up files is to find
      all files of a certain age (modification time). For instance, to find
      all files of at least 10Mbyte with an age of at least 1 year old (365
      days):</para>

      <programlisting>$ <command>find . -type f -size +10M -mtime +365</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Cleaning Up Gentoo-related Files</title>

      <para>If you work with Gentoo, you have a few commands at your disposal
      that help you clean out Gentoo-specific files as well.</para>

      <para>With <command>eclean</command><indexterm>
          <primary>eclean</primary>
        </indexterm>, which is part of
      <package>app-portage/gentoolkit</package>, most Gentoo space-consuming
      directories can be cleaned in a safe manner:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the distfiles location, where Gentoo Portage stores all
          downloaded source code (in case it needs to rebuild packages), can
          be cleaned with <command>eclean distfiles</command>:</para>

          <programlisting># <command>eclean distfiles</command></programlisting>

          <para>As a result, all downloaded source code of packages that are
          not installed on the system anymore is removed from the distfiles
          location.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the packages location, wheren Gentoo Portage stores the binary
          package builds of the packages you install (this is not on by
          default, but I recommend it if you have sufficient amount of space
          as it can help you recover from certain disasters quickly), can be
          cleaned with <command>eclean packages</command>:</para>

          <programlisting># <command>eclean packages</command></programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Another location that you may clean is
      <filename>/var/tmp/portage</filename>. At this location, Portage
      performs the entire build process. If an ebuild build process fails, the
      files are left at this location (this is deliberate, so that one can
      debug and perhaps fix the build failure manually). Since most users
      don't manually fix this, if you are not emerge'ing anything, this entire
      folder can be made empty.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Resizing Partitions</title>

      <para>It is possible to resize partitions, although I recommend that, if
      you plan on using this a lot, you should take a look at LVM2 (logical
      volume management) which provides an easier and safer method for
      resizing filesystems.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Resizing xt2/ext3 file systems</title>

        <para>To increase the size of an ext3 file system, you first need to
        resize the partition. You can do this with <command>fdisk</command> by
        removing the partition and then recreating it, starting from the same
        point as the original partition started, but now larger. Of course,
        this means that the partition cannot be mounted at that time. Then,
        run <command>resize2fs</command><indexterm>
            <primary>resize2fs</primary>
          </indexterm> against the device. The tool will automatically expand
        the file system to use the entire partition again. Once the resize is
        completed, you can mount the file system again.</para>

        <programlisting># <command>fdisk /dev/sda</command>
<emphasis>(Edit partition sda3, making it take more space than before)</emphasis>
# <command>resize2fs /dev/sda3</command></programlisting>

        <para>If you want to decrease the size of an ext3 file system, you
        first need to use <command>resize2fs</command> to shrink the file
        system. Then you edit the partition table again, removing the existing
        partition and recreating it, but with a smaller size, and again
        starting the partition from the same point as the original partition
        started:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>resize2fs /dev/sda3 10G</command>
# <command>fdisk /dev/sda</command></programlisting>

        <para>As you can see, resizing an ext2/ext3 file system suffers from
        the following draw-backs:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>the file system cannot be mounted at the time of resizing.
            If you want to resize the root partition, this means you'll need
            to boot from a LiveCD, LiveUSB or another operating system</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the resize operation can only manipulate the end of the
            partition. The start of the partition must remain the same. In
            other words, if your entire disk is used by partitions, you cannot
            increase any partition without deleting one or more partitions
            behind it (you cannot shrink the last partition by moving its
            starting point closer to the end).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Resizing other file systems</title>

        <para>Almost every file system technology has a command to resize its
        file system. Some even support online resizing, provided that the
        storage on which the file system is put (partition) already has
        unallocated space available. As most people use partitions, this still
        requires unmounting the file system and editing the partition table
        using fdisk.</para>

        <para>The XFS file system has <command>xfs_growfs</command><indexterm>
            <primary>xfs_growfs</primary>
          </indexterm>, the JFS file system uses mount options to
        resize:</para>

        <programlisting><emphasis>(Resizing a JFS file system)</emphasis>
# <command>mount -o remount,resize /jfs/filesystem/mountpoint</command></programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Limiting User Files</title>

      <para>It is possible to limit the amount of files, or total disk space
      that a particular user can take on an individual partition. This is
      especially useful when you have multiple users on your system (and you
      don't want a single user to take almost all disk space on your /home
      partition - provided that it already is a separate partition, which I
      strongly recommend). A second possible reason to do this is when /home
      is not on a separate partition, and you don't want any user to be able
      to fill up your root partition.</para>

      <para>This kind of support is called <emphasis>quota</emphasis> support.
      Quota support (which requires kernel level support as well) is based
      upon two simple files that you place in the root folder of the mount
      point. Inside this file, you specify per user (for the
      <filename>aquota.user</filename> file) or group (for the
      <filename>aquota.group</filename> file) how much blocks (kilobytes)
      and/or inodes (files/directories) can be used. The soft limit there is
      when the system will start complaining, the hard limit is a final limit
      - the user or group cannot go beyond that.</para>

      <para>To use quota, first install the qouta utilities.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>emerge sys-fs/quota</command></programlisting>

      <para>Next, edit /etc/fstab and add usrquota,grpquota (or one of the two
      depending on how you want to configure your quota's) as mount
      parameters.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>nano -w /etc/fstab</command>
<emphasis>(Edit the mount parameters, like so:)</emphasis>
/dev/sda3  /home   ext3   defaults,noatime,usrquota,grpquota  0 0</programlisting>

      <para>Create, inside the mount point, the quota files. Then remount the
      file system and initialize the quota files:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>touch /home/aquota.user /home/aquota.group</command>
# <command>chmod 600 /home/aquota.*</command>
# <command>mount -o remount /home</command>
# <command>quotacheck -avugm</command>
# <command>quotaon -avug</command></programlisting>

      <para>Finally, set the quota's using the
      <command>edquota</command><indexterm>
          <primary>edquota</primary>
        </indexterm> commands. The next example edits the quota's for the
      raghat user and for the group "usergroup". The command will open up your
      standard editor (<command>vi</command> or <command>nano</command>) and
      display the current quota limits (0 means unlimited). You can then just
      edit the file to your liking. Changes will be effective
      immediately.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>edquota -u raghat</command>
# <command>edquota -g usergroup</command></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Resources</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Partition/">Linux Partition
        HOWTO</ulink>, section "<ulink
        url="http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Partition/fdisk_partitioning.html">Partitioning
        with fdisk</ulink>"</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.mythic-beasts.com/~mark/random/hal/">HAL
        and device management</ulink>, written by Mark Longair</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://docs.kde.org/stable/en/kdebase-runtime/userguide/multimedia.html">Multimedia
        with KDE</ulink>, part of KDE base documentation</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
