<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Introducing the Graphical Environment</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Linux is often seen as a command-only operating system. This is far
    from true: although its command-line is a powerful interface, you can also
    launch graphical environments on Linux. In this chapter, we briefly cover
    the graphical environments in Linux.</para>

    <para>Graphical environments are the de facto standard for working with a
    workstation. Many users know the Microsoft Windows family or the Apple
    MacOS series. However, those two aren't the only providers of a graphical
    environment. When the Intel-compliant PCs were hardly known to the world,
    consoles and other personal computers already provided a graphical
    environment to their users.</para>

    <para>It comes to no surprise to hear that the free software community
    also provides graphical environments. And, just like you have choice
    amongst distributions, you have choice amongst graphical environments:
    GNOME, KDE, XFCE4 are popular desktop graphical environments;
    enlightenment, fluxbox, window maker, icewm, ... are window
    managers.</para>

    <para>Although most readers will be sufficiently fluent in using a
    graphical environment, this book wouldn't be complete if it didn't cover
    it. As such, and with the danger of being overly simple on the subject,
    this chapter will briefly cover the concept of graphical
    environments.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Structure of X</title>

    <para>On Linux, a graphical environment consists of many
    components:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Applications</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Widget Tool Kits</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Window Manager</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>X Server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Hardware</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Each of those components interacts with others through specific
    interfaces.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>A possible representation of how X is structured</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/xschema.png" scale="75" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>An application is able to draw graphic components (buttons, windows,
    progress bars, labels etc.) through a common API called a <emphasis>widget
    tool kit</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>widget tool kit</primary>
      </indexterm>. Popular widget tool kits on Linux are GTK+ and Qt. However,
    not all applications require a widget tool kit - they can also talk to the
    X server immediately. Using such tool kits however facilitates the
    development of graphical applications.</para>

    <para>The widget tool kits communicate with the X server through an
    interface which basically drives all commands to a <emphasis>window
    manager</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>window manager</primary>
      </indexterm>. A window manager manages the layout of the users' screen:
    where are the windows positioned, can he drag windows from one location to
    another, how are buttons rendered, ... Popular window managers are
    metacity (used by the GNOME desktop environment), KWin (used by the KDE
    desktop environment), fluxbox, enlightenment, ...</para>

    <para>Most window managers are written for specific widget tool kits, but
    some of their functionality extends beyond one particular window manager:
    this allows window managers to support not only rendering of applications
    built with different widget tool kits, but also interoperability between
    these applications (copy/paste, drag 'n drop ...).</para>

    <para>The window manager receives commands from the <emphasis>X
    server</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>X server</primary>
      </indexterm>. The X server is responsible for turning requests into
    hardware-specific actions (draw window means to render a window through
    the graphic card, mouse movements are events coming from the mouse device
    and directed to the window manager to move the cursor, ...).</para>

    <para>In the following sections, we dive a little bit deeper into each of
    those components...</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The X Window System</title>

    <para>On a Unix/Linux system, the <emphasis>X server</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>X server</primary>
      </indexterm> is a tool which manages the graphical card on your system
    and offers services to draw things on your screen. These services are
    defined in the X11 protocol, an industry open standard. Because the
    interface is open, many X servers exist, one more powerful than the other.
    Popular X servers are Xorg and XFree86. However, on Gentoo Linux, Xorg is
    the only available X server (due to legal restrictions as well as support
    base).</para>

    <section>
      <title>Installing Xorg</title>

      <para>To install Xorg on Gentoo Linux, I suggest to read the <ulink
      url="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xorg-config.xml">X Server
      Configuration HOWTO</ulink> from Gentoo's documentation repository. It
      describes how to install Xorg, configure it to work with your hardware
      and more. This chapter only gives a quick introduction to this.</para>

      <para>You should understand that the Xorg configuration defines, amongst
      other things,</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the resolution and refresh rates of your screen(s)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the language used by your input (keyboard)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the drivers used to render stuff (i810, vesa, but also closed,
          proprietary drivers like nVidia and ATIs)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>...</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Once configured to your likings, do not forget to take a backup of
      your configuration (hint: some people place their X configuration online
      for others to see - there is nothing personal inside anyway).</para>

      <section>
        <title>Installing Xorg</title>

        <para>Before installing Xorg, first make sure that the
        <parameter>VIDEO_CARDS</parameter><indexterm>
            <primary>VIDEO_CARDS</primary>
          </indexterm> and <parameter>INPUT_DEVICES</parameter><indexterm>
            <primary>INPUT_DEVICES</primary>
          </indexterm> variables are set in
        <filename>/etc/make.conf</filename>:</para>

        <programlisting>INPUT_DEVICES="evdev keyboard mouse"
VIDEO_CARDS="vesa intel"</programlisting>

        <para>In the above example, I selected the vesa video driver (a
        default driver that is supported by most video cards, but with little
        functionality) and intel video driver (as I have an Intel graphic
        card).</para>

        <para>Next, install <package>x11-base/xorg-server</package><indexterm>
            <primary>xorg-server</primary>
          </indexterm>:</para>

        <programlisting># <command>emerge x11-base/xorg-server</command></programlisting>

        <para>Once finished, it is time to check out the graphical server
        environment.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Testing Xorg</title>

        <para>Try out Xorg without using any configuration file. The Xorg
        server will try to automatically detect the necessary settings and, to be
        honest, does a fine job at that. Don't test out things as root
        though!</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>startx</command></programlisting>

        <para>If you haven't configured a graphical environment yet, you'll be
        greeted with a console and an ugly background. However, that alone
        should suffice to verify if your mouse and keyboard are working as
        well as do a preliminary verification of the resolution of your
        screen.</para>

        <para>If the graphical server doesn't seem to function properly, make
        sure to read up on Gentoo's <ulink
        url="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xorg-config.xml">Xorg Server
        Configuration HOWTO</ulink>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Window Managers</title>

    <para>Window managers interact with the X server using the X11 interface
    and manage how your graphical environment looks like, but also how it
    behaves (for instance, there are window managers that do not support
    dragging windows).</para>

    <para>Certain window managers are accompanied by various other tools that
    integrate nicely with the window manager. These tools offer services like
    a panel (from which you can launch commands or programs immediately),
    application menus, file manager etc. The aggregation of these tools is
    often called a <emphasis>desktop environment</emphasis><indexterm>
        <primary>desktop environment</primary>
      </indexterm> because it offers a complete desktop to the user.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Installing a Window Manager</title>

      <para>Gentoo supports many window managers. To install one, simply
      emerge it.</para>

      <para>For fluxbox, a popular, lightweight window manager, Gentoo even
      has official documentation available: the <ulink
      url="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/fluxbox-config.xml">Fluxbox
      Configuration HOWTO</ulink>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Activating a Window Manager</title>

      <para>To activate a window manager for your end user, create a file
      called <filename>.xinitrc</filename><indexterm>
          <primary>.xinitrc</primary>
        </indexterm> in your home directory. Inside it, you just add "exec
      &lt;manager&gt;" where &lt;manager&gt; is the command to launch the
      window manager.</para>

      <para>For instance, for fluxbox:</para>

      <programlisting>exec fluxbox</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Desktop Environments</title>

    <para>The majority of Linux users use a desktop environment to work with
    their work station. The two most used desktop environments are KDE and
    GNOME. The third environment, XFCE4, is gaining momentum as a lightweight
    yet powerful desktop environment.</para>

    <section>
      <title>GNOME</title>

      <para>The GNOME<indexterm>
          <primary>GNOME</primary>
        </indexterm> desktop environment is the default desktop environment
      for many Linux distributions, including Ubuntu and Fedora. Its desktop
      is very simple to use: the number of visible options is kept low to not
      confuse users, and all applications that want to integrate with the
      GNOME desktop should adhere to various guidelines such as the user
      interface guideline.</para>

      <para>The GNOME community offers a good introduction to the graphical
      environment called the <ulink
      url="http://www.gnome.org/learn/users-guide/latest/">GNOME User
      Guide</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Gentoo has a <ulink
      url="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gnome-config.xml">GNOME Configuration
      HOWTO</ulink> available as well.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>An example view of a GNOME desktop</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/gnomedesktop.png" scale="75"
                       width="13cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>KDE</title>

      <para>The KDE desktop is a fully featured desktop environment which
      offers all the functionality a regular user might expect from his
      system. KDE comes with many tools, ranging from network related tools
      (browsers, IM, P2P) to office tools, multimedia tools, authoring and
      even development environments.</para>

      <para>Gentoo provides a <ulink
      url="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/kde-config.xml">KDE Configuration
      HOWTO</ulink>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>An example view of a KDE desktop</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/kdedesktop.png" scale="75" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>XFCE4</title>

      <para>The XFCE4 desktop is designed to still run smoothly on low memory
      systems (32 Mbytes and more). Often, power users use XFCE4 even on large
      memory systems just to reduce the memory overhead of the graphical
      environment.</para>

      <para>Gentoo provides an <ulink
      url="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xfce-config.xml">XFCE Configuration
      Howto</ulink>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>An example view of an XFCE4 desktop</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/xfce4desktop.png" scale="75"
                       scalefit="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Activating a Desktop Environment</title>

      <para>To activate a desktop environment for your end user, create a file
      called <filename>.xinitrc</filename><indexterm>
          <primary>.xinitrc</primary>
        </indexterm> in your home directory. Inside it, you just add "exec
      &lt;environment&gt;" where &lt;environment&gt; is the command to launch
      the desktop environment.</para>

      <para>For instance, for Xfce4:</para>

      <programlisting>exec xfce4-session</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Logging on Graphically</title>

    <para>If you want to log on to your system using a graphical logon
    manager, you need to do two things:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Install a graphical logon manager</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Setup the default graphical environment</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Install Graphical Logon Manager</title>

      <para>The desktop environments KDE and GNOME provide their own graphical
      logon manager (which are called kdm and gdm respectively). If you don't
      have them or want to use a different one, I recommend x11-misc/slim. It
      is a lightweight graphical logon manager.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>emerge x11-misc/slim</command></programlisting>

      <para>Once a graphical logon manager is available, configure the xdm
      service to use it.</para>

      <para>In <filename>/etc/conf.d/xdm</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting>DISPLAYMANAGER="slim"</programlisting>

      <para>Finally, add the xdm service to the default runlevel.</para>

      <programlisting># <command>rc-update add xdm default</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setup the Default Graphical Environment</title>

      <para>To setup the default graphical environment for a user, you need to
      create your .xinitrc file as mentioned before (Activating a Window
      Manager or Desktop Environment).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Supporting 3D Acceleration</title>

    <para>The graphical environment can also use 3D acceleration.</para>

    <para>Now, 3D acceleration is a tricky subject because there are many
    implementations that offer 3D services. For instance, you can have 3D
    services with software rendering (i.e. no delegation of rendering to
    specific 3D hardware) but this usually isn't seen as 3D
    acceleration.</para>

    <para>When you have a graphic card capable of rendering 3D, you will need
    to configure the X Window System to hand over 3D rendering tasks to the
    graphic card. This can happen through either open standards or
    specifications (such as OpenGL) or through closed, proprietary drivers
    (such as the nVidia drivers).</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
