<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="installgentoo"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Installing Gentoo Linux</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>I've waited a few chapters before I started discussing the Gentoo
    Linux installation because it isn't for the faint of heart. Although
    Gentoo has tried to offer a graphical installer in the past, its user- and
    developer base swore by the manual installation approach. As a result, the
    graphical installer has been deprecated and the installation procedure is
    once more a manual, step by step guide.</para>

    <para>With the previous chapters discussed, you should now be able to
    install a Gentoo Linux yourself with the following simple set of
    instructions. However, if you want to do it the official way, do not
    hesitate to read the <link
    xl:href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-x86.xml">Gentoo
    Handbook</link>. There are also <link type=""
    xl:href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook">handbooks</link> available
    for other architectures.</para>

    <section>
      <title>System Requirements</title>

      <para>Gentoo Linux can be as heavy as you want, or as small as you want.
      Yet unless you deviate from the documented approach, Gentoo Linux
      remains a source-based distribution. Because of that, it has a slightly
      higher disk space requirement than other distributions. A minimal (base)
      Gentoo Linux installation takes a little less than 2Gbyte of diskspace
      (including Linux kernel source code and the Gentoo Portage tree, which
      take about 640 Mbyte in total). But with 2Gbyte, you don't have room for
      much more than a base installation.</para>

      <para>To have a comfortable installation, yet with room to spare for
      additional installations, you should consider a total diskspace of at
      least 20 Gbyte for the applications alone. With current disk sizes, this
      should not be a problem. If you don't install a full-blown KDE or GNOME,
      you should have enough with 10Gbyte or less.</para>

      <para>Disk space aside, Gentoo Linux can run and install with almost any
      system specification. Of course, the lower the specs, the higher the
      duration of an installation. Installing Gentoo Linux on an i486 with 32
      Mbyte of memory is doable (but not recommended).</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Booting a Linux Environment</title>

    <para>A Gentoo Linux installation starts from a Linux environment. You can
    use any Linux environment you want, but most people suggest to use a
    LiveCD.</para>

    <para>A popular LiveCD to install Gentoo from is <link
    xl:href="http://www.sysresccd.org">System Rescue CD</link>. All necessary
    documentation about booting the CD, including setting up networking (which
    you definitely need to do in order to install Gentoo) is available on the
    site.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Disk Setup</title>

    <para>Once your environment is set up, you'll need to setup your disks by
    partitioning them and then putting a file system on them. Partitioning and
    file system management has been discussed <link
    linkend="hdpartitions">beforehand</link>. If you want, assign labels to
    the file systems to make it easier to create your
    <filename>fstab</filename> file later:</para>

    <programlisting># <command>fdisk /dev/sda</command>
<emphasis>(Partition the disk)</emphasis>
# <command>mkfs.ext2 -L BOOT /dev/sda1</command>
# <command>mkfs.ext3 -L ROOT /dev/sda2</command>
# <command>mkfs.ext3 -L HOME /dev/sda3</command>
# <command>mkswap -L SWAP /dev/sda4</command></programlisting>

    <para>Once that your partitions are created and a file system is put on
    it, it is time to really start the Gentoo Linux installation.</para>

    <para>First, mount all the necessary partitions onto your Linux
    environment. In the rest of this chapter I will assume the partitioning
    layout as described in the following table:</para>

    <table xml:id="example_partitiontable">
      <title>Example partition layout</title>

      <tgroup cols="3">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Device</entry>

            <entry>Partition</entry>

            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>/dev/sda1</entry>

            <entry>/boot</entry>

            <entry>Small boot partition to hold the Linux kernel and
            bootloader information. Can be ext2</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>/dev/sda2</entry>

            <entry>/</entry>

            <entry>Root partition; should be fairly large in this example.
            Suggested is ext3</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>/dev/sda3</entry>

            <entry>/home</entry>

            <entry>Home partition where all users' files are stored. Best to
            always have a separate partition for the home directories so that
            future reinstallations can reuse the home structure.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>/dev/sda4</entry>

            <entry>&lt;none&gt;</entry>

            <entry>Swap partition, roughly 1.5 times the amount of physical
            memory nowadays (still this large because I want to use
            hibernate-to-disk).</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <programlisting>~# <command>mkdir /mnt/gentoo</command>
~# <command>mount /dev/sda2 /mnt/gentoo</command>
~# <command>mkdir /mnt/gentoo/boot</command>
~# <command>mount /dev/sda1 /mnt/gentoo/boot</command>
~# <command>mkdir /mnt/gentoo/home</command>
~# <command>mount /dev/sda3 /mnt/gentoo/home</command>
~# <command>swapon /dev/sda4</command></programlisting>

    <para>With the above commands executed, the various file systems we will
    use for the Gentoo installation are now available at
    <filename>/mnt/gentoo</filename>. Every file or directory we put beneath
    <filename>/mnt/gentoo</filename> will show up on our final Gentoo
    installation. For instance, <filename>/mnt/gentoo/boot</filename> =
    <filename>/boot</filename>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installing Gentoo Base</title>

    <para>First, set your system time correct so that the files you're going
    to create do not have a weird time stamp:</para>

    <programlisting>~# <command>ntpdate pool.ntp.org</command></programlisting>

    <para>Next, surf to the <link
    xl:href="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/mirrors2.xml">Gentoo mirror
    list</link> and pick a mirror close to you. On most LiveCDs browsers are
    available. On the sysresccd you can use links or lynx (command-line
    browsers). Navigate to releases, select your architecture, autobuilds, the
    latest date directory to find a listing of stage3 files and install
    files.</para>

    <programlisting>~# <command>cd /mnt/gentoo</command>
~# <command>links http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/mirrors2.xml</command></programlisting>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A stage3 file is an archive of a prebuilt Gentoo environment
        which we will extract to the installation location
        (<filename>/mnt/gentoo</filename>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>An install file is an ISO file (CD image) which contains a
        minimal Gentoo environment from which you can boot and install Gentoo
        from.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Download the stage3 file and store it in
    <filename>/mnt/gentoo</filename>. If you have the full URL at hand, you
    can also use <command>wget</command>:</para>

    <programlisting># <command>cd /mnt/gentoo</command>
# <command>wget http://gentoo.osuosl.org/releases/x86/autobuilds/20091201/stage3-i686-20091201.tar.bz2</command></programlisting>

    <para>On many forums, you will find the notion of "funtoo" stages. <link
    xl:href="http://www.funtoo.org">Funtoo</link> is, to say it in the author's
    own words (who happens to be Daniel Robbins, the founder of Gentoo Linux),
    a Gentoo Linux variant which offers freshly-built Gentoo Linux stable
    stages using Gentoo's official stable branch. You can use a funtoo stage
    instead of a Gentoo official stage if you want. After all, they both
    contain roughly the same material. However, some caution is still in
    place: the Funtoo stages continuously evolve and diverge into their own
    set so I recommend to take a quick stab at the Funtoo installation
    instructions nevertheless. At the time of writing, the instructions are
    quite resembling.</para>

    <para>
    Finally, quit your browser
    and extract the downloaded files on your installation location.
    </para>

    <programlisting>~# <command>tar xvjpf stage3-*.tar.bz2</command></programlisting>

    <para>Next, edit the <filename>/mnt/gentoo/etc/portage/make.conf</filename> file.
    As discussed previously, this file contains variables that define Portage'
    behaviour. Right now I'm focussing on the variables CFLAGS, CXXFLAGS and
    MAKEOPTS...</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><varname>CFLAGS</varname> (C) and <varname>CXXFLAGS</varname>
        (C++) inform gcc (GNU's Compiler Collection) what optimizations it
        should use (see <link linkend="compilerdirectives">Compiler
        Directives</link>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>MAKEOPTS defines how many parallel compilations should occur
        when you install a package (especially useful for multicore / SMP
        systems). A good choice is the number of core's in your system plus
        one (for instance, a dual-core CPU would lead to
        <varname>MAKEOPTS</varname>="<parameter>-j3</parameter>").</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>You can edit the <filename>make.conf</filename> file using
    <command>nano</command>, <command>vim</command> or any other text
    editor.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuring the System</title>

    <para>Our next step is to configure the installation environment.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Preparing the Installation Environment</title>

      <para>First, prepare the environment for chrooting.
      <emphasis>Chrooting</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>chroot</primary>
        </indexterm> is the process of altering your sessions' file system
      root to another location. In our case, <filename>/mnt/gentoo</filename>
      should become <filename>/</filename> for your running session. In order
      to chroot successfully, we need to ensure that networking will still
      function properly and that both kernel data and device drivers are
      available inside the chroot:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>cp -L /etc/resolv.conf /mnt/gentoo/etc/resolv.conf</command>
~# <command>mount -t proc none /mnt/gentoo/proc</command>
~# <command>mount -o bind /dev /mnt/gentoo/dev</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Chrooting</title>

      <para>Now, chroot into the Gentoo installation environment, update your
      environment variables and, for safety reasons, change your prompt so
      that you know you're inside your Gentoo installation environment.</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>chroot /mnt/gentoo /bin/bash</command>
~# <command>env-update</command>
~# <command>source /etc/profile</command>
~# <command>export PS1="(chroot) $PS1"</command></programlisting>

      <para>Right now, this session (where the prompt starts with "(chroot)")
      is inside your Gentoo installation environment.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring Portage</title>

      <para>Now, update the Portage tree to make sure you have the current set
      of packages at your disposal:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>mkdir /usr/portage; emerge-webrsync;</command></programlisting>

      <para>Next, select a Gentoo profile for your environment. A
      <emphasis>Gentoo profile</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>profile</primary>
        </indexterm> is a collection of default Portage settings. If you want
      to know what a particular profile selects of default settings, check out
      its content at <filename>/usr/portage/profiles</filename> (and don't
      forget to read up on cascading profiles). Currently, the '13.0' set of
      profiles is the stable, default one. </para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>eselect profile list</command>
~# <command>eselect profile set &lt;number&gt;</command></programlisting>

      <para>Finally, set the USE flags you want in either
      <filename>/etc/portage/make.conf</filename> (global USE flags) or
      <filename>/etc/portage/package.use</filename> (local USE flags).</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>nano -w /etc/portage/make.conf</command></programlisting>

      <para>For those of you who want to run Gentoo Linux with support for
      international locales, edit <filename>/etc/locale.gen</filename> and
      specify the locales you want to support. An example of locales are given
      below. Once set, generate the locale files for your system.</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>nano -w /etc/locale.gen</command>
en_US ISO-8859-1
en_US.UTF-8 UTF-8
de_DE ISO-8859-1
de_DE@euro ISO-8859-15

~# <command>locale-gen</command></programlisting>

      <para>If you want to know which locales are supported, view the contents
      of the /usr/share/i18n/SUPPORTED file:</para>

      <programlisting># <command>less /usr/share/i18n/SUPPORTED</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring the Linux Kernel</title>

      <para>First select your time zone file from inside /usr/share/zoneinfo
      and copy it to /etc/localtime. For instance, to use the GMT time
      zone:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>cp /usr/share/zoneinfo/GMT /etc/localtime</command></programlisting>

      <para>Next, install the kernel sources. Gentoo profiles a few kernel
      packages like <package>vanilla-sources</package> (bare Linux kernel as
      delivered by the kernel developers) and
      <package>gentoo-sources</package> (vanilla Linux kernel with patches
      managed by Gentoo developers).</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>emerge gentoo-sources</command></programlisting>

      <para>You will find the kernel sources at
      <filename>/usr/src/linux</filename>. Now continue with building the
      Linux kernel as discussed in <link
      linkend="configuringkernel">Configuring a Kernel</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring the System</title>

      <para>There are three blocks of information we need to configure
      now:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>file system information
          (<filename>/etc/fstab</filename>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>networking information</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>system information</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>To start with the file system information, you need to edit the
      <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> file. The structure of this file has
      been discussed before so this shouldn't be an issue (see <link
      linkend="mountsection">The mount command</link>). If you want to use
      labels instead of device locations, use the
      <parameter>LABEL="..."</parameter> syntax in the first column.</para>

      <programlisting>/dev/sda1  /boot    ext2  noauto,noatime    0 0
/dev/sda2  /        ext3  defaults,noatime  0 0
/dev/sda3  /home    ext3  defaults,noatime  0 0
/dev/sda4  none     swap  sw                0 0
none       /dev/shm tmpfs defaults          0 0</programlisting>

      <para>Next, configure your network settings. Start by setting the system
      host name in <filename>/etc/conf.d/hostname</filename> and then
      configure the networking settings in
      <filename>/etc/conf.d/net</filename>. Finally, add your network
      interface initialization script to the default run level so that
      networking is automatically started at boot time.</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>nano -w /etc/conf.d/hostname</command>
~# <command>nano -w /etc/conf.d/net</command>
~# <command>rc-update add net.eth0 default</command></programlisting>

      <para>Also edit your <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file to include the
      IP addresses and host names of other systems you might need. Also add
      your host name to the 127.0.0.1 entry in
      <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>.</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>nano -w /etc/hosts</command></programlisting>

      <para>Now, set your root password</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>passwd</command></programlisting>

      <para>Next, edit <filename>/etc/rc.conf</filename> which contains your
      general system configuration settings:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>nano -w /etc/rc.conf</command></programlisting>

      <para>Next, edit <filename>/etc/conf.d/keymaps</filename> to set your
      system-wide keyboard layout settings:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>nano -w /etc/conf.d/keymaps</command></programlisting>

      <para>Finally, edit <filename>/etc/conf.d/clock</filename> to set the
      clock options:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>nano -w /etc/conf.d/clock</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing System Tools</title>

      <para>Install a system logger, like syslog-ng:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>emerge syslog-ng</command>
~# <command>rc-update add syslog-ng default</command></programlisting>

      <para>Install a system scheduler (cron daemon), like vixie-cron:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>emerge vixie-cron</command>
~# <command>rc-update add vixie-cron default</command></programlisting>

      <para>Install the file system tools for the file systems you use:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>emerge xfsprogs</command>
~# <command>emerge reiserfsprogs</command>
~# <command>emerge jfsutils</command></programlisting>

      <para>Install the necessary networking tools, like a DHCP client:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>emerge dhcpcd</command></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuring the Boot Loader</title>

    <para>Now, we install the GRUB boot loader (remember to use grub-static if
    you are using an amd64 (x86_64) system with no-multilib):</para>

    <programlisting>~# <command>emerge grub</command></programlisting>

    <para>Once installed, edit the grub configuration file
    (<filename>/boot/grub/grub.conf</filename>) as we've seen before. Finally,
    install GRUB on the master boot record:</para>

    <programlisting>~# <command>grep -v rootfs /proc/mounts &gt; /etc/mtab</command>
~# <command>grub-install --no-floppy /dev/sda</command></programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Finishing Up</title>

    <para>Now that everything is installed, reboot your system by exiting the
    chroot, umounting all mounted file systems and reboot:</para>

    <programlisting>~# <command>exit</command>
~# <command>cd</command>
~# <command>umount /mnt/gentoo/boot /mnt/gentoo/dev /mnt/gentoo/proc</command>
~# <command>umount /mnt/gentoo/home /mnt/gentoo</command>
~# <command>reboot</command></programlisting>

    <para>Once rebooted (and hopefully inside your Gentoo Linux environment),
    log in as root and create a user for daily use:</para>

    <programlisting>~# <command>useradd -m -G users,wheel,audio -s /bin/bash yournick</command>
~# <command>passwd yournick</command></programlisting>

    <para>And to remove the traces from the installation, remove the
    downloaded tarballs from your / file system:</para>

    <programlisting>~# <command>rm /stage3-*.tar.bz2</command>
~# <command>rm /portage-*.tar.bz2</command></programlisting>
  </section>
</chapter>
