<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Taking Backups</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>To finalize this book, lets focus on backups and restores. After
    all, you don't want to put all that effort in your Linux system, only to
    see it vanish with the next power surge or
    daughter-spilled-milk-over-my-laptop incident.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Poor Man's Backup</title>

    <para>Not taking any backups is living on the edge. Especially in case of
    Gentoo Linux, you don't want to lose all the effort you've put in setting
    up your system. A basic, poor man's backup, is nothing more but an
    off-line copy of your important files. This can be on a USB stick, an SD
    card or a CD/DVD. But what to backup?</para>

    <para>The following sections describe a possible set of files and
    directories to back up, without resorting to lots and lots of storage
    requirements.</para>

    <section>
      <title>System Settings</title>

      <para>First of all, take a copy of your <filename>/etc</filename>
      folder. The <filename>/etc</filename> directory contains all system
      settings, including your file system table (<filename>fstab</filename>),
      Portage-specific settings (<filename>/etc/make.conf</filename>,
      <filename>/etc/portage</filename>), service configuration files (in
      <filename>/etc/conf.d</filename> and <filename>/etc/env.d</filename>),
      ... Really, this location is not to be forgotten.</para>

      <para>Next, there are a few non-/etc files or directories that you want
      to copy as well.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>/var/lib/portage/world</filename> is your
          world-file, which contains a list of all software you've installed
          (well, not their dependencies, but that's not needed anyhow). In
          case that you ever need to rebuild your system, this file will tell
          you what needs to be installed</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>/usr/local</filename> contains all non-Portage
          installed software and settings. Although you might not have
          anything inside that, those of you that do will most likely take a
          backup of that as well.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>/proc/config.gz</filename> (or
          <filename>/usr/src/linux/.config</filename>) is your kernel
          configuration. You've probably lost a lot of sweat and oxygen while
          setting up your kernel configuration, so you definitely don't want
          to lose it</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>User Settings</title>

      <para>Next to the system settings, you'll find that your end user(s) on
      your system also have gone through lots of trouble to set up their
      system as they want it. End users' configuration settings are stored in
      the end users' home directories. There is no single directory for all
      configuration settings, so finding which ones to back up and which not
      might be difficult. However, one way that works for me (and which
      usually doesn't include the end users' personal files) is to backup all
      <filename>${HOME}/.??*</filename> files and directories. Most
      configuration directories (or files) are hidden files (i.e. starting
      with a period).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sample Script</title>

      <para>The following command will make an archive of the above mentioned
      settings.</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>tar cvzpf /var/tmp/poormanbackup.tar.gz /etc /var/lib/portage/world /usr/local /proc/config.gz /home/*/.??*</command></programlisting>

      <para>Again, this is just a poor man's backup, because it is not really
      managed, but it is still better than nothing. Make sure you copy the
      poormanbackup.tar.gz to a safe(r) place. Note that it will still be
      fairly large, because of the end user copy (as it contains lots of
      software caches, like your browsers' cache). If you drop the end user
      directories (the <filename>/home/*/.??*</filename>) the file is reduced
      from many dozens (up to hundreds) of megabytes down to about half a
      megabyte.</para>

      <para>To restore files, get the file on your system (mount the USB
      stick/CD) and extract the file(s) you need. For instance, to extract all
      <filename>/etc/portage/*</filename> files:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>tar xvzpf /media/usb/poormanbackup.tar.gz -C / etc/portage</command></programlisting>

      <para>Note the space between <filename>/</filename> and
      <filename>etc/portage</filename>!</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>More Managed Backups</title>

    <para>A slightly more complicated, but probably safer method, is to use
    tools that provide you with a managed backup solution. Managed means that
    you tell them what to backup (although they do propose certain backup
    situations) and they take care of the rest, such as repetitive backups, as
    well as easy restore activities in case things go wrong.</para>

    <para>If you take a look at the packages that Gentoo offers in its
    app-backup category, you'll find that there are plenty of them. I can't
    tell you which one is better, because that is a personal taste. But I will
    provide a few pointers so you can get started.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Backup Ninja</title>

      <para>The backupninja application is a tool which is scheduled to run
      every night (for instance) and that will read in the configuration
      file(s) in /etc/backup.d. Inside this directory, you define what needs
      to be backed up, how often, etc. For instance, the same poor man's
      backup settings of above would result in a file similar to the
      following:</para>

      <para>File <filename>/etc/backup.d/20-basic-system.rdiff</filename> to
      backup regular files:</para>

      <programlisting>when = daily
options = --exclude-special-files
nicelevel = 15

[source]
label = myhostname.mydomain
type = local
keep = 60
include = /etc
include = /var/lib/portage/world
include = /usr/local
include = /home/*/.??*
exclude = /home/*/.mozilla/firefox/*.default/Cache

[dest]
type = local
directory = /var/backups/backupninja</programlisting>

      <para>File
      <filename>/etc/backup.d/19-kernel-config.sh</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting>zcat /proc/config.gz &gt; /etc/kernel-config</programlisting>

      <para>File <filename>/etc/backup.d/21-copy-to-usb.sh</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting>rsync -avug /var/backups/backupninja /media/usb</programlisting>

      <para>The result of this is that the kernel configuration file is
      generated first (into /etc/kernel-config) after which (incremental)
      backups are taken of the presented locations, and stored in
      /var/backups/backupninja. Finally, these files are copied (synchronized)
      to /media/usb (which might be a USB stick or external disk drive). If
      you ever want to store that backup outside of your home (for instance,
      at your parents/kids house), detach the USB stick and store it there.
      Just make sure another USB stick is attached and mounted for the next
      backup cycle.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Bare Metal Recovery</title>

    <para>When you want to make sure your system is up and running in no time,
    even when the entire system crashed, you need to take bare metal backups
    (full system backups) which you can restore quickly. A popular method to
    accomplish this is to use imaging software tools.</para>

    <section>
      <title>PartImage</title>

      <para>If you installed Gentoo using the sysresccd CD, then you already
      have the tools at your disposal to perform imaging backups. A popular
      tool is <emphasis>PartImage</emphasis><indexterm>
          <primary>PartImage</primary>
        </indexterm>, and is available on the sysresccd.</para>

      <para>The tool offers a graphical (or curses) based interface, but you
      don't need to use that: the tool also supports command-line
      backups.</para>

      <para>An example usage would be the following. Boot from the sysresccd,
      and attach USB storage to your system on which you want to back up your
      entire system:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>mount /dev/sdc1 /media/usb</command></programlisting>

      <para>Next, take image(s) of your partitions, or take a full disk
      backup. Don't worry, PartImage is able to detect when disk space isn't
      used, and will skip those empty blocks. The following takes a full
      backup of /dev/sda in blocks of 700Mbyte (in case you ever want to store
      the files on CD or DVD):</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>partimage -b -z1 -o V700 save /dev/sda /media/usb/gentoo_full.sda.partimg.gz</command></programlisting>

      <para>If you ever need to restore the system, use the following
      command:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>partimage -e restore /dev/sda /media/usb/gentoo_full.sda.partimg.gz.000</command></programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Stage4/5/... Installation</title>

      <para>Specifically for Gentoo, some users have created enhancements on
      top of the standard "stage3" installation used by Gentoo Linux. With
      stage4 or stage5 installations, the extracted tarball is a lot larger
      (it contains almost an entire system) and might be accompanied with
      additional script(s) that set up or recover the system. These scripts
      can, for instance, restore your partition layout, reformat the
      partitions, reinstall the bootloader, etc.</para>

      <para>Compared with the poor man's backup approach described above, this
      can be seen as a "entire system poor man's backup", with
      optionally</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Backup &amp; restore of the master boot record and partition
          table</para>

          <programlisting>(Backup)
dd if=/dev/sda of=/media/usb/full-stage-backup/mbr.img bs=512 count=1
sfdisk -d /dev/sda &gt; /media/usb/full-stage-backup/sfdisk.dat

(Restore)
dd if=/media/usb/full-stage-backup/mbr.img of=/dev/sda
sfdisk /dev/sda &lt; /media/usb/full-stage-backup/sfdisk.dat</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Restoration of the boot loader</para>

          <programlisting>(Restore: command after restoring /boot content)
grub-install --root-directory=/mnt/gentoo/boot /dev/hda</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Reformatting of partitions (be carefull here, this is very
          error-prone and specific for your system)</para>

          <programlisting>(Backup)
mount | grep -v 'dev/mapper' | grep -v 'dev/md' | grep 'type ext' | awk -F' ' '{print "mkfs."$5" "$1}' &gt; /media/usb/full-stage-backup/reformat.sh

(Restore)
/media/usb/full-stage-backup/reformat.sh</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>I personally prefer imaging software for such large recovery
      scenarios. However, such stage4/stage5 installations prove to be useful
      when you migrate your system from one disk to another. Using imaging
      tools might fail here, because they often require that the target hard
      disk is equally sized, whereas you probably want to migrate to a larger
      disk.</para>

      <para>So, if you are interested in a stage4 or stage5 backup/restore,
      you can take one from a running system or booted from a livecd. I
      suggest using a livecd (or other live environment) as that will ensure
      that the restore of the archive will give you a sane situation. If you
      take such an archive while running inside the system itself, you will
      also copy state files and other files that should not be there when a
      system is being booted.</para>

      <para>Mount your file systems (say at <filename>/mnt/gentoo</filename>)
      except for the dynamically created ones (like proc, dev, sys, ...).
      Then, run the following <command>tar</command> command to create the
      archive:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>tar -cvzpf /media/usb/backup/stage4.tar.gz --numeric-owner --strip-components=2 /mnt/gentoo</command></programlisting>

      <para>The <option>--numeric-owner</option> will ensure that uid/gid
      numbers are used rather than names, because the live environment can use
      different name/id pairs than your own system. By using
      <option>--strip-components=2</option>, all files are stored in the
      archive without the leading "<filename>/mnt/gentoo</filename>".</para>

      <para>If you need to put back the backup, you can recreate your
      partitions (or create new ones), mount them somewhere (say
      <filename>/mnt/gentoo</filename> again) and run:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>tar xvzpf /media/usb/backup/stage4.tar.gz -C /mnt/gentoo</command></programlisting>

      <para>Don't forget to reinstall the boot loader before you
      reboot!</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
