<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Using A Shell</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>As the Linux basics have been unfolded in the previous chapters, I
    want to close off this book with an introduction to shell scripting. Shell
    scripting is one of Linux' (and Unix) powerful features. It allows you to
    automate various tasks and is often used to help you manage your system.
    One of Linux' main principles is "keep it simple", and by providing simple
    tools that do simple jobs (but do them well) you can build powerful
    systems. The downside of simple tools is that you need plenty of them to
    do certain tasks, and shell scripts help you glue together these various
    tools.</para>

    <para>Before we launch off our shell scripting, we need to cover a few
    basic items of running commands in Linux first. Some of them have been
    described earlier in this book so it might not seem too unfamiliar for
    most of you.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Chaining Commands</title>

    <section>
      <title>Running Multiple Commands</title>

      <para>When you are inside a shell, you can run one or more commands
      after another. We have seen such use cases previously, for instance to
      view the content of a directory and then go inside a
      subdirectory:</para>

      <programlisting>~$ <command>mkdir Documents</command>
~$ <command>cd Documents</command></programlisting>

      <para>In the previous example, multiple commands are ran as single
      commands one after another. But with a shell, you can execute multiple
      on a single line. To do so, you separate the commands with a
      semicolon:</para>

      <programlisting>~$ <command>mkdir Documents; cd Documents</command></programlisting>

      <para>You can add as many commands as you want. The shell will execute
      each command when the previous one has finished. For instance:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>emerge --sync; layman -S; emerge -uDN @world; revdep-rebuild -p</command></programlisting>

      <para>is the equivalent of</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>emerge --sync</command>
~# <command>layman -S</command>
~# <command>emerge -uDN @world</command>
~# <command>revdep-rebuild -p</command></programlisting>

      <para>Nothing too powerful about that, but wait, there's more. Commands
      in a Unix environment always finish with a particular return code. This
      return code tells whomever called the command if the command exited
      successfully (return code is 0) or not (return code is not 0) and why
      not. This return code, as you might have guessed, is an integer, usually
      within the range of 0...255. You can see the return code of a command by
      showing the special shell variable <varname>$?</varname><indexterm>
          <primary>$?</primary>
        </indexterm> (which can be done using <command>echo</command>). Let's
      see a simple example:</para>

      <programlisting>~$ <command>ls</command>
Documents     tasks.txt     bookmarks.html
~$ <command>echo $?</command>
0
~$ <command>ls -z</command>
ls: invalid option -- 'z'
Try 'ls --help' for more information
~$ <command>echo $?</command>
2</programlisting>

      <section>
        <title>Conditional Execution</title>

        <para>The use of return codes allows us to investigate conditional
        execution. For instance, you want to update Portage and then update
        your system, but the latter should only start if the update of Portage
        finished successfully. If you run commands manually, you would wait
        for the Portage update to finish, look at its output, and then decide
        to continue with the update or not. By making use of the return code
        of emerge --sync; we can run the following command only if the
        synchronization finished with return code 0. Using shell scripting,
        you can use <parameter>&amp;&amp;</parameter><indexterm>
            <primary>&amp;&amp;</primary>
          </indexterm> as separator between such commands.</para>

        <programlisting>~# <command>emerge --sync &amp;&amp; emerge -uDN @world</command></programlisting>

        <para>By using <parameter>&amp;&amp;</parameter>, you instruct the
        shell only to execute the following command if the previous one is
        successful. Now what about when the command finishes with an
        error?</para>

        <para>Well, the shell offers the <parameter>||</parameter> separator
        to chain such commands. Its use is less pertinent in regular shell
        operations, but more in shell scripts (for instance for error
        handling). Yet, it is still useful for regular shell operations, as
        the following (perhaps too simple, yet explanatory) example
        shows:</para>

        <programlisting>~$ <command>mount /media/usb || sudo mount /media/usb</command></programlisting>

        <para>The command sequence tries to mount the /media/usb location. If
        for any reason this fails (for instance, because the user does not
        have the rights to mount), retry but using
        <command>sudo</command>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Input &amp; Output</title>

        <para>Now on to another trick that we have seen before: working with
        output and input. I already explained that we can chain multiple
        simple tools to create a more useful, complex activity. One of the
        most often used chaining methods is to use the output of one command
        as the input of another. This is especially useful for text searching
        and manipulation. Say you want to know the last 5 applications that
        were installed on your system. There are many methods possible to do
        this, one of them is using /var/log/emerge.log (which is where all
        such activity is logged). You could just open the logfile, scroll to
        the end and work backwards to get to know the last 5 installed
        applications, or you can use a command like so:</para>

        <programlisting>~$ <command>grep 'completed emerge' /var/log/emerge.log | tail -5</command>
1283033552:   ::: completed emerge (1 of 1) app-admin/cvechecker-0.5 to /
1283033552:   ::: completed emerge (1 of 3) dev-perl/HTML-Tagset-3.20 to /
1283033552:   ::: completed emerge (2 of 3) dev-perl/MP3-Info-1.23 to /
1283033552:   ::: completed emerge (3 of 3) app-pda/gnupod-0.99.8 to /
1283033552:   ::: completed emerge (1 of 1) app-admin/cvechecker-0.5 to /</programlisting>

        <para>What happened is that we first executed grep, to filter out
        specific string patterns out of /var/log/emerge.log. In this case,
        grep will show us all lines that have "completed emerge" in them. Yet,
        the question was not to show all installations, but the last five. So
        we <emphasis>piped</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>pipe</primary>
          </indexterm> the output (that's how this is called) to the
        <command>tail</command><indexterm>
            <primary>tail</primary>
          </indexterm> application, whose sole task is to show the last N
        lines of its input.</para>

        <para>Of course, this can be extended to more and more applications or
        tools. What about the following example:</para>

        <programlisting>~$ <command>tail -f /var/log/emerge.log | grep 'completed emerge' | awk '{print $8}'</command>
app-admin/cvechecker-9999
dev-perl/libwww-perl-5.836
...</programlisting>

        <para>In this example, <command>tail</command> will "follow"
        <filename>emerge.log</filename> as it grows. Every line that is added
        to <filename>emerge.log</filename> is shown by
        <command>tail</command>. This output is piped to
        <command>grep</command>, which filters out all lines but those
        containing the string 'completed emerge'. The results of the
        <command>grep</command> operation is then piped to the
        <command>awk</command> application which prints out the 8th field
        (where white space is a field separator), which is the
        category/package set. This allows you to follow a lengthy emerge
        process without having to keep an eye on the entire output of
        <command>emerge</command>.</para>

        <para>The | sign passes through the standard output of a process. If
        you want to have the standard error messages passed through as well,
        you need to redirect that output (stderr) to the standard output
        first. This is accomplished using the "2&gt;&amp;1" suffix:</para>

        <programlisting>~# <command>emerge -uDN @world 2&gt;&amp;1 | grep 'error: '</command></programlisting>

        <para>In the above example, all lines (including those on standard
        error) will be filtered out, except those having the "error: " string
        in them. But what is that magical suffix?</para>

        <para>Well, standard output, standard error and actually also standard
        input are seen by Unix as files, but special files: you can't see them
        when the application has finished. When an application has a file
        open, it gets a <emphasis>file descriptor</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>file descriptor</primary>
          </indexterm> assigned. This is a number that uniquely identifies a
        file for a specific application. The file descriptors 0, 1 and 2 are
        reserved for standard input, standard output and standard error
        output.</para>

        <para>The 2&gt;&amp;1 suffix tells Unix/Linux that the file descriptor
        2 (standard error) should be redirected (&gt;) to file descriptor 1
        (&amp;1).</para>

        <para>This also brings us to the redirection sign: &gt;. If you want
        the output of a command to be saved in a file, you can use the
        redirect sign (&gt;) to redirect the output into a file:</para>

        <programlisting>~# <command>emerge -uDN @world &gt; /var/tmp/emerge.log</command></programlisting>

        <para>The above command will redirect all standard output to
        /var/tmp/emerge.log (i.e. save the output into a file). Note that this
        will not store the error messages on standard error in the file:
        because we did not redirect the standard error output, it will still
        be displayed on-screen. If we want to store that output as well, we
        can either store it in the same file:</para>

        <programlisting>~# <command>emerge -uDN @world &gt; /var/tmp/emerge.log 2&gt;&amp;1 </command></programlisting>

        <para>or store it in a different file:</para>

        <programlisting>~# <command>emerge -uDN @world &gt; /var/tmp/emerge.log 2&gt; /var/tmp/emerge-errors.log</command></programlisting>

        <para>Now there is one thing you need to be aware: the redirection
        sign needs to be directly attached to the output file descriptor, so
        it is "2&gt;" and not "2 &gt;" (with a space). In case of standard
        output, this is implied (&gt; is actually the same as 1&gt;).</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Grouping Commands</title>

      <para>Shells also offer a way to group commands. If you do this, it is
      said that you create a sub-shell that contains the commands you want to
      execute. Now why would this be interesting?</para>

      <para>Well, suppose that you want to update your system, followed by an
      update of the file index. You don't want them to be ran simultaneously
      as that would affect performance too much, but you also don't want this
      to be done in the foreground (you want the shell free to do other
      stuff). We have seen that you can background processes by appending a "
      &amp;" at the end:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>emerge -uDN @world &gt; emerge-output.log 2&gt;&amp;1 &amp;</command></programlisting>

      <para>However, chaining two commands together with the background sign
      is not possible:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>emerge -uDN @world &gt; emerge-output.log 2&gt;&amp;1 &amp;; updatedb &amp;</command>
bash: syntax error near unexpected token ';'</programlisting>

      <para>If you drop the ";" from the command, both processes will run
      simultaneously. The grouping syntax comes to the rescue:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>(emerge -uDN @world &gt; emerge-output.log 2&gt;&amp;1; updatedb) &amp;</command></programlisting>

      <para>This also works for output redirection:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>(emerge --sync; layman -S) &gt; sync-output.log 2&gt;&amp;1</command></programlisting>

      <para>The above example will update the Portage tree and the overlays,
      and the output of both commands will be redirected to the
      <filename>sync-output.log</filename> file.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Storing Commands</title>

      <para>All the above examples are examples that are run live from your
      shell. You can however write commands in a text file and execute this
      text file. The advantage is that the sequence of commands is manageable
      (if you make a mistake, you edit the file), somewhat documented for the
      future (how did I do that again?) and easier to use (just a single file
      to execute rather than a sequence of commands).</para>

      <para>A text file containing all this information is called a shell
      script. As an- example, the following text file will load in the
      necessary virtualisation modules, configure a special network device
      that will be used to communicate with virtual runtimes, enable a virtual
      switch between the virtual runtimes and the host system (the one where
      the script is ran) and finally enables rerouting of network packages so
      that the virtual runtimes can access the Internet:</para>

      <programlisting>modprobe tun
modprobe kvm-intel
tunctl -b -u swift -t tap0
ifconfig tap0 192.168.100.1 up
vde_switch --numports 4 --hub --mod 770 --group users --tap tap0 -d
echo 1 &gt; /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
iptables --flush
iptables -A POSTROUTING -t nat -o eth0 -j MASQUERADE
iptables -A FORWARD -i tap0 -o eth0 -s 192.168.100.1/24 ! -d 192.168.100.1/24 -j ACCEPT
iptables -A FORWARD -o tap0 -i eth0 -d 192.168.100.1/24 ! -s 192.168.100.1/24 -j ACCEPT</programlisting>

      <para>Can you imagine having to retype all that (let alone on a single
      command line, separated with ;)</para>

      <para>To execute the script, give it an appropriate name (say
      "enable_virt_internet"), mark it as executable, and execute it:</para>

      <programlisting>~# <command>chmod +x enable_virt_internet</command>
~# <command>./enable_virt_internet</command></programlisting>

      <para>Note that we start the command using "./", informing Linux that we
      want to execute the file that is stored in the current working
      directory.</para>

      <para>Now on to the advantages of using shell scripts even
      more...</para>

      <section>
        <title>Documenting</title>

        <para>You can easily document your steps in shell scripts. A comment
        starts with #, like so:</para>

        <programlisting># Load in virtualisation modules
modprobe tun
modprobe kvm-intel
# Setup special networking device for communicating with the virtual environments
tunctl -b -u swift -t tap0
ifconfig tap0 192.168.100.1 up
vde_switch --numports 4 --hub --mod 770 --group users --tap tap0 -d
# Enable IP forwarding
echo 1 &gt; /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
# Set up "internet sharing" by allowing package forwarding towards the Internet
iptables --flush
iptables -A POSTROUTING -t nat -o eth0 -j MASQUERADE
iptables -A FORWARD -i tap0 -o eth0 -s 192.168.100.1/24 ! -d 192.168.100.1/24 -j ACCEP;
iptables -A FORWARD -o tap0 -i eth0 -d 192.168.100.1/24 ! -s 192.168.100.1/24 -j ACCEPT</programlisting>

        <para>Comments can also be added at the end of a line, btw.</para>

        <para>Another, special, comment, is one that tells your operating
        system how the shell script should be called. There are plenty of
        shells in Linux (bash, bsh, zsh, csh, ...) and there are even
        scripting languages that also use text files for their content (perl,
        python, ruby, ...). Linux does not use file extensions to know how to
        execute or interpret a file. To help Linux determine the correct
        execution environment, we add a special comment at the beginning of
        the file (this must be the first line of the script), in this case to
        inform Linux that this is a bash shell script:</para>

        <programlisting>#!/bin/sh
# Load in virtualisation modules
modprobe tun
...</programlisting>

        <para>This line is quite important, and should always start with #!
        (also called the <emphasis>shebang</emphasis><indexterm>
            <primary>shebang</primary>
          </indexterm>) followed by the interpreter (/bin/bash in our
        case).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Introduce Loops, Conditionals, ...</title>

        <para>A shell script like the above is still quite simple, but also
        error-prone. If you had your share of issues / incidents with that
        script, you will most likely start adding error conditions inside
        it.</para>

        <para>First, make sure that we are root. We can verify this by reading
        the special variable $UID (a read-only variable giving the user id of
        the user executing the script):</para>

        <programlisting>#!/bin/sh

if [ $UID -ne 0 ];
then
  echo "Sorry, this file needs to be executed as root!"
  exit 1;
fi

# Load in virtualisation modules
...</programlisting>

        <para>The [[ ... ]] set is a test operator. It gives a return code of
        0 (statement is true) or non-zero (statement is false). The if ...
        then ... fi statement is a conditional which is executed when the test
        operator returns true (0). Although [[ ... ]] seems strange, this is
        nothing more than a command (actually, "[" is the command). But don't
        let that confuse you ;-)</para>

        <para>Next, we introduce a loop:</para>

        <programlisting># Load in virtualisation modules
for MODULE in tun kvm-intel;
do
  modprobe $MODULE
done</programlisting>

        <para>What the loop does is create a variable called
        <varname>MODULE</varname>, and give it as content first "tun" and then
        "kvm-intel". The shell expands the loop as follows:</para>

        <programlisting>MODULE="tun"
modprobe $MODULE     # So "modprobe tun"
MODULE="kvm-intel"
modprobe $MODULE     # So "modprobe kvm-intel"</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Introduce Functions</title>

        <para>You can even made the script more readable by introducing
        special functions.</para>

        <programlisting>...

# This is a function definition. It is not executed at this point.
load_modules() {
  for MODULE in tun kvm-intel;
  do
    modprobe $MODULE
  done
}

setup_networking() {
  tunctl -b -u swift -t tap0
  ifconfig tap0 192.168.100.1 up
  vde_switch --numports 4 --hub --mod 770 --group users --tap tap0 -d
  echo 1 &gt; /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
}

share_internet() {
  iptables --flush
  iptables -A POSTROUTING -t nat -o eth0 -j MASQUERADE
  iptables -A FORWARD -i tap0 -o eth0 -s 192.168.100.1/24 ! -d 192.168.100.1/24 -j ACCEP;
  iptables -A FORWARD -o tap0 -i eth0 -d 192.168.100.1/24 ! -s 192.168.100.1/24 -j ACCEPT
}

# Only now are the functions called (and executed)
load_modules
setup_networking
share_internet</programlisting>

        <para>Functions are often used to help with error handling routines.
        Say that we want the script to stop the moment an error has occurred,
        and give a nice error message about it:</para>

        <programlisting>...

die() {
  echo $* &gt;&amp;2;
  exit 1;
}

load_modules() {
  for MODULE in tun kvm-intel;
  do
    modprobe $MODULE || die "Failed to load in module $MODULE";
  done
}
...</programlisting>

        <para>If at any time the modprobe fails, a nice error message will
        occur, like so:</para>

        <programlisting>~# <command>./enable_virt_internet</command>
Failed to load in module tun
~# </programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Advanced Shell Scripting</title>

    <para>The above is just for starters. Much more advanced shell scripting
    is possible - shells nowadays have so many features that some scripts are
    even disclosed as full applications. You will be surprised how many
    scripts you have on your system. Just for starters, in /usr/bin:</para>

    <programlisting>~$ <command>file * | grep -c 'ELF '</command>
1326
~$ <command>file * | grep -c script</command>
469</programlisting>

    <para>So in my /usr/bin folder, I have 1326 binary applications, but also
    469 scripts. That is more than one third of the number of binary
    applications!</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Want more?</title>

    <para>This is as far as I want to go with a book targeting Linux starters.
    You should now have enough luggage to make it through various online
    resources and other books, and still have a reference at your disposal for
    your day-to-day activities on your (Gentoo) Linux system.</para>

    <para>I would like to thank you for reading this document, and if you have
    any particular questions or feedback, please don't hesitate to contact me
    at <email>sven.vermeulen@siphos.be</email> or on the Freenode and OFTC IRC
    networks (my nickname is SwifT).</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
